<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-23T05:58:22-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">State of the Tenor and Love Coffee</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/state-of-the-tenor-love-coffee" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="State of the Tenor and Love Coffee" /><published>2021-01-23T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/State-of-the-Tenor-Love-Coffee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/state-of-the-tenor-love-coffee">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-01-23-State-of-the-Tenor-Love-Coffee.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AdTFoK7NZmU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we make use of my brand new KaffeBox subscription. For those that do not know KaffeBox are based in Norway and do a subscription service sourcing coffees from the best roasters in Scandanavia. You can read more about them &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaffebox.no/scandinavian-nordic-roast-coffee-subscription/&quot;&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt; Unfortunately due to the christmas period, Covid lockdowns and Brexit delays these coffees arrived to me a little late (roast date 26th November) - so I'm taking this in mind in this review. While the 8 or so weeks is not very old for a coffee (especially for a light filter roast) the flavours might pop a little more if I'd had them a little earlier. And to be perfectly clear, this is not KaffeBox's fault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee themselves is from a roaster in Lund, Sweden called &quot;Love Coffee&quot;. This roaster is completely new to me, I have never tried their coffee before (at least I can't remember if I have). The first thing that strikes me is the packaging, which is very nice. The bag features a black and white cartoon of a coffee shop on the front and a roaster on the back. It's always nice to see roasters put some effort into their packaging designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/040-State-of-the-Tenor/Love-Coffee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/lovecoffeelund&quot;&gt;https://www.instagram.com/lovecoffeelund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case I recieved 2 smaller 125g bags of coffee: one being a washed Colombian 'La Esperanza' and a natural Ethiopian 'Buku'. These are very &quot;classic&quot; origins and processing methods so a good introduction to a new roaster. I used both of these coffees as espresso exclusively (as I was using last week's Plot ICON as my filter alongside them) - so filter fans will need to wait until next week for their fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the Colombian La Esperanza. The farm is located in Nariño, Colobmbia - a location I'm not overly familiar with. It is a washed coffee that is made up of at least 70% of the &quot;yellow Colombia&quot; varietal - as the name suggests a yellow cherry fruit. I can't really find much more information on this one so let's dive straight into the espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is often the case on this blog we are making espresso with &quot;filter&quot; roasts which tend to be quite light. This can often make the dialing in process fiddly. However, in this case it was very easy. The coffee was extremely forgiving with my setup. I found that it actually liked to be around a 1:2 ratio with a fairly ordinary recipe. This accentuates the natural body and mouthfeel in this coffee and is more pleasant to drink. In the flavour notes I got a very nutty quality underlying some top notes of a sweet red apple. The sweetness is fairly high and the acidity muted in this one. This is the sort of coffee that is a pleasure to drink, you don't have to think about it too muich and it just leaves you satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we have the Ethiopian Buku. This coffee takes its name from the washing station where the coffee was processed. The station is located in the Guji zone in the southern part of the country - an area very familiar to those who have read some of my previous postings. The varietals are listed as &quot;heirloom&quot; which is something we have covered in the past so I will not re-tread old ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one was not quite as easy to dial in as the Colombian, but it was not particularly difficult either. Pulling the shots too short introduced a bit of harshness in the finish so I pulled slightly longer to around 1:2.25 in the end. There is plenty of natural sweetness and the acidity is not too high so there was not a huge benefit in pulling any longer than this. This coffee absolutely loves high temperatures though and I had to set my machine to its hottest setting for optimal results. This results in an intensely perfumed cup, I get strong notes of lavendar and bergamot first and foremost. This is combined with the &quot;bruised blueberry&quot; note you often get with a natural Guji. On the funk-o-meter it is fairly low however, it is refined and fairly clean tasting. There is some body in the cup but it is not a &quot;huge&quot; coffee. I found this coffee really enjoyable, these highly perfumed coffees are my favourite ones to use as an espresso so this one was a lot of fun, I wish I had a bit more of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a strong showing from Love Coffee, a roaster I'll certainly keep an eye out for in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I have been listening to the live double album from Joe Henderson: &quot;State of the Tenor&quot; recorded at the Village Vanguard in 1985 and released in 1986 on Blue Note Records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/040-State-of-the-Tenor/State-of-the-Tenor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally this album was released as 2 seperate LPs: &quot;State of the Tenor Vol. 1&quot; and &quot;State of the Tenor Vol. 2&quot; - but subsequently were combined into a double LP. There are so many stellar tunes on this album perhaps I could have seperated them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mid 80s jazz was in a bit of a funny place. At this point fusion was really the &quot;hip&quot; thing to be playing (although that trend in itself was coming to an end) and playing more straight ahead was considered a bit dull and boring. I consider &quot;State of the Tenor&quot; to be Joe throwing down the gauntlet and showing just how creative you can be with a basic acoustic trio of: tenor, bass and drums. The original liner notes to the album states that the recorded concerts were effectivly &quot;saxaphone lessons&quot; owing to the sheer number of sax players in attendence.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P4sA09U-8Og&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

I am a huge Joe Henderson fan, I make no apologies about this. He features regularly on this blog as a result. For me he is, perhaps, the greatest improviser of all time. Some players can play flashier more complicated lines and others may play with a bigger rounder sax sound but Joe captures &quot;something&quot; when he's improvising. In terms of lineage he is clearly in the Sonny Rollins school first and foremost, their playing is quite similar in many regards (even the trio format on this album is something you could link back to Rollins). But Joe takes it a step further, he will stray further &quot;outside&quot; than Rollins ever will. Not only will he play outside harmony we will stray outside in his timing also. His &quot;natural&quot; rhythmic device is to lead the band, it almost feels as if he is pulling the other band members along at times. For effect he'll also play really loose and instinctively, the timing of his lines doesn't &quot;fit&quot; in the true sense but it works because of the overall mood he manages to create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then of course we have Henderson's virtuosity. John Coltrane is often a name synonymous with tenor virtuosity, he plays incredibly fast and harmonically complicated lines (at least before his modal/spiritual journey). These lines all fall relatively comfortably under the fingers however, it still requires immense practice to play that way but the lines usually feel &quot;comfortable&quot;. In contrast some of the lines Joe plays are hideous under the fingers, for anybody but Joe they feel wrong and unintuitive. He might not (often) reach Coltrane's break neck speeds but I argue these lines are way more difficult to play, especially the way Joe does with the odd note groupings and accents. You sometimes here others try and play &quot;Henderson licks&quot; but they are never that convincing nor sound as fluid as Joe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album itself features a combination of Henderson originals and standards by the likes of Parker, Silver, Mingus and Ellington. The album opens with &quot;Beatrice&quot; penned by Sam Rivers (embedded at the start of this post). Continuing the theme of &quot;jazz education&quot; I've always felt that this take was a heavy influence on some of the current crop of tenor players; most notably JD Allen - on many of his albums I notice bass/sax interplay that always makes me think of this take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also worth noting the rest of the cast on this album. On the bass we have Ron Carter - even trying to summarise his recorded output would take up multiple blog posts. Not much more needs to be said about Ron, definitely a legend and one of the greatest bass players in the history of jazz. Rounding out the line-up is Al Foster on drums - again somebody who has played with just about anybody you care to mention. Overall an absolutely incredible line-up for a trio format, it would have been great to hear this band live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second track I picked for this post is &quot;Boo Boo's Birthday&quot; - a piece penned by Thelonious Monk (embedded above). Thelonious is clearly a big influence for Joe, his sense of timing can certainly be described as &quot;Monk-like&quot;. Of course, he also has the tune &quot;Isotope&quot; (originally on &quot;Inner Urge&quot; but a version also appears on this album) which he describes as a tribute to Monk. I find Monk tunes a great canvas for improvisers, the tunes are often very playful which helps the musicians relax. Jazz improvisation is often seen as very &quot;serious&quot; so it's nice to hear musicians having fun from time to time. Of course Monk's arrangements also tend to be quite spacious which allows for more experimentation.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8FvyANqV80g&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The last tune I want to highlight from this album (although they're all stellar) is the Henderson penned: &quot;Y Ya La Quiero&quot; (above). Continuing the theme of education and influence: to me it is clear to see how this influence Kenny Garrett in quite a profound way. When this was recorded Kenny would have just been starting his career and had not quite yet found his signature sound. His early to mid 90s sound is very reminiscent of this &quot;Y Ya La Quiero&quot; and I am always reminded of Kenny when this tune plays. As a Henderson tune it is a bit of an outlier, it is not what you would consider a &quot;typical&quot; arrangement for him which makes it quite a nice addition to this album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with most albums on this blog you really cannot go wrong with this one. My only slight complaint is that on some releases of this album the sound is all over the show, some tunes quiet some tunes really loud. I don't know exactly which releases are the ones to avoid (the &quot;bad&quot; version I had was on a CD) but it's worth keeping in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/040-State-of-the-Tenor/State-of-the-Tenor.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/040-State-of-the-Tenor/State-of-the-Tenor.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unity and Icon II</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/unity-icon-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unity and Icon II" /><published>2021-01-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Unity-Icon-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/unity-icon-2">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-01-16-Unity-Icon-2.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/K_4qxnyOf4s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are back looking at a very special coffee. Last month you may have remembered the Yemeni coffee from Plot Coffee Roasting - this was the first in a new coffee &quot;series&quot; called &quot;Icon&quot; offered by Plot. The idea being that the coffees offered represent the &quot;best of the best&quot; and some of the rarest coffees available. This week we have the second offering in this series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time the coffeee comers courtesy of Finca Monteblanco in Huila, Colombia. Huila is a relatively small department within Colombia located in the south-west region of the country. As a coffee producer Huila certainly punches above its weight however and you don't have to search very hard to find specialty coffee from the region. The farm is owned by Rodrigo Sanchez Valencia who inherited the farm from his grandfather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main areas of interest with this coffee: firstly the varietal is our old friend Gesha. The gesha varietal has appeared on the blog multiple times, it is currently the &quot;goose that lays golden eggs&quot; for specialty coffee. Simply having a Gesha coffee can leads to very high prices owing to the demand for the varietal. Whether this is a good thing or not is debatable. You may recall from previous blogs that you can trace the lineage of the Gesha back to Ethiopia, however its recently popularity is due to a farm called Hacienda La Esmeralda. In this case Rodrigo received Gesha seeds from a client in Panama which led to this weeks coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second area of interest for this coffee is the processing method. This method is the brainchild of Finca Monteblanco and has taken around 5 years to perfect. It is described as a &quot;cold fermentation&quot; process. The main steps of the process (after initial sorting) is to depulp the coffee and store them in bags within a temperature-stable cold room for 76 hours. The remaining pulp is then washed off and then the coffee dries for a total of 28 days. In terms of processing this is certianly a slow and relatively laborious method. By keeping the temperature low Rodrigo is able to control the fermentation and not let things get too funky, yet still allow flavour complexity to develop. Of course a process such as this increases the price of the coffee substaintially. To those new to specialty coffee (and even those well versed) - the price of the Icon series of coffees may seem excessive, but a huge amount of work goes into these coffees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive into the coffee proper: on the nose I don't get a huge hit of aroma. This is somewhat expected, Gesha varietals tend to be fairly polite and tend not to be flavour bombs. What you do notice though is sweet and stickly florals such as honeysuckle. Visually this coffee is roasted pretty light, as you'd want for a coffee like this - a heavy roast could mask the natural flavours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter this coffee makes an extremely elegant and refined cup. The first thing I noticed is just how clean the cup is, I usually buy cleaner tasting coffees but this is next level. The flavour profile is fairly muted, as you would expect with a Gesha. However there is a lot of complexity there, the main flavour notes for me are honeysuckle and white florals. Alongside delicate melon fruit like sweetness. As the cup cools the florals become more and more present and the aftertaste lingers that little bit longer. I wouldn't recommend this being served cold, but it certainly likes being drunk at a lower temperature than most. Since the cup is so clean you can get away with the lower temperature without getting too much bitterness. Overall the cup is very balanced erring slightly towards the sweeter side rather than the acidic side. There is not a big body or particularly big mouthfeel to the coffee but there is a certain &quot;stickyness&quot; to it which is very pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always with these high-end coffees that only come in &quot;small bags&quot; I did not intend to use them for espresso. With 150g of coffee you get very few chances to dial in, especially if you're also making filter coffees with them. This week however I did use these beans to make 1 espresso - purely by accident, I picked up the wrong bag after a long Zoom meeting when I was fairly tired. The coffee I had dialed in was also a Colombian to a similar roast level so it was not a million miles away but I still don't think it's fair to talk about this coffee too much as an espresso after one showing. The flavour notes were largely the same as with the filter, with no real suprises (other than my shock when I realised I'd used the wrong bag for espresso!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall another great Icon - looking forward to see what part 3 brings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we are looking at a coffee Icon it seems only fair to pair this with a jazz icon. In this case the 1966 album from Larry Young on Blue Note Records: Unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/039-Unity/Unity.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An absolutely iconic album from the Blue Note archives. Unity is possibly my favourite album cover of all the Blue Note album artwork - which is saying something when pretty much every one is a classic. Stylistically it is perfect, bold but not overbearing, simple but not boring. Even today this album cover does not look &quot;dated&quot;, it is hard to believe the artwork is now over 50 years old. This just goes to show what a genius Reid Miles was, without his contributions Blue Note may not have been the success it is today. Not only is the music fantastic and recorded well - the overall package and feel of these Blue Note records makes them feel special... Even if, in his own words, Reid Miles &quot;hated jazz&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a roll call of artists who appear on Unity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larry Young – Hammond B-3 organ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Woody Shaw – Trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Henderson – Tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elvin Jones – Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this alone you can see why this album is deserving of the &quot;Icon&quot; status I've given it. Truly an all-star cast - even at the time without the benefit of knowing what these guys did after Unity was released. We can also see that the line-up, interestingly, does not feature a bass player. This is very important for the sound and overall vibe of the album. Larry has to essentially take on the lower-frequency responsibility - often playing a strong groove to drive the music forward. This creates a rather large amount of space in the mix for the soloists. As a result the music is very experimental and ground-breaking. There are clear nods towards the free-jazz movement of Ornette, the post-bop work of Coltrane and the modal explorations of Davis - and I do not make comparisons to those artists lightly.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZXOOpc4OPfs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The use of organs in jazz has always been a bit of a contentious issue for some. The likes of Jimmy Smith and the soul-jazz kind of style heavily rooted in the blues can come across as a bit cornball for some. If this is a sentiment you share Unity is probably the best antidote. While the music is clearly centered around Young's organ sound, it couldn't be further from the soul-jazz sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with a piece penned by trumpet player Shaw called &quot;Zoltan&quot; (embedded at the start of the post). Interestingly enough; the lead artist Young does not have a single writing credit on the album. Zoltan starts off using the march from a Hungarian opera by Zoltán Kodály (no prizes for guessing the inspiration for the name of the piece). Soon after it descends into an exploration of the Lydian mode. The highlight of the tune for me is the incredible solo by Joe Henderson. Here he is at his best, playing &quot;just outside&quot; - it is not quite inside but neither is it full on free, at his best Joe finds that balance perfectly. If you're a fan of Joe's records Inner Urge, Mode for You or In 'n' Out you'll likely recognise some of the licks here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Joe, he also has a writing credit here with the tune &quot;If&quot; (above). This is the most hard-bop-y of all the tunes featured and is a typical Blue Note recording. It is perhaps the most simple tune and closest thing to &quot;straight ahead&quot;. Of course Elvin and Joe have played together many times and so have a near telepathic relationship. They keep the music driving forward and swinging hard, Elvin is in his absolute element here and shows why he is one of the all-time drumming greats. The use of an organ and no bass makes this piece particularly special however. Ordinarily you would expect the band to be rounded out with bass and piano, again the extra space allows the soloists complete freedom in where to go.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aB1H4dJVvvk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The album closes with &quot;Beyond All Limits&quot; another piece penned by Shaw. Harmonically it is the most complicated on the album and features some absolutely mind bending lines. Creating any sort of solo at all over these changes is difficult enough but Henderson, Shaw and Young make it sound easy. You can really hear each soloists personality shine through here: Larry Young's solo to cap off the tune is probably the highlight - as with any good solo he takes what others have played before him and expands upon it, making sure it builds to a crescendo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selecting just a few tracks from this album is difficult, every one is worthy of comment. We did not even touch on the 2 standards featured: Thelonious Monk's &quot;Monk's Dream&quot; and Hammerstein's &quot;Softly as a Morning Sunrise&quot;. I feel like I say this every week but it is especially relevant this week: this is an album worth hunting down and exploring in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post marks a bit of a milestone for jazz featuring on the blog. A few weeks ago I decided to start a Spotify playlist featuring all the music featured on this blog (you can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/3WjENhLmpWzdzlxhBxc7Fd?si=LtHGSnTgRu2zN7Uocdlcnw&quot;&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;) With the tunes in this blog post this playlist now has over 100 tunes and over 12 hours of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/039-Unity/Unity.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/039-Unity/Unity.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Jim Hall Live! and Finca Gascon</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/jim-hall-live-finca-gascon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jim Hall Live! and Finca Gascon" /><published>2021-01-09T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Jim-Hall-Live-Finca-Gascon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/jim-hall-live-finca-gascon">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-01-09-Jim-Hall-Live-Finca-Gascon.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qw9jPOUkiUs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are heading back to Brixton's finest: Assembly Coffee roasters. They are regular features on the blog for good reason, it is generally hard to pick a coffee any less than great from them. I'm sure they will crop up on the blog many times during 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee this week is from Guatemala. Surprisingly this is the first coffee from Guatemala to feature on the blog so far. I tend to find Guatemala to be a reliable origin and one I enjoy coming back to. I tend to find them to be extremely balanced and very easy to work with. They're not necessarily associated with the &quot;big&quot; flavours or &quot;wild&quot; tasting notes, but you don't always want that in a coffee. In the past few years I've noticed the quality of Guatemalan coffees going from strength to strength and hopefully they'll continue to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question is a washed processed orange bourbon. Orange bourbon is a natural hybrid between the red and yellow bourbon varieties - so named because of the colour of the coffee cherries. I consider the bourbon varietal to be the &quot;old reliable&quot; of the coffee world. There are newer sexier varietals that command the higher prices and esteem but I will always find myself going back to bourbons from time to time. Unfortunately bourbon is very suceptible to leaf rust and other diseases and pests, as a result many bourbon plants have been replaced by other varietals that are more robust in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving straight into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I get a caramel note and a faint hint of a fruitiness. It is not powerful on the nose however, it is not one that will blow your socks off. As I've noted previously this does not necessarily translate to flavours in the cup however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start with a filter coffee. The first word that comes to mind with this coffee is &quot;balanced&quot;. The acidity and sweetness is just so perfectly balanced, you have enough acidity to keep things interesting but it is not high acidity by any means. It is actually very easy to drink. In terms of flavour notes I think a crisp green apple is the best description. Assembly use the descriptors: &quot;Lemon Curd and Orange Zest&quot; - I can see what they're getting at with the brightness in the cup but for me it is more like biting into an apple. The sweetness takes the form of a caramel for me - perhaps even a toffee apple. There is a certain amount of mouthfeel and body to the cup, but it is more syrupy than heavy. My one slight negative about the cup is it doesn't cool down well for me, this is one you want to drink quite hot. However, it is so drinkable you'll unlikely have a cup sit around long enough to get to that level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso. The first thing to note is this one is an absolute dream to dial in, the sweet spot is huge and it's very difficult to go too far wrong. The roast level is fairly light but not excessively so, which I think helps the dialing in. I found that a standard 1:2 and 27s (after 7s pre-infuse) was about right to keep enough of the syrupy body. Given the balance of the coffee going longer doesn't help balance things out anymore. Going shorter to ristretto sort of levels can be nice but I found that the flavours get a little too muddled and I preferred the clarity in the standard ratio. One caveat however is the temperature: this coffee liked my machine to be essentially as hot as it could go. Dropping the temperature led to a slight sourness in the aftertaste which I didn't care for. When made in this way the shot was syrupy, balanced with just the right amount of acidity coming through. As with the filter crisp green apple and caramel were my main flavour notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall another solid showing from the folks at Assembly, worth picking up a bag if these flavour notes are speaking to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side I have been listening to the fantastic live album (recorded in Toronto 1975) by the late great Jim Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/038-Jim-Hall/Jim-Hall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been a guitar player since I was around 11 years old, however I have never been a huge fan of many jazz guitarists. Most of the time I'd rather listen to horn, trumpet or piano players. There are a few jazz guitarists who had a profound effect on me however and Jim Hall is certainly in that list. I picked up this album relatively early in my jazz journey and I remember not being particularly moved by it at the time, however as my ear has grown over the years it is one I keep finding myself coming back to.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/d62pCIkbI1Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Jim started his career in the Chico Hamilton quintet during the mid 1950s before moving on to Jimmy Giuffre's band. The rest of his side-man resume reads like a who's-who of the jazz world featuring names such as Paul Desmond, Art Farmer, Bill Evans, Sonny Stitt, Stan Getz, Lee Konitz and countless others. He is perhaps best known, however, for his work with Sonny Rollins. In particular the album: &quot;The Bridge&quot; which was the first to appear after Sonny's hiatus and featured the new &quot;piano-less&quot; format for the Rollins group. &quot;The Bridge&quot; changed everything in terms of jazz guitar, it acted as a blueprint for jazz guitar comping for decades after it and went to show that the guitar could functionally replace the piano in a group. Any jazz guitar player owes a great deal of gratitude for Jim Hall for doing this, without him later players such as Pat Metheny, John Scofield and Bill Frisell would unlikely be drawing the attention they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album in question today: &quot;Live!&quot; was recorded in 1975 when Jim was already a well established name and at the top of is game. It was recorded in Toronto's Bourbon Street Jazz Club - fitting given we looked at an orange bourbon coffee varietal this week. It features Don Thompson on bass and Terry Clarke on drums. Much of Jim's playing is about band interaction, his play essentially &quot;reflects&quot; the ideas of whoever he is playing with back to them. This allows every member to sound &quot;more like themselves&quot; and raises the music to a higher level. This is something that I feel had a profound effect on Bill Frisell who's playing has a similar quality in a more modern setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album itself is entirely made up of standards. The playing of familiar tunes allows the trio to really explore the music freely and express themselves. A lot of the exploration takes place in the subtlties, while it's possible to listen to this album without paying much attention it really rewards those looking deeper. You can hear each band member picking up on the phrasing of each others lines. Jim's sparse comping style is on full display in such a stripped back environment. You can also hear his use of dynamics, something that a lot of jazz guitar players overlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a live album of course there are imperfections: you can hear the audience clinking their glasses in places and there are some notes that I imagine would have been &quot;fixed&quot; on a studio release. However more than most other live albums I can think of it really captures the feeling of a small jazz club.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eJHf22tJ_a0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

If you've not heard Jim Hall or this album before I strongly suggest finding a copy. For the particularly keen you can also find &quot;Live vol 2-4&quot; which is essentially an extension of this album and features additional music recorded at Bourbon Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/038-Jim-Hall/Jim-Hall.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/038-Jim-Hall/Jim-Hall.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Brecker Bros and Shantawene</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/brecker-bros-shantawene" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Brecker Bros and Shantawene" /><published>2021-01-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Brecker-Bros-Shantawene</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/brecker-bros-shantawene">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-01-02-Brecker-Bros-Shantawene.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jhDl4IDfYOg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Welcome to the first JazzCoffeeStuff blog post of2021. Usually the new year is the time for people to turn over a new leaf, try something new or make a life change. At JazzCoffeeStuff we are not doing this: we are once again featuring a blog favourite: Assembly Coffee Roasters - with a coffee of theirs hailing from Ethiopia. And of course served with a side of jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assembly have featured on this blog multiple times in the past - I always list them as one of my favourite UK based roasters and always find myself coming back to them. They have made a small change to their presentation however in removing the roast date and replacing it by a &quot;Best Before&quot; (which is 12 months after roast) - which personally I am not a fan of. I would prefer to see the roast date itself and a &quot;best before&quot; for me would be 3 months at most. For the seasoned coffee person the best before date doesn't really matter, but for those getting into specialty it might be a bit misleading and prevent them getting the most from their coffee. This is the most minor of gripes however and does not stop me buying from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto the coffee itself: what drew me to this particular coffee was the list of varietals: Setami, Mikicho, 72/158, 74/110. I'm glad that Ethiopian coffees are slowly but surely beginning to discover the varietals that constitute &quot;Heirloom&quot;. In this instance this list of varietals does not help me too much as I have no experience with any of them (by name) - but it forms a &quot;first data point&quot; in understanding them. Hopefully I can get my hands on some more in the future. The processing method is washed and the coffee is called: Shantawene - after the village where the wet mill is located and this coffee is made up of produce from multiple smallholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly on to what matters: on the dry aroma I get a hit of a caramel and a crisp green apple. Alongside is a heavier fruit note: a date or prune. It is quite a fragrant coffee, often washed Ethiopians can be quite mellow and restrained but that does not seem to be the case here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week my filter coffee process had to be adjusted slightly: I have been unable to locate my usual chemex filter papers so I am using boxed Hario filters instead. These papers are (much) thinner than the chemex, this has the effect of allowing more of the coffee oils to get through - this increases body and sacrifices a bit of clarity. Which you prefer is personal preference, as long as you make sure you buy the correct Hario filters: the Holland based factory does not produce good filters at all. The boxed filters are the best of the lot (they have 3 different factories) and so I only bother with those. You can make a &quot;faux-chemex&quot; by double bagging the Hario filters but it is not quite the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through an act of serendipity the changed filters actually work well with this particular coffee. There is a lot of texture and mouthfeel on show and the Hario filters amplify this. The body is very big and it is certainly a heavy hitter, not what I was expecting at all to be honest. In the Assembly tasting notes they describe this as &quot;concentrated&quot; which is fair, personally &quot;intense&quot; is one of the first words I wrote down. I think &quot;intense&quot; fits better with my experience because of the absolute punch this coffee gives. The overarching flavour is blackcurrant, it has a sort of Kenyan vibe to it but without the excess acidity. As an Ethiopian you also get the usual peach/apricot flavours coming through too. The florals are less than you might expect but they do pop out in the long lingering aftertaste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso this coffee really shines for me. The thick viscous mouthfeel is really amplified through this method and you end up with a big and punchy shot. Despite the (very) light roast level of this coffee I ended up with a very traditional: 1:2 in 30s type profile at a medium heat. This seemed to highlight the viscosity and massive mouthfeel. I tried going even shorter to ristretto type levels to boost this even more but this seemed to introduce a little harshness in the finish which I didn't care for. Flavour wise it is all about the blackcurrant and stone fruit - it's almost like one of those &quot;superfood shots&quot; you can get at trendy smoothie bars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a great start to coffee in 2021, if you can I'd recommend picking up a bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I dug out an old fusion record from 1975 courtesy of The Brecker Brothers with their (semi)eponymous &quot;The Brecker Bros.&quot; album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/037-Brecker-Bros/Brecker-Bros.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fusion records are not something I listen to particularly often. There are plenty of albums and artists I love in that style but I often struggle with the recording styles, tones and production values. Many of these records end up sounding pretty dated today. Unfortunately this record is one of them, however it is well worth battling through as the music is top draw. It is particularly worth a listen if Snarky Puppy were your gateway into the murky world of jazz since The Brecker Brothers were certainly a big influence in developing the Snarky sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As their name suggests The Brecker Brothers consist of brothers: Randy and Michael Brecker. Those with good memories may remember that Michael Brecker featured on the blog previously as a sideman on the Pat Metheny album 80/81. Michael was best known for his virtousity and ability to play extremely complicated fast lines with complete precision, this is on full display on this album. The opening track &quot;Some Skunk Funk&quot; (embedded at the start of the blog) is a prime example of this, although he doesn't quite reach the dizzying diminished, whole-tone scale wizardry of some of his later recordings. The track &quot;Rocks&quot; (below) is another that Michael Brecker highlight.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q2-NEwoaR8k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

While he never had quite the &quot;star power&quot; of his brother it's important not to overlook Randy Brecker too. In addition to the Brecker Brothers records (where I feel he was the main driving force to be honest, these records have a very different vibe to Michael's solo work) Randy has a number of solo records under his belt and has appeared alongside many of the greats such as George Benson, Jaco Pastorious and Horace Silver. Outside of the jazz world he has also done a lot of session work, appearing on hugely commercially successful albums like Donald Fagen's &quot;The Nightfly&quot;, &quot;Graceland&quot; by Paul Simon, &quot;Brothers in Arms&quot; by Dire Straits, and Chaka Khan's &quot;Chaka Khan&quot; (in addition to countless others). On this album Randy also provides vocals on the track &quot;Oh My Stars&quot; - I've always found this track a little strange and it sticks out on the album. It feels as though this is a concession to a record company to try and write a radio friendly &quot;hit&quot; but for me it's a bit wide of the mark and it's a track I almost always skip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album also features a relatively fresh faced David Sanborn on alto. Sanborn has, rather unfairly, been associated with &quot;smooth jazz&quot; since some of his records have had commercial success and he has done some crossover R&amp;amp;B type work. He has still recorded with many of the greats in more &quot;serious&quot; settings too and while his solo records are not ones I gravitate towards it's a little unfair to lump him in the &quot;smooth&quot; camp. His playing on this record alone shows he certainly has the chops and it is quite cool to hear him in this setting as it's not something you hear from him often. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jV2AZ63cUqk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Overall this is really quite a fun &quot;jazz-funk&quot; fusion record. It is certainly &quot;of a time&quot; but you cannot deny the sheer musical ability of all involved. If you want to hear chops there are worse places to go, assuming you can live with the rather dated production values. Regardless it is worth a listen from a &quot;jazz history&quot; standpoint to hear one of the directions jazz-fusion was heading in the mid 1970s. For Michael Brecker fans this album also provides great insight into how his playing was developing at this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/037-Brecker-Bros/Brecker-Bros.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/037-Brecker-Bros/Brecker-Bros.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tijuana Moods and Santa Claude</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/tijuana-moods-santa-claude" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tijuana Moods and Santa Claude" /><published>2020-12-26T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-26T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Tijuana-Moods-Santa-Claude</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/tijuana-moods-santa-claude">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-12-26-Tijuana-Moods-Santa-Claude.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Kw1BWwiPJCY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

In this festive special we are going to look at a &quot;christmas coffee&quot; from the folks at Round Hill Roasters. Long time readers may remember earilier in the year we featured &quot;Spring Claude&quot; - which was a rather special coffee. For the holiday season this time we have &quot;Santa Claude&quot; and I have high hopes based on previous showing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This coffee gets its name from a cat named Claude, pet of one of the guys at the Round Hill Roastery. You can see him with a bag of this weeks coffee below (credit to: www.instagram.com/monmonsieur_claude/ ):
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/036-Tijuana-Moods/Santa-Claude.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be perfectly honest I've never had a &quot;christmas coffee&quot; that has particularly reminded me of christmas so I'm not judging this coffee with that in mind (it would fail that test) - instead I'm just hoping for a good all round coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical specs of this coffee are that is a washed Colombian coffee consisting of Caturra and Castillo varietals - and as always I selected the &quot;filter roast&quot; option. It is grown at 1900masl by a community of farmers within the Yacuanquer area. This is in the south-west corner of the country, not too far from the border with Ecuador. This is not an area I see many coffees from so I'm happy to give it a try - doubly so after the &quot;Spring Claude&quot; which is one of my favourite coffees of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll try and keep the blog tight this week so everybody can get back to their festivities - so lets dive straight into looking at the coffee itself. On the dry aroma I get a lot of dark and rich caramel notes first of all, combined with this there is the unmistakable blackcurrant note too, to be honest if I was given this blind I might have guessed it was a Kenyan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly on to the filter coffee: here the major note is blackcurrant. It is a huge juicy coffee and it is a bit like drinking hot ribena - albeit less sweet. There is a good amount of acidity in the cup and it provides just the right amount of &quot;mouth drying&quot; in the finish. It is not the most complicated cup I've ever had but it is certainly delicious and very drinkable, in fact it always seems to disappear faster than I expect. If you want an accompanyment to a mince pie/sausage roll/whatever your festive snack of choice is you could do much worse!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso I find that this coffee needs to be ground extremely fine, I ended up not too far away from the minimum my grinder would allow. Otherwise it is a coffee very prone to &quot;gushers&quot;. Thankfully once you reach a certain point it has a very large sweet spot though which makes it a breeze to dial in. I ended up with a very traditional 1:2 ratio in 30s with a medium heat. This results in a thick viscous juicy shot that bashes you round the head with blackcurrant. It is almost a bit like cough mixture (but in a good way). Certainly a tasty shot that is very easy to drink, the acidity is there but is not overpowering and there is a lot of sweetness. It's just a no-nonsense quality espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a rather successful &quot;christmas coffee&quot;, and I'll likely hunt down the 2021 Santa Claude next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week I feel like we need something special for the festive season. I've resisted going down the &quot;christmas songs&quot; route because they tend to be &quot;good for christmas music&quot; rather than good in general. Instead we are going to welcome the inimitable Charles Mingus to the blog for the first time, with his 1957 (or 1962) album &quot;Tijuana Moods&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/036-Tijuana-Moods/Tijuana-Moods.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mingus is one of my all time favourite artists, for me his music transcends jazz and is something much bigger. I find that with Mingus it is not music you want to put on while doing other things, it commands your entire attention. There is so much going on technically and there is so much raw emotion it is just too intense to have as background music. As a result I don't listen to him as much as some other artists, but I do make sure to find time to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing an album from the Mingus back catalogue is tricky, there are so many good ones to choose from. The obvious place to start would be &quot;Mingus Ah Um&quot; - which is as near to perfect as it's possible for a jazz album to be. Or perhaps &quot;Black Saint and the Sinner Lady&quot; - for being art at the absolute highest level. However my favourite, and the one I find myself coming back to, is &quot;Tijuana Moods&quot;. For me it is the perfect balance between his compositional prowess and the free improvisation. At one time Mingus described this as his &quot;best album&quot; but it often gets a bit overshadowed by others (which is not a bad problem to have as an artist.)

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9x1l3tZbXx8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Tijuana Moods&quot; is a &quot;fusion&quot; album of sorts, managing to blend traditional Mexican music with American jazz and blues sensibilities. More than anything else it seems like the musicians are just having a blast recording this music - something you can't often say about Charles, he isn't known as &quot;the angry man of jazz&quot; for nothing! For those new to Mingus there are many famous stories of him chasing musicians off stage, ripping strings of grand pianos and even attacking band members. There is also of course the famous &quot;Mingus light&quot; at the Village Vanguard where he threw his bass into it (reportedly they never fixed it in tribute to the great man).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In jazz, and even society at large, we do have a problem of fetishizing the concept of the &quot;troubled artist&quot; or &quot;tortured genius&quot; - but for Charles Mingus this label certainly fits. If you are interested I highly recommend his autobiography &quot;Beneath the Underdog&quot; (although it is not a happy or easy-going read). He often described himself as a &quot;mongrel&quot; - since he felt too &quot;black&quot; to be accepted by the &quot;white community&quot; and too &quot;white&quot; to be accepted by the &quot;black community&quot;. It appears a lot of his anger came from this feeling, and understandably so. Of course his later career was also riddled with illness where he suffered from ALS (&quot;Lou Gehrig's disease&quot;) - we can only imagine how much more great music he could have released given the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally the album was released with &quot;Charlie Mingus&quot; on the cover, a name Charles despised saying &quot;Charlie is not a man's name, it's the name of a horse&quot;. Later it was repackaged with alternate takes as &quot;New Tijuana Moods&quot; - but to be honest I'm not a fan of these &quot;extended&quot; releases, I want to hear the music the artist was happy with an wanted to showcase not additional takes that weren't considered as good at the time. I feel like I'm alone in this as every year we get re-releases of these great albums with newly discovered takes and I just don't see the appeal. So I'd recommend you stick to the original &quot;Tijuana Moods&quot; release which comes in at a quick 40 minutes or so.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/z0fLC1CTSGs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

You'll notice I've not even tried to describe the music too much here. I feel whatever I do will not do the album justice and you're better off just listening for yourself. There is so much going on in some of the arrangements that you'll likely uncover something different to me anyway. You will find a wide range of musical styles on display however, from the mariachi band inspired sections, through to real swinging jazz and gospel blues. There will be dissonant parts followed by sweet melodies you will be humming for days afterwards. It is really a treat for the ears. It remains shocking to me how Mingus is not considered one of the greatest composers of all time, unfortunately I believe a lot of this is down to how African-American people are viewed in the states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you're at a loss for music to listen to over the festive period and you've never heard Charles Mingus (or &quot;Tijuana Moods&quot;) before it is well worth your time. If you do know the album; perhaps it's time to give it another listen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/036-Tijuana-Moods/Tijuana-Moods.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/036-Tijuana-Moods/Tijuana-Moods.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">After Hours and Ana Sora</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/after-hours-ana-sora" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="After Hours and Ana Sora" /><published>2020-12-19T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/After-Hours-Ana-Sora</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/after-hours-ana-sora">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-12-19-After-Hours-Ana-Sora.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4OJNpGawCRY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The coffee on the blog this week once again comes from firm favourite Plot coffee roasters - and unsurprisngly we have another coffee from an Israel Degfa owned farm. If you have read my previous posts you will recognise Israel Degfa and so we won't get into his business/charity again. This time we are looking a farm called Ana Sora from the Guji zone within the Oromia region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This coffee picqued my interest because of the processing method: described as a &quot;Semi-Carbonic Natural&quot;. It is not a method I can remember seeing very often in the past, and given my love of Ethiopian coffee (and trust in Plot) I felt it was worth a try. The details of the processing are as follows: the cherries are left to macerate in tanks for 36 hours. The cherries at the bottom get crushed and release CO2 which forces oxygen out of the tank. The reduced oxygen means that bacteria are unable to operate as well (as they would in a &quot;regular&quot; natural process). After this process the cherries are dried as usual on raised beds. A very interesting process that should impact the cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly onto the coffee itself: the first thing I notice on the dry aroma is fruit, lots and lots of fruit! It is quite a sweet fruit smell as opposed to a tropical fruit. It almost has a candy quality to it, very inviting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we follow up with a filter coffee brewed in the usual way. As expected from the dry aroma the overwhelming quality of the cup is &quot;fruit&quot;. The label lists: lychee and apricot. Which I think is fair, it has that sticky sweetness I associate with the lychee and as a coffee from Guji it naturally has that apricot vibe. I also notice some more acidic fruit notes however, a citrus that I'd suggest most closely resembles a lemon sharpness. But the first thing I wrote down when taking my first sip was: Strawberry. For me it's what this coffee is about, imagine some strawberries macerated in sugar before being added to a very crisp lemonade - that is the best description I can come up with for the cup. There is more to it than this however and it is certainly a complex cup - there are floral notes aplenty as the drink cools. It's a very drinkable cup but can also keep you entertained when searching for flavour descriptors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso this coffee really shines for me. The roast level for this coffee is fairly light so unsurpisingly &quot;hot, fast, long&quot; is my advice. I put my machine to near top temperature and pulled 1:2.75 in 22s when I dialed it in - however it is fairly forgiving. I found going shorter made the shot a bit too intense, with all the complexity of this coffee it is a bit overwhelming. Again for me the first thing I thought of when tasting was strawberry. It has a sticky mouthfeel too so it sort of gives an impression of strawberry jam (without the pits). Again the apricot and lemon notes are there too but they take more of a backseat, the florals all but disappear when put up against the bigger stronger flavours. This is one that I couldn't get enough of as an espresso, I'd be knocking back the shot in milliseconds then instantly wanted to go back and make another. A very good quality for a coffee to have!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we are heading way back to the 1940s and Minton's Playhouse in Harlem with the Charlie Christian album &quot;After Hours&quot; featuring Dizzy Gillespie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/035-After-Hours/After-Hours.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album represents a very significant time and place in Jazz history. Following the swing era many of the modern jazz musicians were looking at where the artform should go &quot;post-swing&quot;. The forward looking musicians of the day would play their regular swing based gigs during the evening and then hang out &quot;after hours&quot; without an audience to experiment and push things forward. Minton's Playhouse in Harlem was one of the key destinations for this, the owners not only allowed the musicians to play whatever they liked they also offered them food for doing so - an irresistable combination for jazz musicians at the time. Of course through this experimentation came the language of be-bop - the &quot;After Hours&quot; album acts as an insight into how the change from swing to bop came about. Much of the album swings but you can see the beginnings of the be-bop harmony coming into play. For any jazz fan interested in the history of the music this is a very interesting recording.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to give a quick warning however, since this was recorded in a jazz club (not a studio) around 80 years ago the sound quality is not the best you'll find. If you enjoy pristine recordings this is unlikely to be the record for you! I also note that this album appears under a number of names, I believe &quot;After Hours&quot; is the most famous of these - however I also mistakenly bought a copy of &quot;Dizzy Gillespie - Stardust&quot; on vinyl which ended up being the exact same recording!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album is essentially split into a &quot;Charlie Christian&quot; section (5 tracks) and a &quot;Dizzy Gillespie&quot; section (4 tracks). Each section also features Kenny Clarke on drums and Thelonious Monk on piano with a few others appearing in either of the sections.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/oQN-cuR_ZEI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Dizzy Gillespie needs no introduction, being one of the most famous jazz musicians of all time and has the nickname of &quot;the ambassador of jazz&quot;. While Charlie Parker gets a lot of the credit for popularizing be-bop Dizzy is one of the ones who &quot;worked out&quot; how to get the music to work on a theoretical level - in the early days some even referred to him as &quot;the professor&quot;. The Dizzy tracks on &quot;After Hours&quot; give just a hint of what is to come, you can see his mind working and the early ideas he had on be-bop. This makes the album essential listening and completely fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Charlie Christian section, however, likely gets talked about the most. This is due to a lack of recordings on Charlie given his short career and tragic death at the age of just 25 - one can only imagine where he could have taken the music given a chance. He is best known for appearing in the Benny Goodman band - which to be honest while a lot of fun does not give musicians a chance to really stretch their legs and show off some chops. &quot;After Hours&quot; is perhaps the best example we have of what Charlie was &quot;really about&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's worth remembering that Charlie Christian is really the &quot;first guitar hero&quot; in a lot of ways. He was somewhat fortunate that his rise to prominence coincided with the advent of the electric guitar - prior to this guitars were acoustic and as such it was not really possible to cut through a band with single note lines. Charlie was really the first to show the guitar could also be a lead instrument (at least the first in a commercially successful setting). You would normally expect the first electric guitar sounds to be terrible by today's standards - but for my money Charlie has the best electric guitar tone in all of jazz. Unlike those that followed him he used a relatively bright and clear tone and given the rather low-powered amp of the day (the Gibson EH150) he was typically at the edge of break-up. As technology &quot;improved&quot; jazz players opted for cleaner and cleaner tones and rolled off more and more top end from their sounds. In addition to the amp a key part of the sound is the guitar pickup he used, now referred to as the &quot;Charlie Christian&quot; pickup. These too are quite different from modern pickups, the originals feature large soft and relatively weak magnets compared to the harder more powerful alnico and ceramic ones of today. They also feature wire that is significantly thicker than the wire used in say a PAF or fender pickup (modern pickups tend to use around 42 gauge wire while the Charlie Christian styles use 38) - the thicker wire allows less top-end to be rolled off and so you can make a hotter pickup that retains clarity (which in turn pushed the weaker amps of the day harder). Of course a thicker wire takes up more space which is likely why they became less popular. I am a big fan of the Charlie Christian style pickups however and it is core to my guitar sound, I like to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ccpickups.co.uk/&quot;&gt;http://www.ccpickups.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt; here in the UK - no affiliation, just a fan.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1VxeZPnrZ_w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

I remember when I first picked up a copy of &quot;After Hours&quot; clearly. I bought a copy on vinyl from a record shop in Reading. It is a rather haphazard shop that sells old comic books, action figures as well as old records and so on. The guy that runs the place is a big jazz fan and there are hundreds if not thousands of records in the shop. These are not in any sort of order so it takes ages to flick through to find anything, but in doing so you uncover gems (such as this one). When I went to pay the owner told me how this was &quot;one of his favourite albums&quot; and how he &quot;hates the Benny Goodman recordings- but Charlie is great on this&quot;. I enjoy shops like this where you get interesting interactions with the owners, something that is sadly disappearing with the increase in online shopping. Perhaps the most mystifying thing with this shop however is the pricing &quot;structure&quot; - the label prices on the records are insane but when you go to pay he does some bizarre mental arithmetic and you end up paying less than half the label price. It is super confusing and you never know quite what you'll end up paying - which adds to the excitement I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/035-After-Hours/After-Hours.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/035-After-Hours/After-Hours.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">There is a Tide and Haraz</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/there-is-a-tide-haraz" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="There is a Tide and Haraz" /><published>2020-12-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/There-is-a-Tide-Haraz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/there-is-a-tide-haraz">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-12-12-There-is-a-Tide-Haraz.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FCy7W1RGmbM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

In this blog post we are in for a treat. Historically it has been very hard to get hold of quality Yemeni coffee, owing largely to the political climate in that region. When coffee did make its way out of Yemen it was often lacking in provenance and traceability. In recent times it has become easier to get hold of good quality coffee from Yemen. In September of this year there was also the QIMA auction for coffees from Yemen - including some lots consisting of the newly discovered &quot;Yemenia&quot; varietal. In this blog post we look at the first coffee in Plot Roasting's &quot;Icon&quot; series - a superb and rare Yemeni coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a recap of Plot Roasting: these guys (and girls) are relatively new to me having only discovered them earlier in the year but have continually impressed with their quality and attention to detail. They have become one of the regular roasters featuring on this blog and have yet to disappoint. Earlier in this month they launched their &quot;Icon&quot; series of coffees - once a month they will be releasing an extremely rare and special coffees with limited availability. Obviously &quot;rare&quot; means the price for this is a bit higher than their other offerings but I could not resist buying this one. The bag itself is only 150g in nature so for this blog I will focus only on filter, I don't believe that 150g is enough to dial in espresso and still have some filter coffee. If you're into espresso rest assured next week normal service will resume!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question today is called Haraz and it is a micro community lot. The community is located in the region west of Sana'a and the coffee is processed in a natural style. Yemen is an interesting origin to look at since it is in some sense &quot;the birthplace of coffee&quot; in as much as it was the first place where the crop was grown commercially. I have to admit I don't have a huge amount of experience with Yemeni coffees, I've tried a few at various coffee shops/events over the years but I think this might be the first bag that I have bought for myself. While not the sort after &quot;Yemania&quot; this coffee consists of the Ja'adi varietal - which as far as I know is only native to Yemen and it's not a varietal I've seen elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's dive straight into looking at the coffee itself. The dry aroma from this coffee is, frankly, bizarre. As I am grinding it I get a very strong &quot;meat&quot; note. It actually reminds me of something oddly specific: Royster's T-Bone crisps! It took me a while to pin-point exactly where I recognised the scent from but it very obvious now (I used to eat a lot of these crisps as a child). In addition to this I also get a strong clove note coming through. It is a very pungent and hard hitting coffee from a dry aroma perspective and certainly very distinctive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now onto the filter itself: this coffee is certainly different. It is difficult to describe in terms of comparisons to other coffees as it has its own thing going on. For me the bigggest flavour is cola. It reminds me of drinking cola at a cinema (or wherever you usually drink cola) - just at a higher temperature. In addition that clove note comes out again too and hits hard. I also get the Turkish delight note listed on the bag, but only after it was pointed out (perhaps because I've only eaten Turkish delight a couple of times in my entire life). In the aftertaste and finish strong violet florals also come out to play, I find this coffee a bit of a rollercoaster in terms of flavour profile - it is super complex and changes dramatically through the life of the drink. If you like discovering flavour notes this is one for you - you'll undoubtedly find dozens of other notes I have not mentioned (I only mentioned the biggest ones here). In terms of mouthfeel and body we are definitely at the heavier end of the scale here, it almost has a &quot;chewy&quot; texture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a very strange and interesting coffee, for me it was well worth the price of admission and I would buy it again. However, I could see some people absolutely despising this coffee and being very upset they spent the premium on it. I would suggest this is a coffee for an &quot;advanced&quot; coffee drinker and not one for somebody just starting their specialty coffee journey - but everybody is different so if these flavour notes appeal to you and you are will to pay certainly give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the jazz side of the blog we have something equally special to listen to this week: Chris Potter's &quot;There is a Tide&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/034-There-is-a-Tide/There-is-a-Tide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an album jazz fans have been eagerly awaiting since it was announced around summer of this year. To see why this album has caused such a stir in the community one only has to look at the personnel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Potter - Saxophones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Potter - piano, keyboards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Potter - electric and acoustic guitars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Potter - bass guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Potter - clarinet, bass clarinet, flute, alto flute, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Potter - drums, percussion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Potter - samples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is correct, this is an entirely &quot;one man band&quot; album with Chris playing all instruments and recording at his home studio during lockdown. We (should) all know that Chris Potter is one of, if not the, best saxophonists in the world today having released albums under his own name as well as appearing alongside artists such as Pat Metheny, Dave Holland, Paul Motian, Dave Douglas and countless others. Many see him as carrying the torch from Michael Brecker in pushing the limits of the saxaphone to new heights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A completely solo album is an interesting concept, I can't think of many examples where jazz musicians have experimented with this in the past - at least from a &quot;big&quot; name. Pat Metheny had his Orchestrion project of course but that was a different prospect as that was largely mechanically controlled (mostly from his guitar) as opposed to playing individual instruments. I guess Jacob Collier would be the other name that might spring to mind here - but past that you tend to find yourself in the region of more obscure artists. Jazz has always had a history of adapting to the times, given the current state of the world perhaps these solo &quot;mad scientist&quot; style projects will become more prominent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What immediately strikes me with &quot;There is a Tide&quot; is just how &quot;pure&quot; the album feels. You can tell there is a single focus and creative direction, it seems very different to a typical small/big band project where you get a blend of ideas. I think this is highlighted because Potter does not have &quot;chops&quot; on say the guitar. In recent projects he had Adam Rogers playing guitar who is (clearly) very talented and so plays complicated lines and technically difficult solos. On &quot;There is a Tide&quot; in contrast the guitar (and piano, drums, etc) play the supporting role - this is not to say Potter is &quot;bad&quot; on these instruments (far from it) but you can tell he doesn't have the same fluency as on the sax. This makes the statments he is making on the woodwind instruments really standout and shine. It is a very different and unique sound, if you have heard any Chris Potter projects in the past &quot;There is a Tide&quot; is &quot;the same, just more&quot;.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zr9ItG5HupI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Since its release about a week ago this album has been on a near constant repeat at JazzCoffeeStuff HQ. Even still I struggle to think of a suitable way to describe the music on this album. The album starts with &quot;I Had a Dream&quot; (embedded at the start of this blog). Which I guess you could describe as being in the &quot;fusion&quot; style with the main theme slowly coming together around a driving (electric) bass line. As you would expect from Chris it doesn't take long for this to descend into some complicated rhythmic ideas and a searing tenor solo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is in contrast to a tune later on the album &quot;Drop Your Anchor Down&quot; (embedded above) which is largely based around a catchy hook, I've found myself humming this one multiple times throughout the week. It is probably the least &quot;complicated&quot; of all pieces on the album so one that might get overlooked but is worthy of some love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most will listen to Chris Potter, however, to hear the complicated mind-bending rhythms and symmetric and diminished sax lines. This is most evident on &quot;Rising Over You&quot; (embedded below) which I imagine will be considered the &quot;stand-out&quot; track of the album by jazz fans. It has the Wayne Krantz style syncopations combined with the Michael Brecker influenced sax lines as one would expect in the main theme. Amongst the chaos it is important to bring the energy levels down in order to let the solos speak, which Potter does masterfully. I imagine in the coming weeks we will see many YouTube videos of people playing licks from this one.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XG-evfyiTEM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As one would expect from a &quot;lock down album&quot; the underlying themes revolve around the current state of the world. It does not take Columbo to work out the meaning with track titles such as: &quot;As the Moon Ascends&quot;, &quot;New Life (In the Wake of Devastation)&quot; and so on. Once again, as it has many times throughout history, jazz is showing it's resiliency in the face of struggle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, whatever I write here will not do the album justice. It is well worth hunting down a copy if you have not already. Although it's only been a week I think it is safe to say this album will be in contention for &quot;album of the year&quot; in most 2020 year end reviews (and if not it: it should be!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/034-There-is-a-Tide/There-is-a-Tide.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/034-There-is-a-Tide/There-is-a-Tide.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">80/81 and Balesi Dingu</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/8081-balesi-dingu" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="80/81 and Balesi Dingu" /><published>2020-12-05T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/8081-Balesi-Dingu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/8081-balesi-dingu">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-12-05-8081-Balesi-Dingu.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xMniT5qhKio&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are sticking with the Round Hill coffee roastery for a second week in a row. I've talked many times about Round Hill in the past so won't cover the same ground again - but if this is your first time reading the blog the concise version is: &quot;buy coffee from Round Hill&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will come as no surprise that we are looking at another Ethiopian coffee. Ethiopia is my favourite origin and so I end up buying/drinking a lot of it. Usually I head towards the washed coffees but this one is a natural process instead. This coffee is a single farmer lot, this is something a little out of the ordinary within Ethiopian coffee. A lot of the time farmers will lack the distribution chain to be able to connect with importers/exporters/roasters and instead have to deal with a washing station. These deals are typically for a fixed price and their lot will be blended with other lots and so there will be a lack of tracebility. In this case the coffee takes its name from the farmer himself: Balesi Dingu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving straight in to the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I do not get a whole lot to be honest. There are hints of citrus and a nudge of florals but overall it is quite tame. From this I gather that this will not be a very &quot;natural&quot; natural and we are in for a relatively clean cup profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start with a filter. With this coffee I found I had to adjust my grind size to the coarser side, which is quite interesting. Usually I don't recommend changing grind size for filter coffees as you end up losing a lot of time and effort for minimal gain. However in this case with my usual setting I was noticing a bit of harsh bitterness in the finish which I did not enjoy, by knocking the grinder 1 step coarser the whole coffee came alive. The major flavours are the peach and apricot notes one would expect, combined with a grapefruit type acidity and some florals on the back end. Earl Grey tea/bergamot would be a good way to describe the florals in my opinion. This is quite a clean cup but the natural processing method brings in some more body to the cup. I would describe it as a creamy body, it is not a super chew-y huge mouthfeel but it is noticable and adds to the cup enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso. Again this is the &quot;filter roast&quot; option of this coffee and so all my usual advice applies. In the end I settled for 1:2.75 in about 22s at a high heat - basically what you would expect for a coffee of this style. Unfortunately this sacrifices some of the mouthfeel I noticed in the filter but in my opinion the extra sweetness opens the espresso up. It becomes a very sweet peach iced tea in espresso form, very drinkable. The grapefruit acidity is there but it is not overbearing, in fact I would say it is perhaps medium or even medium-low acidity. This could be one that would surprise those who think this roast style is &quot;too light&quot; for espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again another solid showing from Round Hill, for my money one of the most dependable roasters out there and for the money one of the best value. Hats off to the boys and girls from Bath once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we are going all Pat Metheny. This time we are looking at the 1980 release called: &quot;80/81&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/033-8081/8081.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eagle eyed among you will have noticed that the tune embedded at the start of this blog is not actually from 80/81 but a later release from the Pat Metheny Unity Group. This was not a mistake, 80/81 was released on ECM records who are particularly vigilant about removing any YouTube videos of their recordings. As such it is next to impossible to find things to embed for this blog, instead I have taken re-recordings or live versions of some of the tunes off the album. For the full effect get a copy of the album itself, it is well worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way let's talk about Pat. Pat needs no introduction - he is one of the biggest jazz artists in the world today; his gigs always sell out, he has countless Grammy wins, gold records and has worked with just about anybody you could possibly think of. If you are looking for a jazz gig that would convert somebody onto jazz I can't think of many better gigs to go to, Pat always puts on a fantastic show! I have been lucky enough to see him live numerous times and have yet to be disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why then did I pick 80/81? There were many albums I could have picked here, he has recorded some all time classics over the years. 80/81 is one that I continually find myself coming back to however. Pat's style is typically fairly polished and produced, his albums are typically highly composed and in recent years have become increasingly complicated. 80/81 in contrast feels more &quot;organic&quot;, it is just a few guys in a room playing tunes and having fun. Pat doesn't do his synth guitar wailing, there is no Lyle Mays beautifully rich harmonies, it is the closest thing to a &quot;straight ahead&quot; album from Pat.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q32Zlnm9qKU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

It is worth looking at the line-up on this album:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pat Metheny - Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charlie Haden - Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jack Dejohnette - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dewey Redman - Tenor Sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Brecker - Tenor Sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an absolutely all-star cast, every member here is a legend in their own right with countless records and acolades to their name. Reportedly Metheny wrote the tunes on this album with these members in mind, he had a clear vision of exactly how he wanted the band to sound together. What is remarkable about this is that none of the 4 other members had recorded together previously. I had to double check this regarding Charlie and Jack as I found it very hard to believe. In addition this is the first album where Metheny played with any reed players - deciding to double up with a Redman-Brecker duo on this record. They tend to split tenor duties on the record however, they only appear together on 3 of the 9 tracks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with &quot;Two Folk Songs&quot; - perhaps the most well known of the albums tracks (the Unity Group version from 2016 embedded at the start of the post). This is perhaps one of the most iconic opening tracks of any jazz album period, it is a relatively simple melody that will stick in your head for days. However the Jack Dejohnette drum work, for me, really brings the track to life - he manages to find a groove yet still push the music forward at the same time, no mean feat. It also features some sublime tenor work from Brecker. In some sense this was a turning point in Brecker's career and marked a slight change in approach for him and really opened up his vocabulary to become one of the greatest tenors of all time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight is the tune &quot;The Bat&quot; which is quintessential Metheny. A slow meandering ballad full of Metheny-isms albeit with a different tonal-pallete thanks to the use of the tenor sax. It is refreshing to hear Pat's music in this format, as much as I love the other 80s recordings from him, some of the synth work does sound a bit dated now. &quot;The Bat&quot; in contrast sounds timeless to me.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v6LHo3Tnmcw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

When recording this album it became apparent that Metheny had written too much music. A decision was made to instead turn this into a double-album (thankfully). The band then decided to take on the Ornette Coleman piece &quot;Turnaround&quot; - Charlie Haden being a long term collaborator with Ornette. It feels as though this was largely done on the fly and there is a great moment at the end of the tune where you can hear Charlie say &quot;Woah boy! Jack Dejohnette man!&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight of the album (and perhaps the most famous track on the album after &quot;Two Folk Songs&quot;) is the ballad &quot;Every Day (I Thank You)&quot; - which Pat wrote with Michael Brecker in mind. Brecker is best known for his wild Coltrane inspired diminished style lines and crazy up-tempo numbers, however he is also an exceptional on ballads. On this track (a live version embedded above) we get to hear Brecker at his most expressive and heartfelt, certainly not something to be missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80/81 is such a solid album you could pick any of the tunes to write about, each has a story, envokes a feeling and is all around just fun to listen to. I'd highly recommend you find a copy and just listen to it start to finish. It will be time well spent and one you'll likely find yourself coming back to time and time again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/033-8081/8081.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/033-8081/8081.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Love Hurts and Duromina</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/love-hurts-duromina" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love Hurts and Duromina" /><published>2020-11-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Love-Hurts-Duromina</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/love-hurts-duromina">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-11-28-Love-Hurts-Duromina.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kmnAOu124g4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are heading back to our friends at Round Hill Roastery all the way in sunny Bath. Round Hill are an old favoruite of the blog and have featured many times in the past so need no real introduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we are featuring a washed Ethiopian coffee called Duromina. This is a coffee I am very familiar with and have tried many times from many different roasters over the years. Duromina is a co-operative based in the town of Agaro within the Jimma zone of the West Oromia region. It was set up in 2011 and has helped develop specialty coffee production within the area. Previously farmers were producing lower quality coffees for use in blends, but the co-operative structure has allowed quality to increase and the farmers to earn a better premium for their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a co-operative comprised of many smaller farmers there has not been much in the way of varietal tracing for this coffee and as such it is labelled as &quot;heirloom varietal&quot;. This was standard practice for Ethiopian coffees for many years but recently some work has been done to trace the varietal types of each coffee. Hopefully this practice will become more adopted in time and we will be able to talk about the specificities of a Kume against a Wolisho varietal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving straight into the coffee itself: as usual from Round Hill I chose the &quot;filter roast&quot; version of this coffee. On the dry aroma I get a faint light caramel note combined with some peach-y and floral type notes as one would expect from a washed Ethiopian. Overall the aroma is stronger than one might expect for a coffee like this, they can often be shrinking violets (excuse the pun). There is some complexity here but it does not come across as a super complex coffee upon first sniff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving into a filter brew. The first thing I notice is the quintessential &quot;washed Ethiopian&quot; character, it is just a very good example of what to expect from this type of coffee. The major notes are peach iced tea and lavendar and violet style florals. The peach iced tea gives a delicate juicy flavour and lots of sweetness. The florals come in the finish and aftertaste and dry the palette just enough to want you to come back for more. This one is very drinkable - I always notice that I have far less left in the cup than I'd like. It is in fact quite a &quot;linear&quot; coffee in that, for me, the flavour profile doesn't change too much as the drink cools. This might be because recently I've had a number of coffees where this was a defining feature however. In terms of mouthfeel and body there is not a whole lot to talk about, which is not a problem for me as these are not characters I hunt down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the espresso we have to work a little bit to get the most out of it. As we would expect: turn the temperature up very high and pull the shot long is a good starting point. I found ultimately a 1:2.75 ratio worked best for me and my set-up. The resulting espresso is very clean and has great clarity of flavour so I wanted to exemplify that by pulling longer. Going any shorter than this the flavour clarity suffered slightly and you don't gain any additional mouthfeel so it was not worth it for me. Even at a longer ratio the flavours were still punchy and strong: as in the filter peach iced tea and lavendar florals were the major tasting notes. The aftertaste is relatively shortlived but very clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall another very good showing from Round Hill, but I would expect nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week I've decided to cover a 2019 Mack Avenue records release from guitarist Julian Lage: &quot;Love Hurts&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/032-Love-Hurts/Love-Hurts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those that do not know Julian, he started off as a &quot;child prodigy&quot;: he was subject of a documentary film at 8 years old, played at the Grammy's aged 12 and was a jazz faculty member at Stanford at 15. I believe his first recorded work was with Gary Burton in 2004 (aged 16) and his first release under his own name in 2009. Unlike many child prodigies he did not make a name for himself for simply having crazy chops, basically from the beginning he had a very ature and sophisticated sense of melody and harmony. In jazz there is a relatively low conversion rate between the child prodigy to established artist, and I believe one of the main reasons is the focus on technique and chops - it is much harder to develop a good touch, phrasing and harmonic identity. Of course none of this comes from a vacuum and there are hints of other players within Julians playing, I would say that Bill Frisell is a major influence in Julian's style (at least his current style) given the ability to go from simple pure melodies through to the avant garde seemlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cover art of &quot;Love Hurts&quot; shows a line of used matches, it is believed that this is meant to represent the feeling of &quot;burn-out&quot; of having the weight of expectation on his shoulders from a young age. It seems that in recent times Julian has become more at ease with these expectations judging by his interviews. He has always been a soft spoken, fairly shy character but he seems to relax much more in interviews now which nice to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that sets Julian apart from other jazz guitarists out there is his tone. Jazz guitar is often synonymous with some pretty horrible guitar sounds (even for well established and respected artists). Julian does not follow the typical &quot;L5 into a Polytone with the tone rolled down&quot; cliche. Instead he adopts something closer to a rock/blues sound. He is perhaps best known for playing a telecaster (type guitar) into a cranked tweed champ or similar, although recently he has been playing a Gretsch duo-jet style guitars including a signature model made by Collings. His tone is on the edge of break-up so not totally clean and he can get a bit of grit when he digs in hard. This is not something you often here in jazz where pristine cleans are often sort after. Unlike Bill Frisell however, he rarely uses effect pedals or uses them very sparingly instead letting the guitar and amp sing together. It is a very unfussy setup but the simplicity adds to the music I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title track of the album is &quot;Love Hurts&quot; (a live version embedded at the start of the post), a take on a ballad originally recorded by the Everly Brothers. On his Spotify channel Julian has a playlist of the &quot;original&quot; versions of the tracks he covered on this album and instead lists the Roy Orbison version of this track as the inspiration (a version I admit I had never heard before this morning not being a Roy Orbison fan.) Which once is pointed out makes a lot of sense with the arrangement Julian opted for. As with the rest of the album the arragements are stripped back, simple yet elegant. He seems to take the underlying meaning of the song and amplify it, I feel this version gets closer to capturing the spirit of the lyrics written by Boudleaux Bryant than any of the other versions of this song I have heard. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YYb7HUOpVi8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The album features a large number of covers, of the 10 tracks only 2 are penned by Lage. This includes &quot;Tomorrow is the Question&quot; (a live version embedded above) originally by Ornette Coleman on an album of the same name from 1959. As one would expect playing an Ornette Coleman tune allows Julian much more freedom to improvise and take risks than on a ballad like the title track. This results in some truly mind-bending and finger-knotting lines being played throughout. When Julian is playing freely like this it feels as though he is able to completely disengage and play whatever lines he wants. With other players, even when playing free, you can notice certain lines/patterns occurring that stick to some basic structure. What makes Julian's playing so special is he is completely unpredictable, he can throw out a line that would take you months to analyse but then very quickly resolve it and bring you back to earth and move on to the next idea. I've not heard many guitarists (or musicians generally) who can do this so fluently. It is truly magnificent to behold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other &quot;jazz covers&quot; on the album include &quot;The Windup&quot; from Keith Jarrett's &quot;Belonging&quot; album, &quot;Encore (A)&quot; also from Keith Jarrett on &quot;Eyes to the Heart&quot; and &quot;Trudgin&quot; off &quot;Jimmy Giuffre 3&quot; - Julian clearly went on a bit of an ECM records binge while recording this album. In addition there is the standard &quot;I'm Getting Sentimental Over You&quot; - on the Spotify covers playlist Julian selected the Thelonious Monk version as the inspiration, which to be honest I don't hear too much of in this rendition but I'll take Julian's word for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That leaves a few more &quot;pop&quot; covers on the album including &quot;In Heaven&quot; - a song recorded by Peter Ivers and David Lynch that featured on the &quot;Eraserhead&quot; film soundtrack. Lastly we have &quot;Crying&quot; a Roy Orbison number, Julian obviously being a much bigger fan of Orbison than I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two tracks penned by Julian are titled &quot;In Circles&quot; and &quot;Lullaby&quot;. On an album full of mostly covers it is often difficult to write tunes that stand up to the well established ones. It is kind of a double edged sword for jazz artists: if they write simple melodies that stick in your head they're accused of playing it safe or &quot;selling out&quot; yet if they throw every substitution and harmonic device they know at a piece they can become fairly forgettable. On this album Julian manages to write 2 pieces that can hold their own. &quot;In Circles&quot; features some really inventive playing based around a drone in the intro and follows it up with some really interesting rhythmic play later in the piece. In contrast &quot;Lullaby&quot;, as the name suggests, is a much more simple affair yet Julian is still able to stretch his fingers and play some expressive lines.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e-vSkNOKXkY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

If you have not heard Julian before and are looking for something new to listen to that is interesting but not too challenging then you could do much worse than look at &quot;Love Hurts&quot;. Be sure to pick up a copy from whichever channel you get your music from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/032-Love-Hurts/Love-Hurts.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/032-Love-Hurts/Love-Hurts.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">London Jazz Festival and Carmelita</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/ljf-carmelita" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="London Jazz Festival and Carmelita" /><published>2020-11-21T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/LJF-Carmelita</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/ljf-carmelita">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-11-21-LJF-Carmelita.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uTYnh8zmq1s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are looking at the last of the current batch of Drop Coffee. I think Drop are consistently once of the best roasters going, unfortunately shipping costs mean I purchase from them less often than I'd like. This goes for most other non-UK based roasters in fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question today is from Bolivia, an origin we have spoken about a few times in the past. The farm is located in the Caranavi region, perhaps the most famous of all Bolivian coffee regions. The coffee goes by the name &quot;Carmelita&quot; which comes from the producer: Carmelita Urduvi. It has a washed fermented processing, a fairly standard approach from Drop's literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is &quot;interesting&quot; about this coffee is the varietal it is a Java. This has nothing to do with the island of Indonesia - which I believe is the origin of the colloquialism &quot;a cup of java&quot;. Instead the Java varietal has a bit of a checkered history, originally thought to be part of the typica lineage it was later discovered to have its origins in Ethiopia (through a local landrace called Abysinia). Java is known for having very high cup quality and reasonable resistance against leaf rust and various other diseases. This makes it a good proposition for a &quot;Gesha-alternative&quot; that is easier for producers to grow while still leading to cup quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's move onto the coffee itself: as usual starting with the dry aroma I'm getting 2 main notes: butter and pears. It is soft and fairly delicate in nature, and certainly very comforting. I'm not getting much in the way of floral notes, which is a little surprising for a java (but perhaps less so for a Bolivian). The roast level appears to be towards the medium-light level - about the same as last weeks Hunkute but a touch darker than some of the previous Drops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto our prototypical filter recipe: the first thing I notice is that there is quite a lot of body in this coffee. It is quite dense and heavy hitting. This is not something I typically look for but when it's there I won't complain. In terms of flavours again the butter and pears come to the forefront. The label says &quot;pear cider&quot; but I don't get the same sort of acidity I'd associate with a cider. For me a more apt description would be a poached pear dessert with custard. As the cup cools down the finish and aftertaste becomes more intense and very sweet and floral in nature. I'd describe it as a &quot;sticky floral&quot; like an elderflower or honeyblossom if pushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso I was extremely lucky to land on a perfect recipe first time! This is not something that happens very often, especially when jumping from a vastly different origin/varietal. How did I do this? I knew this bean would be less dense than the previous Hunkute so I would need to fine up my grind quite a bit. Given the qualities in the filter I knew the mouthfeel was something that would benefit from a shorter/standard pull compared to my usual approach - again pointing towards a finer grind. On the temperature side I knew a medium-high heat would work best given the roast levels we're dealing with. I ended with a 1:1.9 ratio with a 10s preinfuse followed by a 28s pull - pretty much a standard espresso recipe you'd find anywhere on the web. As expected this leads to a big heavy buttery mouthfeel with sticky-pear sweetness and surprisingly the floral notes shine through. Despite being a heavy hitter it still has exceptional clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest this was a coffee I bought to &quot;make up the numbers&quot; to get free shipping on my order. I expected it to be one of the weaker offerings in my order but I have really enjoyed drinking it. It goes to show that you can't judge a coffee based on &quot;specs&quot; alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we are going to take a different approach. This past week has been London Jazz Festival, so in the evenings I have been listening to various livestreams/concerts so I thought I'd give an round up of what I experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/LJF.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly London Jazz Festival has been a bit different this year. Given the timing they were unable to allow &quot;in-person&quot; audiences and so everything has been live-streamed online. Of course you will never be able to capture the magic of live jazz through a screen in quite the same way, but I have to say being able to relax in my own home was quite nice. As much as I love Ronnie Scott's I did not miss being squeezed into the church pews and my legs going to sleep halfway through the first set! I also did not miss having to commute back home after the gigs finished, especially during mid-week! One evening isn't too bad but when the festival is on and you're doing something everyday and not getting home until past midnight most days the end of the work week can feel like hell on earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/BillLaurence.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first artist I &quot;saw&quot; was Bill Laurence at Ronnie Scott's with a solo piano performance. Bill is best known for his work with the Snarky Puppy collective. I have to admit I struggle with Snarky a bit, don't get me wrong they're objectively a great band and put on fantastic live shows - the music just doesn't move me and I don't go reaching for their records. As such I'm not really familiar with Laurence's solo work. The set opened with (I believe) a take on &quot;Flamenco Sketches&quot; and made me sit up and take notice. I was expecting more of a fusion oriented experience but Bill showed he has a wide jazz repertoire and played some beautifully emotive lines throughout.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ia9PLzX1RUM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Much of the rest of the set was made up of his own music from his dystopian record &quot;Cables&quot; which was more in the fusion space. However he also presented a great rendition of the standard &quot;You Don't Know What Love Is&quot; - which was another highlight for me. He definitely did enough for me to take notice of his releases and gigs in future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/Dinosaur.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next gig on the agenda for me was Laura Jurd's Dinosaur at King's Place. As expected there were a few technical issues leading to a rather lengthy delay in start time - but when has a jazz gig ever started on time? I guess this adds to the realism. And a shoutout to the person in the chat who commented: &quot;Even Keith Jarrett didn't make me wait this long!&quot; - I genuinely laughed out loud at that.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z0_5yNYQl8M&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The gig was a play through of the latest 2020 release &quot;To the Earth&quot;. I swotted up before the gig to get familiar with this album so I could understand the tunes a bit better. The thing that really struck me was how different the feel was in this performance - each tune was played with a much looser, bluesy quality. On the record everything is much more clinical and precise, I have to say I much preferred the live version for feeling more organic. I guess they recorded the album using a click-track to get everything perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standout piece of the night for me was &quot;Slow Loris&quot; which really expemplified the blues groove the band had. And also a shoutout to pianist Elliot Gavin who was truly fantastic from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was kind of eerie hearing a jazz gig with no applause however, in the Ronnie Scott's gig above the crew/staff provided the applause which made the experience feel more &quot;real&quot;. Laura did here best to compere between tunes but there was only so much she could do. Perhaps they could have used a canned applause or similar to give the performance more atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/LindaOh.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps my highlight of the week was Linda Oh's performance. This one was not so much a &quot;performance&quot; as a sequence of recorded tracks. After each tune it cut so it was not clear whether this was recorded in one continuous set or, as is my assumption, tunes were recorded individually with breaks along the way. Regardless it was a truly incredible performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could certainly tell the influence working with Metheny has had on Linda, there were plenty of &quot;Metheny-isms&quot; throughout the set (no bad thing). The music gently oscillated between bop, fusion and free styles with lots of mind-bending rhythmic patterns. At times there were even Zappa-style quintuplet lines thrown in for good measure.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/20YiLp7_dXM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Linda split her time between acoustic and electric basses, with my favourite pieces being where she focussed on the former. But also a shout out to tenor saxophonist Jamie Oehlers for playing some dizzingly impressive lines throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music here was so adventurous, energetic and fast moving it is hard to do it justice with words. I have seen Linda live a few times both as a band member and a lead act, she is always worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/HaroldLopezNussa.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last act I want to talk about is Harold Lopez Nussa. I've been a fan of his since he first broke onto the scene play his Cuban jazz music. Traditionally it has been fairly hard for those outside of Cuba to hear the best Cuban artists but Harold has had some commercial success starting with his &quot;New Day&quot; album back in 2013 through his latest 2020 release &quot;Te Lo Dije&quot;. Much of this gig (streamed from Havana) featured music from this release. Here he moves a bit further from &quot;just&quot; playing Cuban jazz and takes influence from fusion, classical and popular music - it for example features a rendition of &quot;The Windmills Of Your Mind&quot; from the Thomas Crowne Affair fame. He also referenced his back catalogue and played &quot;Paseo&quot; one of my favourite pieces off his debut album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N1nf1MCpKhg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Overall, although atypical, a rather enjoyable London Jazz Festival. But here's to hoping that normal service can resume in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/LJF.svg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/LJF.svg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>