<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-12T05:06:59-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">80/81 and Balesi Dingu</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/8081-balesi-dingu" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="80/81 and Balesi Dingu" /><published>2020-12-05T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/8081-Balesi-Dingu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/8081-balesi-dingu">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-12-05-8081-Balesi-Dingu.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xMniT5qhKio&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are sticking with the Round Hill coffee roastery for a second week in a row. I've talked many times about Round Hill in the past so won't cover the same ground again - but if this is your first time reading the blog the concise version is: &quot;buy coffee from Round Hill&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will come as no surprise that we are looking at another Ethiopian coffee. Ethiopia is my favourite origin and so I end up buying/drinking a lot of it. Usually I head towards the washed coffees but this one is a natural process instead. This coffee is a single farmer lot, this is something a little out of the ordinary within Ethiopian coffee. A lot of the time farmers will lack the distribution chain to be able to connect with importers/exporters/roasters and instead have to deal with a washing station. These deals are typically for a fixed price and their lot will be blended with other lots and so there will be a lack of tracebility. In this case the coffee takes its name from the farmer himself: Balesi Dingu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving straight in to the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I do not get a whole lot to be honest. There are hints of citrus and a nudge of florals but overall it is quite tame. From this I gather that this will not be a very &quot;natural&quot; natural and we are in for a relatively clean cup profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start with a filter. With this coffee I found I had to adjust my grind size to the coarser side, which is quite interesting. Usually I don't recommend changing grind size for filter coffees as you end up losing a lot of time and effort for minimal gain. However in this case with my usual setting I was noticing a bit of harsh bitterness in the finish which I did not enjoy, by knocking the grinder 1 step coarser the whole coffee came alive. The major flavours are the peach and apricot notes one would expect, combined with a grapefruit type acidity and some florals on the back end. Earl Grey tea/bergamot would be a good way to describe the florals in my opinion. This is quite a clean cup but the natural processing method brings in some more body to the cup. I would describe it as a creamy body, it is not a super chew-y huge mouthfeel but it is noticable and adds to the cup enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso. Again this is the &quot;filter roast&quot; option of this coffee and so all my usual advice applies. In the end I settled for 1:2.75 in about 22s at a high heat - basically what you would expect for a coffee of this style. Unfortunately this sacrifices some of the mouthfeel I noticed in the filter but in my opinion the extra sweetness opens the espresso up. It becomes a very sweet peach iced tea in espresso form, very drinkable. The grapefruit acidity is there but it is not overbearing, in fact I would say it is perhaps medium or even medium-low acidity. This could be one that would surprise those who think this roast style is &quot;too light&quot; for espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again another solid showing from Round Hill, for my money one of the most dependable roasters out there and for the money one of the best value. Hats off to the boys and girls from Bath once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we are going all Pat Metheny. This time we are looking at the 1980 release called: &quot;80/81&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/033-8081/8081.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eagle eyed among you will have noticed that the tune embedded at the start of this blog is not actually from 80/81 but a later release from the Pat Metheny Unity Group. This was not a mistake, 80/81 was released on ECM records who are particularly vigilant about removing any YouTube videos of their recordings. As such it is next to impossible to find things to embed for this blog, instead I have taken re-recordings or live versions of some of the tunes off the album. For the full effect get a copy of the album itself, it is well worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way let's talk about Pat. Pat needs no introduction - he is one of the biggest jazz artists in the world today; his gigs always sell out, he has countless Grammy wins, gold records and has worked with just about anybody you could possibly think of. If you are looking for a jazz gig that would convert somebody onto jazz I can't think of many better gigs to go to, Pat always puts on a fantastic show! I have been lucky enough to see him live numerous times and have yet to be disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why then did I pick 80/81? There were many albums I could have picked here, he has recorded some all time classics over the years. 80/81 is one that I continually find myself coming back to however. Pat's style is typically fairly polished and produced, his albums are typically highly composed and in recent years have become increasingly complicated. 80/81 in contrast feels more &quot;organic&quot;, it is just a few guys in a room playing tunes and having fun. Pat doesn't do his synth guitar wailing, there is no Lyle Mays beautifully rich harmonies, it is the closest thing to a &quot;straight ahead&quot; album from Pat.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q32Zlnm9qKU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

It is worth looking at the line-up on this album:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pat Metheny - Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charlie Haden - Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jack Dejohnette - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dewey Redman - Tenor Sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Brecker - Tenor Sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an absolutely all-star cast, every member here is a legend in their own right with countless records and acolades to their name. Reportedly Metheny wrote the tunes on this album with these members in mind, he had a clear vision of exactly how he wanted the band to sound together. What is remarkable about this is that none of the 4 other members had recorded together previously. I had to double check this regarding Charlie and Jack as I found it very hard to believe. In addition this is the first album where Metheny played with any reed players - deciding to double up with a Redman-Brecker duo on this record. They tend to split tenor duties on the record however, they only appear together on 3 of the 9 tracks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with &quot;Two Folk Songs&quot; - perhaps the most well known of the albums tracks (the Unity Group version from 2016 embedded at the start of the post). This is perhaps one of the most iconic opening tracks of any jazz album period, it is a relatively simple melody that will stick in your head for days. However the Jack Dejohnette drum work, for me, really brings the track to life - he manages to find a groove yet still push the music forward at the same time, no mean feat. It also features some sublime tenor work from Brecker. In some sense this was a turning point in Brecker's career and marked a slight change in approach for him and really opened up his vocabulary to become one of the greatest tenors of all time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight is the tune &quot;The Bat&quot; which is quintessential Metheny. A slow meandering ballad full of Metheny-isms albeit with a different tonal-pallete thanks to the use of the tenor sax. It is refreshing to hear Pat's music in this format, as much as I love the other 80s recordings from him, some of the synth work does sound a bit dated now. &quot;The Bat&quot; in contrast sounds timeless to me.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v6LHo3Tnmcw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

When recording this album it became apparent that Metheny had written too much music. A decision was made to instead turn this into a double-album (thankfully). The band then decided to take on the Ornette Coleman piece &quot;Turnaround&quot; - Charlie Haden being a long term collaborator with Ornette. It feels as though this was largely done on the fly and there is a great moment at the end of the tune where you can hear Charlie say &quot;Woah boy! Jack Dejohnette man!&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight of the album (and perhaps the most famous track on the album after &quot;Two Folk Songs&quot;) is the ballad &quot;Every Day (I Thank You)&quot; - which Pat wrote with Michael Brecker in mind. Brecker is best known for his wild Coltrane inspired diminished style lines and crazy up-tempo numbers, however he is also an exceptional on ballads. On this track (a live version embedded above) we get to hear Brecker at his most expressive and heartfelt, certainly not something to be missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80/81 is such a solid album you could pick any of the tunes to write about, each has a story, envokes a feeling and is all around just fun to listen to. I'd highly recommend you find a copy and just listen to it start to finish. It will be time well spent and one you'll likely find yourself coming back to time and time again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/033-8081/8081.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/033-8081/8081.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Love Hurts and Duromina</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/love-hurts-duromina" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love Hurts and Duromina" /><published>2020-11-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Love-Hurts-Duromina</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/love-hurts-duromina">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-11-28-Love-Hurts-Duromina.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kmnAOu124g4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are heading back to our friends at Round Hill Roastery all the way in sunny Bath. Round Hill are an old favoruite of the blog and have featured many times in the past so need no real introduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we are featuring a washed Ethiopian coffee called Duromina. This is a coffee I am very familiar with and have tried many times from many different roasters over the years. Duromina is a co-operative based in the town of Agaro within the Jimma zone of the West Oromia region. It was set up in 2011 and has helped develop specialty coffee production within the area. Previously farmers were producing lower quality coffees for use in blends, but the co-operative structure has allowed quality to increase and the farmers to earn a better premium for their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a co-operative comprised of many smaller farmers there has not been much in the way of varietal tracing for this coffee and as such it is labelled as &quot;heirloom varietal&quot;. This was standard practice for Ethiopian coffees for many years but recently some work has been done to trace the varietal types of each coffee. Hopefully this practice will become more adopted in time and we will be able to talk about the specificities of a Kume against a Wolisho varietal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving straight into the coffee itself: as usual from Round Hill I chose the &quot;filter roast&quot; version of this coffee. On the dry aroma I get a faint light caramel note combined with some peach-y and floral type notes as one would expect from a washed Ethiopian. Overall the aroma is stronger than one might expect for a coffee like this, they can often be shrinking violets (excuse the pun). There is some complexity here but it does not come across as a super complex coffee upon first sniff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving into a filter brew. The first thing I notice is the quintessential &quot;washed Ethiopian&quot; character, it is just a very good example of what to expect from this type of coffee. The major notes are peach iced tea and lavendar and violet style florals. The peach iced tea gives a delicate juicy flavour and lots of sweetness. The florals come in the finish and aftertaste and dry the palette just enough to want you to come back for more. This one is very drinkable - I always notice that I have far less left in the cup than I'd like. It is in fact quite a &quot;linear&quot; coffee in that, for me, the flavour profile doesn't change too much as the drink cools. This might be because recently I've had a number of coffees where this was a defining feature however. In terms of mouthfeel and body there is not a whole lot to talk about, which is not a problem for me as these are not characters I hunt down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the espresso we have to work a little bit to get the most out of it. As we would expect: turn the temperature up very high and pull the shot long is a good starting point. I found ultimately a 1:2.75 ratio worked best for me and my set-up. The resulting espresso is very clean and has great clarity of flavour so I wanted to exemplify that by pulling longer. Going any shorter than this the flavour clarity suffered slightly and you don't gain any additional mouthfeel so it was not worth it for me. Even at a longer ratio the flavours were still punchy and strong: as in the filter peach iced tea and lavendar florals were the major tasting notes. The aftertaste is relatively shortlived but very clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall another very good showing from Round Hill, but I would expect nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week I've decided to cover a 2019 Mack Avenue records release from guitarist Julian Lage: &quot;Love Hurts&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/032-Love-Hurts/Love-Hurts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those that do not know Julian, he started off as a &quot;child prodigy&quot;: he was subject of a documentary film at 8 years old, played at the Grammy's aged 12 and was a jazz faculty member at Stanford at 15. I believe his first recorded work was with Gary Burton in 2004 (aged 16) and his first release under his own name in 2009. Unlike many child prodigies he did not make a name for himself for simply having crazy chops, basically from the beginning he had a very ature and sophisticated sense of melody and harmony. In jazz there is a relatively low conversion rate between the child prodigy to established artist, and I believe one of the main reasons is the focus on technique and chops - it is much harder to develop a good touch, phrasing and harmonic identity. Of course none of this comes from a vacuum and there are hints of other players within Julians playing, I would say that Bill Frisell is a major influence in Julian's style (at least his current style) given the ability to go from simple pure melodies through to the avant garde seemlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cover art of &quot;Love Hurts&quot; shows a line of used matches, it is believed that this is meant to represent the feeling of &quot;burn-out&quot; of having the weight of expectation on his shoulders from a young age. It seems that in recent times Julian has become more at ease with these expectations judging by his interviews. He has always been a soft spoken, fairly shy character but he seems to relax much more in interviews now which nice to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that sets Julian apart from other jazz guitarists out there is his tone. Jazz guitar is often synonymous with some pretty horrible guitar sounds (even for well established and respected artists). Julian does not follow the typical &quot;L5 into a Polytone with the tone rolled down&quot; cliche. Instead he adopts something closer to a rock/blues sound. He is perhaps best known for playing a telecaster (type guitar) into a cranked tweed champ or similar, although recently he has been playing a Gretsch duo-jet style guitars including a signature model made by Collings. His tone is on the edge of break-up so not totally clean and he can get a bit of grit when he digs in hard. This is not something you often here in jazz where pristine cleans are often sort after. Unlike Bill Frisell however, he rarely uses effect pedals or uses them very sparingly instead letting the guitar and amp sing together. It is a very unfussy setup but the simplicity adds to the music I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title track of the album is &quot;Love Hurts&quot; (a live version embedded at the start of the post), a take on a ballad originally recorded by the Everly Brothers. On his Spotify channel Julian has a playlist of the &quot;original&quot; versions of the tracks he covered on this album and instead lists the Roy Orbison version of this track as the inspiration (a version I admit I had never heard before this morning not being a Roy Orbison fan.) Which once is pointed out makes a lot of sense with the arrangement Julian opted for. As with the rest of the album the arragements are stripped back, simple yet elegant. He seems to take the underlying meaning of the song and amplify it, I feel this version gets closer to capturing the spirit of the lyrics written by Boudleaux Bryant than any of the other versions of this song I have heard. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YYb7HUOpVi8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The album features a large number of covers, of the 10 tracks only 2 are penned by Lage. This includes &quot;Tomorrow is the Question&quot; (a live version embedded above) originally by Ornette Coleman on an album of the same name from 1959. As one would expect playing an Ornette Coleman tune allows Julian much more freedom to improvise and take risks than on a ballad like the title track. This results in some truly mind-bending and finger-knotting lines being played throughout. When Julian is playing freely like this it feels as though he is able to completely disengage and play whatever lines he wants. With other players, even when playing free, you can notice certain lines/patterns occurring that stick to some basic structure. What makes Julian's playing so special is he is completely unpredictable, he can throw out a line that would take you months to analyse but then very quickly resolve it and bring you back to earth and move on to the next idea. I've not heard many guitarists (or musicians generally) who can do this so fluently. It is truly magnificent to behold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other &quot;jazz covers&quot; on the album include &quot;The Windup&quot; from Keith Jarrett's &quot;Belonging&quot; album, &quot;Encore (A)&quot; also from Keith Jarrett on &quot;Eyes to the Heart&quot; and &quot;Trudgin&quot; off &quot;Jimmy Giuffre 3&quot; - Julian clearly went on a bit of an ECM records binge while recording this album. In addition there is the standard &quot;I'm Getting Sentimental Over You&quot; - on the Spotify covers playlist Julian selected the Thelonious Monk version as the inspiration, which to be honest I don't hear too much of in this rendition but I'll take Julian's word for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That leaves a few more &quot;pop&quot; covers on the album including &quot;In Heaven&quot; - a song recorded by Peter Ivers and David Lynch that featured on the &quot;Eraserhead&quot; film soundtrack. Lastly we have &quot;Crying&quot; a Roy Orbison number, Julian obviously being a much bigger fan of Orbison than I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two tracks penned by Julian are titled &quot;In Circles&quot; and &quot;Lullaby&quot;. On an album full of mostly covers it is often difficult to write tunes that stand up to the well established ones. It is kind of a double edged sword for jazz artists: if they write simple melodies that stick in your head they're accused of playing it safe or &quot;selling out&quot; yet if they throw every substitution and harmonic device they know at a piece they can become fairly forgettable. On this album Julian manages to write 2 pieces that can hold their own. &quot;In Circles&quot; features some really inventive playing based around a drone in the intro and follows it up with some really interesting rhythmic play later in the piece. In contrast &quot;Lullaby&quot;, as the name suggests, is a much more simple affair yet Julian is still able to stretch his fingers and play some expressive lines.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e-vSkNOKXkY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

If you have not heard Julian before and are looking for something new to listen to that is interesting but not too challenging then you could do much worse than look at &quot;Love Hurts&quot;. Be sure to pick up a copy from whichever channel you get your music from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/032-Love-Hurts/Love-Hurts.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/032-Love-Hurts/Love-Hurts.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">London Jazz Festival and Carmelita</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/ljf-carmelita" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="London Jazz Festival and Carmelita" /><published>2020-11-21T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/LJF-Carmelita</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/ljf-carmelita">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-11-21-LJF-Carmelita.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uTYnh8zmq1s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are looking at the last of the current batch of Drop Coffee. I think Drop are consistently once of the best roasters going, unfortunately shipping costs mean I purchase from them less often than I'd like. This goes for most other non-UK based roasters in fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question today is from Bolivia, an origin we have spoken about a few times in the past. The farm is located in the Caranavi region, perhaps the most famous of all Bolivian coffee regions. The coffee goes by the name &quot;Carmelita&quot; which comes from the producer: Carmelita Urduvi. It has a washed fermented processing, a fairly standard approach from Drop's literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is &quot;interesting&quot; about this coffee is the varietal it is a Java. This has nothing to do with the island of Indonesia - which I believe is the origin of the colloquialism &quot;a cup of java&quot;. Instead the Java varietal has a bit of a checkered history, originally thought to be part of the typica lineage it was later discovered to have its origins in Ethiopia (through a local landrace called Abysinia). Java is known for having very high cup quality and reasonable resistance against leaf rust and various other diseases. This makes it a good proposition for a &quot;Gesha-alternative&quot; that is easier for producers to grow while still leading to cup quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's move onto the coffee itself: as usual starting with the dry aroma I'm getting 2 main notes: butter and pears. It is soft and fairly delicate in nature, and certainly very comforting. I'm not getting much in the way of floral notes, which is a little surprising for a java (but perhaps less so for a Bolivian). The roast level appears to be towards the medium-light level - about the same as last weeks Hunkute but a touch darker than some of the previous Drops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto our prototypical filter recipe: the first thing I notice is that there is quite a lot of body in this coffee. It is quite dense and heavy hitting. This is not something I typically look for but when it's there I won't complain. In terms of flavours again the butter and pears come to the forefront. The label says &quot;pear cider&quot; but I don't get the same sort of acidity I'd associate with a cider. For me a more apt description would be a poached pear dessert with custard. As the cup cools down the finish and aftertaste becomes more intense and very sweet and floral in nature. I'd describe it as a &quot;sticky floral&quot; like an elderflower or honeyblossom if pushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso I was extremely lucky to land on a perfect recipe first time! This is not something that happens very often, especially when jumping from a vastly different origin/varietal. How did I do this? I knew this bean would be less dense than the previous Hunkute so I would need to fine up my grind quite a bit. Given the qualities in the filter I knew the mouthfeel was something that would benefit from a shorter/standard pull compared to my usual approach - again pointing towards a finer grind. On the temperature side I knew a medium-high heat would work best given the roast levels we're dealing with. I ended with a 1:1.9 ratio with a 10s preinfuse followed by a 28s pull - pretty much a standard espresso recipe you'd find anywhere on the web. As expected this leads to a big heavy buttery mouthfeel with sticky-pear sweetness and surprisingly the floral notes shine through. Despite being a heavy hitter it still has exceptional clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest this was a coffee I bought to &quot;make up the numbers&quot; to get free shipping on my order. I expected it to be one of the weaker offerings in my order but I have really enjoyed drinking it. It goes to show that you can't judge a coffee based on &quot;specs&quot; alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we are going to take a different approach. This past week has been London Jazz Festival, so in the evenings I have been listening to various livestreams/concerts so I thought I'd give an round up of what I experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/LJF.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly London Jazz Festival has been a bit different this year. Given the timing they were unable to allow &quot;in-person&quot; audiences and so everything has been live-streamed online. Of course you will never be able to capture the magic of live jazz through a screen in quite the same way, but I have to say being able to relax in my own home was quite nice. As much as I love Ronnie Scott's I did not miss being squeezed into the church pews and my legs going to sleep halfway through the first set! I also did not miss having to commute back home after the gigs finished, especially during mid-week! One evening isn't too bad but when the festival is on and you're doing something everyday and not getting home until past midnight most days the end of the work week can feel like hell on earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/BillLaurence.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first artist I &quot;saw&quot; was Bill Laurence at Ronnie Scott's with a solo piano performance. Bill is best known for his work with the Snarky Puppy collective. I have to admit I struggle with Snarky a bit, don't get me wrong they're objectively a great band and put on fantastic live shows - the music just doesn't move me and I don't go reaching for their records. As such I'm not really familiar with Laurence's solo work. The set opened with (I believe) a take on &quot;Flamenco Sketches&quot; and made me sit up and take notice. I was expecting more of a fusion oriented experience but Bill showed he has a wide jazz repertoire and played some beautifully emotive lines throughout.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ia9PLzX1RUM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Much of the rest of the set was made up of his own music from his dystopian record &quot;Cables&quot; which was more in the fusion space. However he also presented a great rendition of the standard &quot;You Don't Know What Love Is&quot; - which was another highlight for me. He definitely did enough for me to take notice of his releases and gigs in future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/Dinosaur.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next gig on the agenda for me was Laura Jurd's Dinosaur at King's Place. As expected there were a few technical issues leading to a rather lengthy delay in start time - but when has a jazz gig ever started on time? I guess this adds to the realism. And a shoutout to the person in the chat who commented: &quot;Even Keith Jarrett didn't make me wait this long!&quot; - I genuinely laughed out loud at that.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z0_5yNYQl8M&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The gig was a play through of the latest 2020 release &quot;To the Earth&quot;. I swotted up before the gig to get familiar with this album so I could understand the tunes a bit better. The thing that really struck me was how different the feel was in this performance - each tune was played with a much looser, bluesy quality. On the record everything is much more clinical and precise, I have to say I much preferred the live version for feeling more organic. I guess they recorded the album using a click-track to get everything perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standout piece of the night for me was &quot;Slow Loris&quot; which really expemplified the blues groove the band had. And also a shoutout to pianist Elliot Gavin who was truly fantastic from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was kind of eerie hearing a jazz gig with no applause however, in the Ronnie Scott's gig above the crew/staff provided the applause which made the experience feel more &quot;real&quot;. Laura did here best to compere between tunes but there was only so much she could do. Perhaps they could have used a canned applause or similar to give the performance more atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/LindaOh.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps my highlight of the week was Linda Oh's performance. This one was not so much a &quot;performance&quot; as a sequence of recorded tracks. After each tune it cut so it was not clear whether this was recorded in one continuous set or, as is my assumption, tunes were recorded individually with breaks along the way. Regardless it was a truly incredible performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could certainly tell the influence working with Metheny has had on Linda, there were plenty of &quot;Metheny-isms&quot; throughout the set (no bad thing). The music gently oscillated between bop, fusion and free styles with lots of mind-bending rhythmic patterns. At times there were even Zappa-style quintuplet lines thrown in for good measure.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/20YiLp7_dXM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Linda split her time between acoustic and electric basses, with my favourite pieces being where she focussed on the former. But also a shout out to tenor saxophonist Jamie Oehlers for playing some dizzingly impressive lines throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music here was so adventurous, energetic and fast moving it is hard to do it justice with words. I have seen Linda live a few times both as a band member and a lead act, she is always worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/HaroldLopezNussa.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last act I want to talk about is Harold Lopez Nussa. I've been a fan of his since he first broke onto the scene play his Cuban jazz music. Traditionally it has been fairly hard for those outside of Cuba to hear the best Cuban artists but Harold has had some commercial success starting with his &quot;New Day&quot; album back in 2013 through his latest 2020 release &quot;Te Lo Dije&quot;. Much of this gig (streamed from Havana) featured music from this release. Here he moves a bit further from &quot;just&quot; playing Cuban jazz and takes influence from fusion, classical and popular music - it for example features a rendition of &quot;The Windmills Of Your Mind&quot; from the Thomas Crowne Affair fame. He also referenced his back catalogue and played &quot;Paseo&quot; one of my favourite pieces off his debut album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N1nf1MCpKhg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Overall, although atypical, a rather enjoyable London Jazz Festival. But here's to hoping that normal service can resume in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/LJF.svg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/031-LJF/LJF.svg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Midnight Special and Hunkute</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/midnight-special-hunkute" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Midnight Special and Hunkute" /><published>2020-11-14T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Midnight-Special-Hunkute</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/midnight-special-hunkute">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-11-14-Midnight-Special-Hunkute.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lCNYt9oBJxE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Hello and welcome to the 30th JazzCoffeeStuff blog post! In this installment, as last week we are sticking with Stockholm based Drop Coffee Roasters. This week we are featuring another washed Ethiopian coffee - probably my favourite &quot;style&quot; of coffee, so I have high hopes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question is called Hunkute - a name that may be familiar to those in the speciailty scene since many roasters offer/have offered this coffee in the past. As such I have a certain level of expectation going in to this coffee, unlike some of the previous offerings which have been totally new to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hunkute is the name of the co-operative that processes the coffee. A co-operative, as the name suggests, is where many small local farmers (who would struggle to sell their coffee individually due to low yields) pool together their crops in order to sell their wares. This is quite common in some origins where farmers literally have trees in their back gardens as opposed to operating a large commercial farm. The Hunkute co-operative is made up of over 2000 members, the payment for the coffee gets split between the farmers (~70%) and investment in the washing station and admin costs (~30%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly on; let's go straight into the coffee itself. On the dry aroma you get the typical profile one would expect from a washed Ethiopian such as this. Notes of citrus fruits, white florals and tea are present but it is a subtle affair. In the past I seem to remember this coffee being delicate and soft in nature, being a prototypical washed Ethiopian. In terms of roast level this is probably the &quot;darkest&quot; of the Drop offerings I've had so far. That is not to say this is a dark or even medium roast, but compared to some of the very light roasts in the past few weeks it is a step towards medium-light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual the next step is to make a filter brew in the usual way. Again this on does not give off a huge aroma during/after brewing, it is a very understated experience. In the cup however there are certainly flavour notes galore, the first I noticed was the citrus fruits again. I would describe it as a lemon-type citrus note, clean and refreshing. Perhaps edging into a juicy orange but for me this coffee is more of a clean one than a juicy one. Of course you get the peach iced tea notes that really characterise these sorts of coffees for me. Then we have the florals, part of the reason you hunt down a washed Ethiopian is for the florals and this surely does not disappoint. I would describe them as white florals - jasmine and honeysuckle come to mind - as opposed to say a violet note. The florals really come out to play as the coffee cools down and are particularly present in the finish and aftertaste. In terms of mouthfeel and body there is not much to talk about, it is not a &quot;big&quot; coffee - subtlty, softness and delicacy are how I would describe it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto the espresso - these delicate coffees can sometimes be a bit of a pain for espresso, they can feel a bit empty. You sometimes have that you want to pull short to give some body and intensity but this leaves things a bit too harsh, but pulling longer to reduce the harshness leaves things water-y. Thankfully this coffee is not like this at all, I found it surprisingly easy to dial in, the &quot;sweetspot&quot; was massive and you could pull it how you want. In the end I went with a fairly typical 1:2.25 ratio, 5s pre-infuse follwed by a 24s pull. Temperature wise I was at the high end. This seemed to work best for me as it gave me a bit of extra texture to the shot which was lost at longer pulls. Going any shorter began to add some harshness in the aftertaste. The flavour profile of the shot very much matched that of the filter coffee, lemons and iced-tea were the main notes with just a hint of florals in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall another great showing from Drop. This might not be a &quot;blow you away&quot; coffee in terms of having a really obscure flavour profile, but it is a solid example of what you would want from a washed Ethiopian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sticking with the theme of &quot;does what it says on the tin&quot; - the jazz this week is a 1961 release on Blue Note Records: &quot;Midnight Special&quot; by Jimmy Smith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/030-Midnight-Special/Midnight-Special.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week has been a busy one in JazzCoffeeStuff HQ, as such I haven't wanted music to &quot;think&quot; about - instead I've just needed something reliable to act as a soundtrack. Jimmy Smith is one of the artists I naturally head to in such situations. I know organs and &quot;soul jazz&quot; can be a bit of a contentious subject for some jazz fans. I've seen a lot of vitriol aimed at the style, but for me it has its time and place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To those unfamiliar with Jimmy Smith: he is a jazz heavy-weight. He played the Hammond b3 organ and essentially singlehandedly popularized its use within jazz. Others had used organs in the past (e.g. Fats Waller) but prior to Jimmy there wasn't anybody synonymous with the instrument. Without Jimmy it is unlikely we would have artists such as Joey DeFrancesco, John Medeski or Larry Goldings today, and most likely would not have great rock organists such as Jon Lord or Keith Emerson. Not only was his tone so distinctive on the instrument he had virtuosic chops to back it up, while some &quot;soul jazz&quot; dropped a lot of technique and harmonic complexity in favour of hard groove - Smith maintained a balance of blues grooves along with be-bop inspired lead lines and raw technique. As a lead artist he has over 80 records to his name plus a dozen or so as a sideman and achieved some commercial success - as such if you ask somebody to name a &quot;jazz organist&quot; Jimmy Smith is likely to be the first name they mention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album we're looking at today is &quot;Midnight Special&quot; which was recorded on a session in 1960 but not released until a year later. During the same session they also recorded &quot;Back at the Chicken Shack&quot; released in 1963. Both albums being fantastic and worth hunting down. Part of what makes the Blue Note records from this era so special is the sound quality from Rudy Van Gelder's studio and this is particularly true of &quot;Midnight Special&quot;, if you consider yourself a bit of an audiophile this is one for you! I also love the album cover of this one, it is a bit atypical of a Reid Miles cover: featuring a large colour photograph. But it is so well done, it really shouldn't matter but a good album cover really adds to the whole experience. Especially if you have a nice vinyl copy of the record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The line up features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jimmy Smith – organ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stanley Turrentine – tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kenny Burrell – guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Donald Bailey – drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full line up features on 3 of the 5 tracks on the album, Kenny sitting out of tracks 2 and 4 leaving a leaner trio format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with the title track (embedded at the start of this post). Like many cuts on the album, and much of Smith's back catalogue, it is based on a blues. The longest track on the album at over 9 minutes and features some extended soloing. Jimmy in particular is able to stretch his legs and show off some chops. However Turrentine steals the show for me, with a very tasteful and restrained solo early on and then a second more emotive blues wail towards the end. Kenny's playing is also sublime on this take.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yXCsr9npo84&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another highlight is track 3 &quot;Jumpin' the Blues&quot;, another track featuring the entire quartet. This one is one of the more energetic pieces on show and gives everybody a chance to show off their chops. It probably features the most ambitious soloing on the album. Without a bass player Smith needs to drive the piece forward in the low end, this is paired with Bailey's swinging style. Although a &quot;blues&quot; it features a lot of the hallmarks of jazz and be-bop. This become evident in the solos where each player in turn uses the be-bop vocabulary masterfully. It is perhaps some of the best recorded soloing by Burrell in my opinion. Turrentine again plays his socks off too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the blues the record also features a few slower down-tempo ballads too. The Smith-Turrentine interplay is on full display in these and it is really a joy to listen to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole the record is a masterpiece from start to finish. It allows the listener to engage at whatever level they feel comfortable. It is simple enough that it doesn't require your full attention, however the more you dig into it the more you can get out of it. If you have never listented to a Jimmy Smith record in the past this is a good a place as any to start!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/030-Midnight-Special/Midnight-Special.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/030-Midnight-Special/Midnight-Special.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Happening and Alasitas</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/happening-alasitas" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happening and Alasitas" /><published>2020-11-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Happening-Alasitas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/happening-alasitas">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-11-07-Happening-Alasitas.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y8psxWBFAEw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we feature another coffee from Drop coffee roasters in Stockholm. In order to make the shipping economical I had to order a few different coffees so they will appear for a few more blog posts yet! As I said previously they are one of my favourite roasters so this is no bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee this week is another &quot;premium&quot; one - we have another washed Gesha varietal, this time from Bolivia. Bolivian Gesha is a relatively new phenomena for me, if you recall earlier in the year I had my first experience of this from Gold Box coffee. Bolivian coffee is an interesting one for me, it is one of the first origins I got into when I was first starting out with specialty coffees. Back then HasBean had a number of great Bolivian offerings. Unfortunately the political landscape in Bolivia has made it a little difficult to get quality coffee from the region, but this appears to be slowly changing and this year I've noticed more and more Bolivians on offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular coffee comes from producers Pedro-Pablo, Daniela and Pedro Rodriguez with their Alasitas farm. Gesha is not a &quot;natural&quot; varital in Bolivia and so the Rodriguez family used seeds from the famed La Hacienda farm in Panama (the farm famed for popularising the Gesha varietal). The farm is located in famed coffee growing region Caranavi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the coffee itself. On the dry aroma I am getting mostly floral notes underlined with a caramel. It is not the most boisterous I've ever come across but neither is it a shrinking violet (ignore the pun). An inviting and intriguing coffee for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start by making a filter coffee, in much the usual way - you'll likely be bored of hearing about the technique/equipment by now. Taking the first sip my first thought was &quot;wow&quot; - this is truly an exquisite coffee. As you would expect from a Gesha it is subtle yet fragrant with a lot of complexity. The overarching flavour for me is peach iced tea, it has the juicy peachy quality, the sweetness but also the floral tea-like quality. As the cup cools there are waves after waves of floral notes: honeysuckle, lavendar, jasmine... basically think of any floral note and it will be there. It is really sensitive to temperature of the cup and it is constantly evolving. If you enjoy cup complexity and trying to work out flavour notes this is certainly one for you. The acidity is reasonable but not overbearing, the cup is definitely on the sweeter end. The mouthfeel and body are what I'd describe as &quot;juicy&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the espresso. To dial this one in I found that a med-high sort of temperature works best, for a ratio around 1:2.25 was the sweetspot - perhaps a little shorter than you would expect for a light roast filter coffee. For reference I was pulling this shot with a 5s pre-infuse followed by a 24s pull - a fairly &quot;standard&quot; espresso recipe despite being a filter roast. As an espresso everything great about the filter is just amplified. The mouthfeel gets juicier, the peaches get peachier and the florals really linger on the finish. As much as I loved it as a filter it is even better as an espresso!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This coffee is one I just couldn't get enough of, I was sad to see the bag come to an end. On the price scale it is certainly not cheap, but not quite at the price of the previous Gesha featured (and to be honest I prefer this one to that one - but both were fantastic). For my bank balance's sake I'll probably take a break from the Geshas for a while!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week I have picked another 2020 release. This one was released a few months ago (July) but I totally missed but it has been the soundtrack of my week since discovering it. The artist is Gerald Clayton and the album is called: &quot;Happening: Live at The Village Vanguard&quot;. His debut on the legendary Blue Note label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/029-Happening/Happening.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess the question is: why did this album pass me by for so long? I have to be honest here; Clayton is not somebody I follow religiously. He is (clearly) a great player but I just tend not to connect with his music as much as I do with other players. I have never seen him live under his own name however, perhaps if I saw him live that would have changed (hopefully I will get a chance soon). This album has changed my opinion somewhat and I'll be certain to follow a bit more closely in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you release an album called &quot;Live at The Village Vanguard&quot; you very quickly put a target on your back. Rightly or wrongly peopl will always compare your release to previous albums recorded there (for example Sonny Rollins, John Coltrane and so on). The Village Vanguard is the oldest continuously operated jazz club in the world (next on the list being London's own Ronnie Scott's). I have never had the opportunity to visit the Vanguard yet but it is somewhere I certainly plan to go to. Visually it is a fairly unassuming place, the room itself being essentially &quot;pizza slice&quot; shaped. But as with many of these old jazz clubs it has near perfect acoustics which makes it such a great venue and consequently why so many live albums have been recorded there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clayton can still be considered somewhat of a jazz &quot;up and comer&quot; at 36 years old, but given his &quot;child prodigy&quot; type background it does feel as though he has been around for a long time. In that time he has released 5 albums under his own name (including &quot;Happening&quot;.) And has also recorded and toured with artists such as Charles Lloyd, John Scofield, Roy Hargrove, Ambrose Akinmusire and Peter Bernstein among others. Certainly a well qualified CV for any modern jazz player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The band takes the form of a quintet with the personnel on this album being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gerald Clayton - piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logan Richardson - alto saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walter Smith III - tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Sanders - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marcus Gilmore - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a &quot;star studded&quot; line up full of veterans with loads of acolades - instead a band of relative youngsters trying to make an impact. This gives the album itself a lot of vibrancy and energy, it feels fresh without falling into the trap of being &quot;too modern&quot;. This album has a unique sound but at the same time it feels as though it could have been released any time from the 1950s through to today. This is something that is not easy to achieve.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lzQM_SVM7dM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The music itself is definitely in the &quot;post-bop&quot; universe with lots of twisting and turning rhythmic and harmonic devices used throughout. However in places it also borrows from the modal school and uses some &quot;fusion&quot; ideas (although there are no electric instruments on show here). When not flying at full speed there are also times when things are slowed down and you have time to catch your breath - here the influence of Bill Evans (another artist with a legendary Vanguard album) comes to the fore front. There are also nods towards latin and even hip-hop at times - like much modern jazz it is all about taking a wide variety of influences and trying to mash them together into something coherent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album spans 75 minutes while featuring just 7 tunes - so the band has a chance to really explore each one. 4 of the tunes are Clayton originals and 3 are standards including Ellington's &quot;Take the Coltrane&quot;, &quot;Body and Soul&quot; and Bud Powell's &quot;Celia&quot; - the latter 2 being presented in trio format (offering the sax players a well needed break!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &quot;highlight&quot; picks from the album are &quot;Rejuvenation Agenda&quot; (embedded at the start of this post), one of the Clayton originals. The main theme features some inter-twined sax lines and some really grooving drum work from Marcus Gilmore. The majority of the tune is made up of an extended piano solo from Clayton however. Here he shows off some great virtuosity but always respecting the tune, many of the new breed of jazz musician often forget this and just throw their chops at it. Another highlight is Ellington's &quot;Take the Coltrane&quot; (embedded above) which closes the album. It starts off with some Monk-like solo piano work before breaking into the tune proper. On this tune everybody gets a chance to take an extended solo and really stretch their legs. Each player seems to egg on the next to reach even higher heights. It essentially becomes a clinic on modern jazz improvisation. Again Gilmore's drumming is on point (and includes an awe inspiring solo) - some of the sax work really takes things to the next level. I guess this is fitting for a tune with &quot;Coltrane&quot; in the title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were looking for a representation of the current state of live jazz you could do much worse than pick up a copy of &quot;Happening&quot;. It is one that I have been enjoying throughout the week - I'll certainly keep more of an eye out for Gerald Clayton releases in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/029-Happening/Happening.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/029-Happening/Happening.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Valentine and Adola</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/valentine-adola" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Valentine and Adola" /><published>2020-10-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Valentine-Adola</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/valentine-adola">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-31-Valentine-Adola.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TJxURT1NGro&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with Drop coffee from Stockholm, who were featured last week on the blog. This time we are looking at a more &quot;reasonably priced&quot; coffee instead of a super expensive rare coffee. As is a trend on this blog it is a naturally processed coffee from Ethiopia. Again we are looking at the Guji zone within the Oromoia region - and yet again it is from a washing station owned by Israel Degfa's company. This blog might be becoming a bit predictable! The coffee takes its name from the washing station &quot;Adola&quot;. In addition to running the washing station Israel has also built a school in the local area so that the children can get an education, Drop offer an &quot;extra&quot; version of this coffee which includes a donation directly to the school. To be honest the &quot;extra&quot; cost to a bag of coffee is negligible (about £2.50 at time of writing) in the scheme of things so it is worth opting for this version in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike last week this coffee is one I could use as an espresso! In fact it was (mostly) what I was drinking as an espresso last week while using the Gesha as a filter. Usually I like to keep the same coffee on both filter and espresso as I like to see how the different characteristics come into play with each preparation method. For me it's rare I'll find a coffee that I love prepared one way but hate prepared another. I might prefer one to the other for a specific coffee but there's rarely a coffee that is only suited to one style. And as I have said multiple times on this blog I only ever opt for filter roasts or occassionally omni-roasts as I find these show off the coffees character most clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto the coffee itself. The first thing to notice is this is very light roast, one of the lightest I've had in a while. Grinding for filter on my handgrinder I could physically feel the difference in density compared to previous coffees. The dry aroma coming off the coffee is fairly subdued, there is a little natural processing funkiness and a bit of a floral note but that is about it. This is not a blow your socks off coffee on the nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the filter prepared in the usual way. the first thing that jumped out to me is the funk. If you're unsure of what I mean by &quot;funk&quot; - some natural coffees that have been left in their cherries for a long time essentially start to ferment and develop a flavour profile sometimes referred to as funk. Funk is almost like a &quot;gone off&quot; taste (but in a good way). For me I always associate the funky notes with 2 things: firstly bruised fruits (typically blueberry) and alcohol (particularly fortified alcohol). Adola is not super funky, but it is noticable - espescially if you're like me and don't tend to drink the funky stuff very often. With the funk I also get huge sweetness in the cup combined with the mouthfeel it gives a sticky syrupy kind of quality. In terms of flavour notes blueberry is the first thing that comes to mind. As the cup cools it totally transforms however and the tropical fruits come out to play - it actually reminds me of those old fashioned pineapple cube sweets. All the way through there is a background floral note that adds a lot of elegance to the cup. With this coffee you're also given a really long aftertaste which is great when the coffee tastes so good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you would naturally expect this coffee to be an absolute pig to dial in for espresso given how light the roast is but I actually found it surprisingly forgiving. As you would expect you want to whack up the temperature on your espresso machine to as high as it can reliably go and you want to pull longer shots. For a ratio something like 1:2.75 is a good place to start, I was pulling this one with a quick 3s or so pre-infuse then a 25s pull - so not super quick compared to some. As an espresso this coffee is truly fantastic. The sweet sticky syrupy quality from the filter just gets amplified and it's one of the sweetest cups you'll find. The funkiness is there but is not overbearing, combined with the florals it gives the cup elegance and keeps it interesting. The pineapple cube note is unfortunately nowhere to be found in the espresso but the long aftertaste is thankfully still there. This is a coffee I'd give to somebody unsure about lighter roast coffees for espresso, it is a slightly different experience to a more developed roast but I'd struggle to see how anybody could not find this delicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this is another fantastic coffee from Drop. I said it in my last post but I'll repeat it here: for my money Drop is in the truly &quot;elite&quot; level of coffee roasters. I don't think I've ever had a bad coffee from them, I just wish they were a bit easier to get hold of in the UK!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we're going to look at another relatively recent release (from August 2020). From the Blue Note record label it is Bill Frisell's latest: &quot;Valentine&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/028-Valentine/Valentine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill has appeared a couple of times on this blog but never with an album under his own name. I heard this album the day it was released and have been listening to it since. I am unapologetically a huge Frisell fan-boy so I have been a bit reluctant to feature this album on the blog - I wanted to make sure my fan-boy-ism wasn't causing me to overhype it. But after a few more listens I have come to the conclusion that it is actually that good and is up there with Bill's best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Valentine Bill is joined by regular collaborators: Rudy Royston on the drums and Thomas Morgan on the bass. Although Bill has recorded with countless musicians in the past for his own projects he seems to have a small &quot;inner-circle&quot; with whom he collaborates regularly. I think this is an important part of the magic of some of his recordings/performances since it is very much focussed on interaction and intimacy between band members. In his post-ECM recordings he tends to take relatively simple tunes and elevate them to new levels. Often re-recording the same few tunes in different ways on his various projects. This is in some sense similar to Thelonious Monk who also had a relatively small repertoire but continually re-invented them (unlike say a Duke Ellington who wrote many pieces). Bill is in some sense similar to Monk in other ways too; he often focusses on rhythmic ideas and creating space when playing, and of course he has a history of playing Monk tunes with the Paul Motian band(s) earlier in his career. On this album the title track &quot;Valentine&quot; is quite clearly “an affectionate wink to Thelonious Monk&quot; (to use Bill's own terms) with its twisting time signatures, angular melody and humorous motifs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track list will be familiar to the more seasoned Frisell fan. It features &quot;Winter Always Turns to Spring&quot; featured on &quot;Ghost Town&quot; and &quot;Levees&quot; from the Great Flood documentary. Along with familiar pieces such as &quot;What the World Needs Now&quot; and &quot;Baba Drame&quot; (off &quot;The Intercontinentals&quot;) which he has done renditions of in the past. This habit of re-visiting pieces is very interesting as it allows us to see how Bill has matured and evolved over the years and it invites comparison. Often he will entirely re-work the piece for a new format so it never just feels like re-treading old ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album closes with the civil rights anthem &quot;We Shall Overcome&quot; (another tune that Bill has played many times in the past). This is embedded at the start of this blog, along with a great piece of animation in the music video (I would suggest watching it in its entirety at some point). In this version he sticks very closely to the melody and remaining faithful to the tune itself. Given the civil rights issues in the recent past it feels as though this was intentional. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zU0HS4aMqBg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The latter part of the album features many tracks that seem aimed at the current world landscape: &quot;Winter Always Turns to Spring&quot;, &quot;We Shall Overcome&quot;, &quot;Where Do We Go?&quot; and a beautiful rendition of Bacharach's &quot;What The World Needs Now&quot; (embedded above is a live version from a recent socially distanced outdoor gig). The track titles combined with the dream like quality to the arrangement appears to be Bill's attempt at fostering hope going forward. He is not an artist you'd associate with making political statements typically but I guess that is what he is trying to do with &quot;Valentine&quot;. Perhaps his recent work with Charles Lloyd, who is relatively outspoken, has rubbed off on him?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any writing I do about the music on this album will not do it justice, if you have heard any recording of Bill's from the past 20 years or so you'll know what to expect. This is not a particularly &quot;groundbreaking&quot; album but more of a solidification of the style built up over the past years. It is one of the most complete and polished offerings in the Frisell cannon so is well worthy of your time. The interplay between Frisell/Thomas/Royston is something to behold, it can easily go over your head the first few times you hear them but once you really start to pay attention you can see how well they work as a unit. There is no &quot;flashiness&quot; here just good solid performances all round. As it's incredibly rainy in London right now, I'd definitely recommend the album for some rainy afternoon listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll end with a funny story I have about Bill: a few years ago I saw him live when he was touring the &quot;Guitar in the Space Age&quot; album where he was revisiting tunes from his childhood. It is probably the most &quot;pop&quot; or radio friendly album he has released. I was in the front row and sat next to a party of Americans visiting London. Those who know Frisell know that in addition to the &quot;pop&quot; style recordings on this album he also has his &quot;weird Bill&quot; mode where he uses effect pedals to create crazy sounds and feedback. At the end of one of the pieces you could see Bill get a grin across his face and he bent down to adjust some effect pedals and treated the audience to 60s or so of crazy oscillating feedback and noise (I guess he got a bit bored playing simple melodies every night). At the interval I heard the American party talking to each other saying: &quot;It was a shame about the technical issues with his guitar at the end of that tune&quot;... I'm sure Bill would have found that amusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/028-Valentine/Valentine.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/028-Valentine/Valentine.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Live at Town Hall and Doña Daisy</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/live-at-town-hall-dona-daisy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Live at Town Hall and Doña Daisy" /><published>2020-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Live-At-Town-Hall-Dona-Daisy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/live-at-town-hall-dona-daisy">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-24-Live-At-Town-Hall-Dona-Daisy.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cd5rGoDqTyE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week we take a bit of a different turn with our coffee. We are for the first time stepping away from roasters located in the UK and moving our sights to Sweden. In particular we are looking at Drop Coffee Roasters located in Stockholm. This has been one of my favourite roasters for many years but getting their coffee to the UK is often expensive (as is true with most of the Scandi roasters). I noticed they had a &quot;free shipping&quot; offer however so wanted to make the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the coffee itself is a bit different for this blog too. In browsing the online shop for which coffees to purchase this one jumped out at me. It was a bit expensive so I had my doubts but thought it had been a while since I bought a higher end coffee so went for it. Unfortunately it wasn't until I had ordered that I noticed it was a half-bag size instead of a full-bag size. So what was initially &quot;a bit expensive&quot; turned out to be &quot;very expensive&quot;! So this will be by far the most expensive coffee featured on this blog so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is from San Jose in Central Valley, Costa Rica. The farm is called Finca Don Pepe and the coffee is called Doña Daisy. The farm is a result of a partnership between Daisy and Pepe Fallas who decided to grow coffee in their garden relatively recently - this is not a coffee from a big farming conglomerate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you'd guess from being an expensive coffee (at this level) we are looking at a Gesha varietal - something we have talked about previously in the blog. Gesha is finnicky to grow and finnicky to work with, it requires absolute attention at every stage to get the most out of it. I can't recall seeing a Costa Rican Gesha before this so it is interesting to see how it behaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processing on this coffee is listed as a natural process by Drop but is described more as a &quot;white honey&quot; process in their literature. We have talked about Honey/Pulped-Natural processing before, the &quot;colour&quot; preceeding the &quot;honey&quot; is used as a descriptor for how much of the cherry is left on the seed. White representing the least amount of cherry left (i.e. the closest to a &quot;washed&quot;) - so I am expecting quite a clean elegant cup profile. Following the honey stage the coffee has been left for 25-32 days to dry, which is fairly long for this processing style. This may help to increase the cup complexity - but only the producer will know for sure why they opt for a longer drying style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I only have a half bag of this coffee I did not try to pull an espresso with it - at the price I did not want to risk a &quot;sink job&quot; with a poorly pulled shot when dialing in. Don't worry however! There was still plenty of espresso being consumed at JazzCoffeeStuff towers, the coffees in question may appear in next weeks post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that build up let's get on to the coffee itself. First thing to note about this (and other Drop coffees) is how light the roast is. It is certainly lighter than most other coffees around, if you are more of a medium-light or medium fan this might be a bit much for you. But if like me you enjoy the lighter roasts Drop are always worth a shout. On the dry aroma I get lots of notes, the first thing that came to mind was tangerine. Along with this there are floral notes of jasmine and bergamot and hints of that honey sweetness you get from a pulped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual the filter comes from my Hamasi brewer with (bleached) chemex papers. What is striking about this coffee is its complexity. There is so much going on in the cup. As with a lot of these complex coffees they come alive as they cool. Unfortunately since the roast is so light you need to brew with very hot water. This leaves you like a kid on christmas eve staring at their presents unable to open them, quite a torturous affair. If you don't let the cup cool enough everything gets a bit muddled and it is difficult to get any flavour separation. If you can hold off long enough you are treated with a truly amazing cup of coffee. In a blind cupping you would likely guess this is an Ethiopian coffee given the major flavour notes are peach and florals. However there is more to it than that, the sweetness is very high - syrupy even. This syrupy character carries through to the mouthfeel too. The tangerine note we had on the nose also comes into play too and gives a big juicy and fruity character to the coffee. As you'd expect with Gesha the florals are ever present too, they come more to the forefront the longer you leave the coffee to cool. The coffee also has a strikingly long aftertaste too described on the tasting notes as &quot;strawberry lemonade&quot; - which is an absolutely perfect description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this is a great coffee. Whether it is worth the price of admission is up to you - at around 5 times the price of the other coffees featured on this blog, is it really 5 times the coffee? Probably not, but this is true with most &quot;premium&quot; items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to pick some jazz to pair with such a special coffee is no easy task. In the end I decided to pick Thelonious Monk with his 1959 album &quot;The Thelonious Monk Orchestra at Town Hall&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/027-Live-At-Town-Hall/Live-At-Town-Hall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Monk's first appearance on this blog, I wanted to save him for a special occassion. For me no other artist sums up what jazz is all about more than Thelonious Monk. More than that he transcends the genre to become, in my opinion, one of the greatest artists on any medium. It takes a matter of seconds to know you're listening to Thelonious, even if people try their best to replicate him they never quite nail it - they always sound like a karaoke impersonation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As some readers to this blog may be relatively new to jazz it is worth giving a brief re-cap on Monk's history. He first came to prominence in the 1940s as one of the leading fore-fathers of the be-bop movement. Along with Dizzy Gillespie and Charlie Parker he helped work out how be-bop could be played - most notably in after hours gigs at Minton's jazz club in Harlem (if you gave me a time machine this is one of the places/times I would visit just to hear some of those gigs). A little while later during his career he and fellow pianist Bud Powell were caught in a car with drugs in it. Thelonious refused to rat on his friend and so the police took away his cabaret card. Monk apparently heeded the aphorism &quot;snitches get stitches&quot;. By losing his card he was unable to play in the main jazz clubs in NY (any club serving alcohol). This allowed Monk to be effectively shielded from the jazz scene and develop his own sound. Another consequence was it allowed him the opportunity to collaborate with John Coltrane and create some truly great music. In the latter stages of his career he was plagued by mental illness/neurological issues and his behaviour became more and more erratic before his death in 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monk's compositions (and playing style) are characterised by their twisting rhythmic constructions and angular sounding melodies. I have to admit the first time I heard Monk I didn't &quot;get&quot; it, I heard him too early on in my jazz journey and it was just too much of a stretch at the time. I revisted Monk a few years later and he blew my mind, from then on he became (probably) my favourite jazz artist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another big part of the Monk vibe is the humour, there are very few other artists who use humour in the same way. Not only in the sometimes cartoon-ish playful melodies but also when performing. He would often get up and dance while others were soloing, sometimes interrupting his dancing to add a chord stab at an opportune moment without missing a beat. He was also renowned for his fashion/style being particularly associated with hats - this is also picked up on the tribute to Monk by Eric Dolphy in the tune &quot;Hat and Beard&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Town Hall&quot; album was recorded in Feb 1959, it is one of the rare opportunities to hear Monk in a &quot;big band&quot; context. Most of his other works are in quartet and small-band formats. Here he revisits some of his previous tunes but uses the wider soundscape available to him. You can also hear, perhaps most clearly, his love of Duke Ellington being in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of &quot;behind the scenes&quot; recordings from the concert which give a real insight into Monk's approach, the particularly interested can hunt these down and you can hear Monk describe the tunes to the band and it is very illuminating. I also remember hearing a story that in the rehearsals for this album one of the musicians was unable to lock into the rhythm and so Thelonious pulled him to one side and preceeded to dance in front of him as a way of portraying the rhythm. This gives a great insight into how to think about these tunes, and with that in mind it gives you a whole fresh perspective on the pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 10 musicians appearing on this album so we will not mention all of them. However it is worth noting that this album features a relatively young Donald Byrd on the trumpet, Art Taylor on the drums and is the first collaboration between Monk and Charlie Rouse who played tenor with various Thelonious bands for 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to pick out choice tracks on this recording as all 6 tunes are fantastic. Perhaps the most revered on this album is &quot;Little Rootie Tootie&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). This is quintessetially Monk featuring a twisting rhythmic melody that is both silly yet also completely logical. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/G9Nf2qOqhoE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Up to now we have mostly talked about the fun playful side of Monk, but lest we forget he was also a master at writing hauntingly beautiful sombre tunes. On this album &quot;Monk's Mood&quot; is probably the best example of this. It manages to conjure up great sadness but at the same time just the right amount of happiness and hope. It is a melody that can rattle around your head for weeks after listening to it and the extended band arrangment adds to the weight behind the melody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this album belongs in the &quot;essential&quot; category of jazz albums for me. If you have not heard it before do yourself a favour and hunt down a copy (I'd recommend the original 6 track listing above the extended reissues which don't really add much in my view).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/027-Live-At-Town-Hall/Live-At-Town-Hall.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/027-Live-At-Town-Hall/Live-At-Town-Hall.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rainbow Sign and Debeka</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/rainbow-sign-debeka" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rainbow Sign and Debeka" /><published>2020-10-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Rainbow-Sign-Debeka</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/rainbow-sign-debeka">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-17-Rainbow-Sign-Debeka.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iRRwSAoRX28&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the blog this week we are staying in sunny Margate and sticking with the Curve Coffee Roasters. Yet again we're featuring another Ethiopian coffee, this time a natural process from the Debeka farm - another owned by Israel Degfa (this blog is becoming a bit predictable at this rate). Again we're in the Oromia region but this time the Borena zone (I believe a blog first).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this coffee particularly interesting however is the varietal: Mundo Novo. This is not a varietal one would usually associate with Ethiopia. Typically Mundo Novo is found in South American regions - most notably Brazil. It has also been introduced to Central America but you don't see it often there either, reportedly due to the farmers not liking how tall the plants become. In this case Israel received some plants from a friend on a trip to Brazil and decided to plant then at Debeka. Mundo Novo comes from the typica-bourbon lineage and is a natural mutation of a bourbon, as such it inherits a lot of bourbon characteristics: good cup quality but not particularly resistant to pests nor disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly on to what matters: the coffee itself. The dry aroma consists of two main components for me: a syrupy rich sweet note like a honey and a soft delicate floral note - I would describe it as a white floral instead of a lavender/violet type floral. Overall it is fairly delicate and is not one that will blow you away on the nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start with the filter. Here the &quot;soft&quot; and &quot;delicate&quot; descriptors certainly come to play. Although this is a natural process it is a very clean cup and you couldn't describe this one as a &quot;fruit bomb&quot; like some naturals. There are fruit notes however, the typcial apricot/peach notes you expect with Ethiopian coffees but also a hint of a tropical fruit from the processing. The taste notes on the bag call this pineapple, which I feel is fair. The whitefloral notes certainly come out to play in the aftertaste, it reminds me of the jasmine flowers that come out to bloom in early summer. This is a coffee I find very interesting and have enjoyed coming back to, it is so soft that it doesn't command your attention if you have other things to do but there's enough intrigue to keep you entertained. Another great filter cup from Curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll move onto the espresso here, but before we talk taste notes I'm going to take a brief de-tour into the topic of &quot;puck-prep&quot;. This something that seems to boggle the mind of a novice barista and internet message boards/youtube comments are filled with questions about it. You'll often find people coming up with increasingly complicated preparations to get a &quot;better&quot; shot. In my experience a lot of it amounts to chasing ghosts and simplicity is the best approach, you want to have something you can repeat day in day out without thinking about it. Your approach should match the equipment you have and the type of coffee you drink. For me WDT (Weiss distribution trick) is worth doing but the other prep types (e.g. the OCD spinner style) are a waste of time. To do WDT you essentially &quot;stir&quot; your grounds within the portafilter, this aims to break up any lumps and ensure that the grounds are well &quot;mixed&quot;. Depending on your grinder you might find that the grind quality changes as you grind coffee (due to different weights of beans being above the burrs, popcorning etc.) You want the puck to be as homogeneous as possible so you give it a little stir. That's it, very simple... Yet many get this part wrong: first part to consider is the stirrer itself. You can pick these up from various places such as etsy if you search &quot;WDT tool&quot; - but not all tools are created equally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/026-Rainbow-Sign/WDT.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a WDT tool you want to find one with &quot;thin&quot; lugs, if they are made from thick pieces of metal you risk compressing the grinds more and leaving a &quot;hole&quot; when you remove the tool itself. The next thing to consider is the positioning of the lugs themselves, typically you'll see the lugs being parallel to each other pointing straight down. This gives the tool a very &quot;thin&quot; profile (like the picture above), this is not ideal for mixing the grounds. Instead it's best if you point the lugs outwards to give a &quot;wider&quot; profile, this will allow for much more efficient mixing. You can do this by gently bending the legs at the body of the tool. Ideally you want the lugs to touch the edges of your basket. With your good &quot;wide&quot; WDT tool it's time to start mixing, to do this you want to gently make a circular motion so that you bring grinds from the basket walls towards the centre and vice versa. You do not have to spend long doing this; I like to do 10 rotations in a clockwise direction then 10 in an anti-clockwise direction. After this remove the tool, tamp and go. It's that simple, it should only take a matter of seconds after you get the technique down. I see lots of people say WDT doesn't make a difference, but also lots of videos of people doing it badly - I do wonder if the two are linked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the coffee itself. Again this is the &quot;filter&quot; roasted version of this coffee as is my preference. The roast is fairly light and for filter I use a hand grinder so I can tell these beans are particularly hard. This usually means that a coffee can be a pain to dial in, but actually this one was a pleasure. It is very forgiving and with my setup almost impossible to get it too &quot;wrong&quot;. Unsuprisingly I find it works best with a high temperature and a long pull (1:2.75) which I get through in about 25s. In the cup the same &quot;soft&quot; descriptors come through, it seems to pickup a &quot;melon&quot; type quality in the espresso which I did not notice in the filter. The mouthfeel is big and somewhat creamy in texture. Both acidity and sweetness are medium. In the aftertaste those familiar white florals come through, this seems to be this coffees &quot;signature&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I'm very happy with this coffee and another solid showing from Curve. This is the last of my current batch from Curve but given the two I've had here I'm sure they will appear back on the blog at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this weeks jazz we're looking at another 2020 recent release. This time we're going to Blue Note records and taking on the new Ron Miles album: &quot;Rainbow Sign&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/026-Rainbow-Sign/Rainbow-Sign.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who have not come across Ron before he is a trumpet player and composer from Denver, Colorado. He first started making records in the late 1980s/early 1990s. He is perhaps best known for his collaborations with guitarist Bill Frisell with whom he has released many albums under both his own name and Bill's. The line up on &quot;Rainbow Sign&quot; is the same quintet as on the 2017 &quot;I Am A Man&quot; release, namely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ron Miles: Trumpet and Cornet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jason Moran: Piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Frisell: Electric Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas Morgan: Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brian Blade: Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of modern jazz this is pretty much an &quot;all star&quot; line-up. Each player being regarded as a premier artist in their own right.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/p4-cnRUsIlQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Ron wrote started writing this album in 2018 while looking after his father at the end of his life. Rather than being a maudlin and sombre affair &quot;Rainbow Sign&quot; instead offers up a loving dedication. The album seems to reflect a spiritual awakening for the trumpeter as he comes to terms with his loss. It seems to offer up hope of eternal peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many albums in the Miles and Frisell back catalogue it is hard to classify the music. The music seems to start off in one place and then gently transform into something completely different without the listener noticing. Really it is about letting the music take you to a different place rather than diving in to explore the technicalities in this author's opinion. Ron and Bill are completely on the same page and create new sonic landscapes for us to explore. I often describe the ultimate goal for any artist as creating their own universe and allowing their fans to explore this. I feel this is what separates the merely &quot;very good&quot; musicians to true artists. The Miles/Frisell partnership is capable of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface &quot;Rainbow Sign&quot; seems like an easy-going, simple record - one that can simply blend into your day without demanding much attention. However the more you concentrate the more the album gives, dancing between jazz, folk, blues, world-music and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title track (embedded at the top of this post) is one of the more &quot;jazz&quot; focussed pieces. It is characterised by Ron's beautifully clear and articulate tone giving the melody some weight. Brian Blade is given the chance to swing on this track, perhaps more so than any other track. Elsewhere Blade offers up subtle textures to his playing which is perhaps what he is known best for. Bill and Jason take on the comping duties, each relying on sparsity to give the piece space. It feels like more than a little nod towards Thelonious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is followed by &quot;The Rumor&quot; which feels very much like a tune that could have featured in any number of Frisell recordings. The main melody is driven via Bill's guitar. It has the feel of an old Americana tune (albeit revisited through the lens of modern jazz). The second half of the tune features some of Miles most subtle playing, there's no hint of ego here - letting Bill take a bit of the limelight. This lifts the piece into a well rounded composition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album ends with the piece &quot;A Kind Word&quot; which almost has a &quot;rock&quot; vibe. Knowing that this album is dedicated to his late father this piece feels a bit like a eulogy.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lJxzoS11z8c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This is another great album released in 2020. It is well worth hunting down a copy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/026-Rainbow-Sign/Rainbow-Sign.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/026-Rainbow-Sign/Rainbow-Sign.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hero Trio and Chelbesa</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/hero-trio-chelbesa" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hero Trio and Chelbesa" /><published>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Hero-Trio-Chelbesa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/hero-trio-chelbesa">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-10-Hero-Trio-Chelbesa.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CrUm4CsKW8c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we have a new roaster appearing on the blog: Curve Coffee Roasters - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.curveroasters.co.uk/&quot;&gt;https://www.curveroasters.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt; - based in Margate. They have been on my &quot;to try&quot; list for a while but I never got round to it until now. They come with a reputation for roasting some truly great coffees and their pricing is very reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you would expect with this blog I stuck with their &quot;filter roast&quot; offerings (they also offer an &quot;espresso roast&quot; option). For me personally I tend to find these speak to me more than the espresso roasts - admittedly you need to work a bit harder to get a good espresso out of one though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is from the Chelbesa village within the Gedeb Zone of the Oromia Region. of Ethiopia. This coffee is made up from contributions from a number of small holders within the village and the coffee is a washed process. This is generally a recipe for a coffee I will enjoy, washed coffees from this area are generally my &quot;go to&quot;. After a bit of digging it appears this coffee has a cupping score of 89.5 - which is very high!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado lets get right in to the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I get a sweet honey note paired with the typical floral notes one would expect from this sort of coffee. The aromas are not too strong coming off the grinds, everything is soft and subtle. As we've said before on this blog: the dry aroma can give you some indication of a coffees character but does not tell you everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual starting with our usual filter technique: one word to get us started is &quot;wow&quot;. This coffee is a near perfect example of why washed coffees from this area are so prized. The first thing I notice is an apricot or peach note, a sweet but not too sweet character. These flavours slowly morph into a melon type flavour the more the cup cools. Then of course the florals: bergamot is clearly present along with violets and lavendar in the background. The mouthfeel is soft, creamy but slightly syrupy - it is not one of the very thin washed Ethiopians completely devoid of mouthfeel. As one  would expect the aftertaste is a lingering black tea affair. Overall very enjoyable!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso. This one I found a little finnicky to dial in, all my shots tasted good but there was a certain astringency in the aftertaste that took a while to sort out. In the end I found a ratio of 1:2.5 was about right - I didn't want to go superlong with this one since I knew it had a good mouthfeel I didn't want to go to waste. I went for a pull of around 25s which is reasonably quick but not excessively. The story was the same with the temperature: hot but not super-hot. As a shot many of the notes from the filter came through, however the florals took more of a backseat. With the mouthfeel and the very subtle florals the &quot;honey&quot; descriptor from the dry aroma became more apt. If you're willing to put the work in you will be rewarded for it with this coffee but I see why they would label this a &quot;filter&quot; roast - certainly not a coffee I'd recommend to the novice barista for espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is certianly a very good coffee and one I very much enjoyed, hopefully this is representative of what Curve can do - I'm sure I'll be trying them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jazz this week is a 2020 release from Rudresh Mahanthappa called &quot;Hero Trio&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rudresh is an alto-saxophonist based in New York. He is perhaps best known for his work with pianist Vijay Iyer with whom he has collaborated often. As well as regularly featuring in Downbeat polls he is also musical director at Princeton - so quite a pedigree for a modern jazz musician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with his work I would describe Rudresh's playing as being fairly &quot;outside&quot;, it is technical and wild but at the same time he still respects the music and song structure. I like free jazz but I sometimes struggle with the really avant garde artists who completely throw out all semblance of musical structure. Mahanthappa also spent many years studying Indian classical music - and this often comes out in his playing, however this never comes across as forced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the album &quot;Hero Trio&quot; Rudresh pays tribute to some of his favourite artists including: John Coltrane, Keith Jarrett, Ornette Coleman and of course no alto saxophonist would not list Charlie Parker as an influence (Rudresh even released &quot;Bird Calls&quot; in 2015 - an entire album dedicated to Parker). Alongside these jazz stalwarts there are even pieces from Stevie Wonder and Johnny Cash. We should not think of this as simply rehashing a number of standards however, each tune has been majorly reworked and given its own style. The music feels modern while still paying respect to the past - this is certainly not easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the album name suggests the band is a trio format consisting of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rudresh Mahanthappa - Alto Saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;François Moutin - Acoustic Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rudy Royston - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rudresh the band as &quot;superheros&quot; even dressing up the band in suitable costumes for some of the promotional material. Listening to the album it is easy to understand why. The band is totally locked in, this allows them to take real risks in the arrangments. The album feels like being on a rollercoaster, you know you're in safe hands despite travelling a mile a minute. In a piano-less trio format the band is allowed to really stretch their legs, without chords tying down what is &quot;acceptable&quot; to play Mahathappa (and Moutin) is free to play without inhibition - something he really takes advantage of. The extra space in the mix allows Royston to really flex his chops too, Rudy is one of my favourite current jazz drummers but he is probably more well known for playing sparsely - so it is nice to hear him let loose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with &quot;Red Cross&quot; a Charlie Parker tune. Whereas Parker's classic bounces along with a jovial be-bop type rhythm, the Hero Trio goes for a much more direct hard hitting approach. This is somewhat characteristic of the album as a whole - this is music that demands your attention, it's difficult to imagine this being &quot;background music&quot;. Mahathappa relies on a lot of chromaticism throughout his solo, this along with his phrasing certainly point towards his Indian classical background. It is a sound that is uniquely his, I don't think you would mistake him for anybody else out there today.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NSmY80pmavE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

One of the &quot;non-jazz&quot; tributes on the album is to the Johnny Cash classic &quot;Ring of Fire&quot;. I sometimes find it worrisome when jazz artists take on these really well known tunes. It is very easy for them to become either: instantly forgettable as they don't take any risks (and it's just a ploy to sell records) or they use so much reharmonization that the original tune is completely unrecognisable. Thankfully Mahanthappa and crew take on &quot;Ring of Fire&quot; seriously and pay it the respect it deserves. They do not take too many liberties with the melody, instead they play rhythmically instead. This gives the tune some energy and freshness without straying too far away from the spirit of the piece. Of course the solos are free and wild as one would expect, however they are some of the most restrained on the entire album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlight of the album for me however is &quot;The Windup&quot; a Keith Jarrett piece (and one of my all time favourite tunes from the Jarrett songbook). Covering a Jarrett piece without having a single instrument capable of playng chords is certainly a challenge. This really goes to show just how talented Moutin is as a bass player, much of the main melody falls on him and he needs to drive the music forward. At the same time he needs to imply the chords of the piece so that it doesn't feel &quot;hollow&quot;. About mid-way through the tune when comping Mahanthappa's solos there is some of the best bass playing you are likely to hear. A truly fantastic acheivement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album is another 2020 banger, if you are into jazz you definitely should hunt this album down. For a rank newbie to the world of jazz this might be a bit much as a first step and it'd perhaps be worth familiarising yourself with the source material first - but certainly put this one of the list of albums to catchup on later. I feel this is an album I'll come back to time and time again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stein Urheim and La Lima</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/stein-urheim-la-lima" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stein Urheim and La Lima" /><published>2020-10-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Stein-Urheim-La-Lima</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/stein-urheim-la-lima">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-03-Stein-Urheim-La-Lima.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KUAaMLeE4OE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with Whitstable based roaster Eigthy Seven Plus. This time we have a Peruvian coffee from the La Coipa district, in the north west corner of the country not too far from the border with Ecuador. This is a washed Caturra/Bourbon coffee from a farm called La Lima owned by Eduardo Campos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we noted before the roaster takes its name from dealing with coffees with an SCA rating in excess of 87 exclusively. This particular coffee has a score of 88 - the highest currently offered by the roaster. It is also the most expensive they currently have at £15 per 250g - which is still very reasonable for a coffee of this quality - this comes out to around 90p per (large) cup of coffee so compared to what you pay in a cafe a veritable bargain!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've mentioned in the past Peru is not an origin I naturally gravitate towards, I don't dislike Peru and don't avoid at all costs but usually other origins speak to me more so I rarely order Peruvians. This year however I have found some fantastic Peruvian coffees. I tend to find that each year there is one origin where the stars have aligned and they produce fantastic coffee. This feels like Peru's year to me and maybe I'll start buying more Peruvians from now on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado lets get onto what is important: the cup. First things first the dry aroma: I get faint hints of tropical fruits (that I am unable to put my finger on) but really the big notes are: raspberry, apricot and florals. It is quite a delicate aroma, if you want a big bold fruit bomb it might not be for you. This is sophsticated and refined, these are charactersitics I find myself looking for more and more these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we will start by looking at the filter, again my usual set up of using my Hasami brewer with chemex papers and relying on a &quot;pulse pour&quot; style technique to avoid excess agitation and so I end up with a super clean cup. The first thing to note is this coffee &quot;grinds coarse&quot; by which I mean for a given grind setting you'll likely find drawdown is quicker than you expect. If you are a relative coffee novice one of the first things you might try to do is &quot;chase&quot; a specific time for a brew and fine up the grind (I used to do this when I started). I personally think this is a bad idea, I don't believe there's a &quot;magic&quot; drawdown time that will fix all woes. Instead any adjustment should be by taste alone - and it was clear this coffee liked the shorter drawdown! In all the brewtime I acheieved was around 2:20s on average - many brewguides will tell you to hit 3:00-4:00 for an &quot;optimal&quot; cup. My cup did not suffer from this, in fact I tried to hit a 3:30 drawdown out of curiousity one day and it made the coffee 100 times worse, it became more bitter and harsh and lost a lot of flavour separation in the process. As always your tastebuds are the best measuring device!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter coffee we get a cup that pretty much mimics the dry aroma. It is a delicate affair and shows real sophistication. The major underlying flavour is raspberry, the tartness and acidity along with the sweetness therein.  This is supported by the delicate juicy apricot type note (which itself brings more sweetness). Throughout the cup the florals are prominent too, while the cup is hot they take a bit of a back seat but as it cools they come to the front. They remind me mostly of a bergamot Earl-grey type floral but there are also plenty of white jasmine notes too. This coffee really evolves as it cools so try and savour it (if you can). In terms of acidity I'd say it is fairly low (but does not taste flat) and the sweetness high, but the cup is very complex and interesting. Definitely a very enjoyable cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso, again this is a filter roast so all the usual rules apply. This coffee seems to be slightly lighter in roast compared to the previous Kayon Mountain (from memory and by eye - I don't own a meter to check this). However I found that it actually benefits from a more &quot;typical&quot; recipe of about 1:2.2 and a medium heat, with a PI time of 10s then a 27s pull - a very &quot;standard&quot; recipe for an espresso and not usually what you expect from a filter roast. As an espresso I found a new note becomes more prominent: Pears. The raspberry note seems less noticable than in the filter but otherwise all the familiar notes appear. Being so subtle some of the florals are a little harder to find but they're still there, but cold espresso is disgusting so they don't really get a chance to speak as the drink cools. As such I think while it makes a good espresso this coffee really shines in the filter settings. I don't drink milky coffee but I imagine this one would struggle to punch through so look elsewhere if you're looking for a flat-white!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto this weeks jazz. This one might be a bit contentious to the jazz purists out there, I could see this causing an &quot;Is this jazz?&quot; argument. Personally I don't care where the boundaries are - as long as the music is good! And this record is certainly good. It is from 2014 and is on the Norwegian &quot;Hubro&quot; record label: Stein Urheim - Stein Urheim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stein Urheim is a Norwegian jazz guitarist/composer. His self titled album is not his debut album having released (to my knowledge) 2 albums under his own name before this and multiple collaborations. The self titled album marks a bit of a change of direction however. The album is essentially a solo project, Stein plays a number of instruments on the recording (guitars, flutes, harmonica, slide tamboura, fretless bouzouki, gu qin, mandolin, langeleik, charango, banjo, analog synths and effects),  there is a brief cameo by Jørgen Træen who adds some synth parts. In essense it is a &quot;one man band&quot; however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album was recorded entirely at the home of Ole Bull (a Norwegian violinist of the 1800s) - the space was designed with acoustics in mind with each room being tailored for small band concerts. This is distinctly noticable in the recording as it has a very &quot;warm&quot; sound and does not &quot;feel&quot; like a cold studio enviroment. In fact I would say in terms of recording quality I can't think of many albums released in the past 20 years or so that come close to having this level of &quot;organic&quot; recording. It is truly a pleasure to listen to, if you can find a vinyl copy I would strongly suggest picking it up as it's worth listening to on a quality sound system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music itself is no slouch either. Each piece is highly ambitious with many layers and interacting tracks. While it would take an eternity to unpick all the key and time signature changes that happen, all this doesn't really matter. Each piece is essentially a little look into a distinct universe, Urheim takes us on a journey - they are essentially films in musical form. Exact details matter less than the overall &quot;feeling&quot; of each piece. There are many influences throughout the album from the obvious jazz and blues, through traditional folk, surf, western classical and baroque through the middle east, hasidic and eastern musical traditions. The music slowly meanders through these styles but it never sounds forced, it is all done in a respectful and natural way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the standout pieces on the album for me is the 11 minute long &quot;After the Festival&quot; (embedded above). This piece is probably the most playful and joyous on the album, it features folk, flamenco and Carribean elements prominently along with atmospheric drones. Towards the end of the track a simple beautiful melody appears out of the chaos - what is so clever is that this melody has been there (in various forms) throughout the track it's just been obscured. This is a &quot;trick&quot; that Stein relies on for a few of the tracks on the album and it gives the project a real cohesion which I think makes it such a memorable album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/an9C8kvNjYw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another stand-out piece is &quot;Beijing Blues&quot; - which as the name suggests is a juxtaposition of eastern-classical and blues traditions, there is even a bit of an Indian raga thrown in for good measure. The subtle use of harmonica towards the end of the track just lifts the whole piece as it slowly morphs into a blues swagger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an album that is very hard to do justice through words, I find listening to it a very visceral experience. You are transported to different worlds when you listen to it. It is an album that rewards those willing to dedicate the 40 minutes or so to listen to it without distraction - I would recommend nothing more than a comfy chair and a big pot of coffee as an accompaniment. However it can also blend into the background of your day, providing a soundtrack to whatever else you are doing. Although it relies on complex arrangement and harmony in places, it is not at all distracting. It is not often you find music that can take on both of these functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a superb album that is well worth hunting down. For my money one of the best albums released in the past 10 years and a modern classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>