<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-10T07:00:20-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hero Trio and Chelbesa</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/hero-trio-chelbesa" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hero Trio and Chelbesa" /><published>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Hero-Trio-Chelbesa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/hero-trio-chelbesa">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-10-Hero-Trio-Chelbesa.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CrUm4CsKW8c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we have a new roaster appearing on the blog: Curve Coffee Roasters - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.curveroasters.co.uk/&quot;&gt;https://www.curveroasters.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt; - based in Margate. They have been on my &quot;to try&quot; list for a while but I never got round to it until now. They come with a reputation for roasting some truly great coffees and their pricing is very reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you would expect with this blog I stuck with their &quot;filter roast&quot; offerings (they also offer an &quot;espresso roast&quot; option). For me personally I tend to find these speak to me more than the espresso roasts - admittedly you need to work a bit harder to get a good espresso out of one though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is from the Chelbesa village within the Gedeb Zone of the Oromia Region. of Ethiopia. This coffee is made up from contributions from a number of small holders within the village and the coffee is a washed process. This is generally a recipe for a coffee I will enjoy, washed coffees from this area are generally my &quot;go to&quot;. After a bit of digging it appears this coffee has a cupping score of 89.5 - which is very high!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado lets get right in to the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I get a sweet honey note paired with the typical floral notes one would expect from this sort of coffee. The aromas are not too strong coming off the grinds, everything is soft and subtle. As we've said before on this blog: the dry aroma can give you some indication of a coffees character but does not tell you everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual starting with our usual filter technique: one word to get us started is &quot;wow&quot;. This coffee is a near perfect example of why washed coffees from this area are so prized. The first thing I notice is an apricot or peach note, a sweet but not too sweet character. These flavours slowly morph into a melon type flavour the more the cup cools. Then of course the florals: bergamot is clearly present along with violets and lavendar in the background. The mouthfeel is soft, creamy but slightly syrupy - it is not one of the very thin washed Ethiopians completely devoid of mouthfeel. As one  would expect the aftertaste is a lingering black tea affair. Overall very enjoyable!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso. This one I found a little finnicky to dial in, all my shots tasted good but there was a certain astringency in the aftertaste that took a while to sort out. In the end I found a ratio of 1:2.5 was about right - I didn't want to go superlong with this one since I knew it had a good mouthfeel I didn't want to go to waste. I went for a pull of around 25s which is reasonably quick but not excessively. The story was the same with the temperature: hot but not super-hot. As a shot many of the notes from the filter came through, however the florals took more of a backseat. With the mouthfeel and the very subtle florals the &quot;honey&quot; descriptor from the dry aroma became more apt. If you're willing to put the work in you will be rewarded for it with this coffee but I see why they would label this a &quot;filter&quot; roast - certainly not a coffee I'd recommend to the novice barista for espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is certianly a very good coffee and one I very much enjoyed, hopefully this is representative of what Curve can do - I'm sure I'll be trying them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jazz this week is a 2020 release from Rudresh Mahanthappa called &quot;Hero Trio&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rudresh is an alto-saxophonist based in New York. He is perhaps best known for his work with pianist Vijay Iyer with whom he has collaborated often. As well as regularly featuring in Downbeat polls he is also musical director at Princeton - so quite a pedigree for a modern jazz musician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with his work I would describe Rudresh's playing as being fairly &quot;outside&quot;, it is technical and wild but at the same time he still respects the music and song structure. I like free jazz but I sometimes struggle with the really avant garde artists who completely throw out all semblance of musical structure. Mahanthappa also spent many years studying Indian classical music - and this often comes out in his playing, however this never comes across as forced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the album &quot;Hero Trio&quot; Rudresh pays tribute to some of his favourite artists including: John Coltrane, Keith Jarrett, Ornette Coleman and of course no alto saxophonist would not list Charlie Parker as an influence (Rudresh even released &quot;Bird Calls&quot; in 2015 - an entire album dedicated to Parker). Alongside these jazz stalwarts there are even pieces from Stevie Wonder and Johnny Cash. We should not think of this as simply rehashing a number of standards however, each tune has been majorly reworked and given its own style. The music feels modern while still paying respect to the past - this is certainly not easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the album name suggests the band is a trio format consisting of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rudresh Mahanthappa - Alto Saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;François Moutin - Acoustic Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rudy Royston - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rudresh the band as &quot;superheros&quot; even dressing up the band in suitable costumes for some of the promotional material. Listening to the album it is easy to understand why. The band is totally locked in, this allows them to take real risks in the arrangments. The album feels like being on a rollercoaster, you know you're in safe hands despite travelling a mile a minute. In a piano-less trio format the band is allowed to really stretch their legs, without chords tying down what is &quot;acceptable&quot; to play Mahathappa (and Moutin) is free to play without inhibition - something he really takes advantage of. The extra space in the mix allows Royston to really flex his chops too, Rudy is one of my favourite current jazz drummers but he is probably more well known for playing sparsely - so it is nice to hear him let loose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with &quot;Red Cross&quot; a Charlie Parker tune. Whereas Parker's classic bounces along with a jovial be-bop type rhythm, the Hero Trio goes for a much more direct hard hitting approach. This is somewhat characteristic of the album as a whole - this is music that demands your attention, it's difficult to imagine this being &quot;background music&quot;. Mahathappa relies on a lot of chromaticism throughout his solo, this along with his phrasing certainly point towards his Indian classical background. It is a sound that is uniquely his, I don't think you would mistake him for anybody else out there today.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NSmY80pmavE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

One of the &quot;non-jazz&quot; tributes on the album is to the Johnny Cash classic &quot;Ring of Fire&quot;. I sometimes find it worrisome when jazz artists take on these really well known tunes. It is very easy for them to become either: instantly forgettable as they don't take any risks (and it's just a ploy to sell records) or they use so much reharmonization that the original tune is completely unrecognisable. Thankfully Mahanthappa and crew take on &quot;Ring of Fire&quot; seriously and pay it the respect it deserves. They do not take too many liberties with the melody, instead they play rhythmically instead. This gives the tune some energy and freshness without straying too far away from the spirit of the piece. Of course the solos are free and wild as one would expect, however they are some of the most restrained on the entire album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlight of the album for me however is &quot;The Windup&quot; a Keith Jarrett piece (and one of my all time favourite tunes from the Jarrett songbook). Covering a Jarrett piece without having a single instrument capable of playng chords is certainly a challenge. This really goes to show just how talented Moutin is as a bass player, much of the main melody falls on him and he needs to drive the music forward. At the same time he needs to imply the chords of the piece so that it doesn't feel &quot;hollow&quot;. About mid-way through the tune when comping Mahanthappa's solos there is some of the best bass playing you are likely to hear. A truly fantastic acheivement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album is another 2020 banger, if you are into jazz you definitely should hunt this album down. For a rank newbie to the world of jazz this might be a bit much as a first step and it'd perhaps be worth familiarising yourself with the source material first - but certainly put this one of the list of albums to catchup on later. I feel this is an album I'll come back to time and time again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stein Urheim and La Lima</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/stein-urheim-la-lima" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stein Urheim and La Lima" /><published>2020-10-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Stein-Urheim-La-Lima</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/stein-urheim-la-lima">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-03-Stein-Urheim-La-Lima.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KUAaMLeE4OE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with Whitstable based roaster Eigthy Seven Plus. This time we have a Peruvian coffee from the La Coipa district, in the north west corner of the country not too far from the border with Ecuador. This is a washed Caturra/Bourbon coffee from a farm called La Lima owned by Eduardo Campos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we noted before the roaster takes its name from dealing with coffees with an SCA rating in excess of 87 exclusively. This particular coffee has a score of 88 - the highest currently offered by the roaster. It is also the most expensive they currently have at £15 per 250g - which is still very reasonable for a coffee of this quality - this comes out to around 90p per (large) cup of coffee so compared to what you pay in a cafe a veritable bargain!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've mentioned in the past Peru is not an origin I naturally gravitate towards, I don't dislike Peru and don't avoid at all costs but usually other origins speak to me more so I rarely order Peruvians. This year however I have found some fantastic Peruvian coffees. I tend to find that each year there is one origin where the stars have aligned and they produce fantastic coffee. This feels like Peru's year to me and maybe I'll start buying more Peruvians from now on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado lets get onto what is important: the cup. First things first the dry aroma: I get faint hints of tropical fruits (that I am unable to put my finger on) but really the big notes are: raspberry, apricot and florals. It is quite a delicate aroma, if you want a big bold fruit bomb it might not be for you. This is sophsticated and refined, these are charactersitics I find myself looking for more and more these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we will start by looking at the filter, again my usual set up of using my Hasami brewer with chemex papers and relying on a &quot;pulse pour&quot; style technique to avoid excess agitation and so I end up with a super clean cup. The first thing to note is this coffee &quot;grinds coarse&quot; by which I mean for a given grind setting you'll likely find drawdown is quicker than you expect. If you are a relative coffee novice one of the first things you might try to do is &quot;chase&quot; a specific time for a brew and fine up the grind (I used to do this when I started). I personally think this is a bad idea, I don't believe there's a &quot;magic&quot; drawdown time that will fix all woes. Instead any adjustment should be by taste alone - and it was clear this coffee liked the shorter drawdown! In all the brewtime I acheieved was around 2:20s on average - many brewguides will tell you to hit 3:00-4:00 for an &quot;optimal&quot; cup. My cup did not suffer from this, in fact I tried to hit a 3:30 drawdown out of curiousity one day and it made the coffee 100 times worse, it became more bitter and harsh and lost a lot of flavour separation in the process. As always your tastebuds are the best measuring device!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter coffee we get a cup that pretty much mimics the dry aroma. It is a delicate affair and shows real sophistication. The major underlying flavour is raspberry, the tartness and acidity along with the sweetness therein.  This is supported by the delicate juicy apricot type note (which itself brings more sweetness). Throughout the cup the florals are prominent too, while the cup is hot they take a bit of a back seat but as it cools they come to the front. They remind me mostly of a bergamot Earl-grey type floral but there are also plenty of white jasmine notes too. This coffee really evolves as it cools so try and savour it (if you can). In terms of acidity I'd say it is fairly low (but does not taste flat) and the sweetness high, but the cup is very complex and interesting. Definitely a very enjoyable cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso, again this is a filter roast so all the usual rules apply. This coffee seems to be slightly lighter in roast compared to the previous Kayon Mountain (from memory and by eye - I don't own a meter to check this). However I found that it actually benefits from a more &quot;typical&quot; recipe of about 1:2.2 and a medium heat, with a PI time of 10s then a 27s pull - a very &quot;standard&quot; recipe for an espresso and not usually what you expect from a filter roast. As an espresso I found a new note becomes more prominent: Pears. The raspberry note seems less noticable than in the filter but otherwise all the familiar notes appear. Being so subtle some of the florals are a little harder to find but they're still there, but cold espresso is disgusting so they don't really get a chance to speak as the drink cools. As such I think while it makes a good espresso this coffee really shines in the filter settings. I don't drink milky coffee but I imagine this one would struggle to punch through so look elsewhere if you're looking for a flat-white!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto this weeks jazz. This one might be a bit contentious to the jazz purists out there, I could see this causing an &quot;Is this jazz?&quot; argument. Personally I don't care where the boundaries are - as long as the music is good! And this record is certainly good. It is from 2014 and is on the Norwegian &quot;Hubro&quot; record label: Stein Urheim - Stein Urheim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stein Urheim is a Norwegian jazz guitarist/composer. His self titled album is not his debut album having released (to my knowledge) 2 albums under his own name before this and multiple collaborations. The self titled album marks a bit of a change of direction however. The album is essentially a solo project, Stein plays a number of instruments on the recording (guitars, flutes, harmonica, slide tamboura, fretless bouzouki, gu qin, mandolin, langeleik, charango, banjo, analog synths and effects),  there is a brief cameo by Jørgen Træen who adds some synth parts. In essense it is a &quot;one man band&quot; however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album was recorded entirely at the home of Ole Bull (a Norwegian violinist of the 1800s) - the space was designed with acoustics in mind with each room being tailored for small band concerts. This is distinctly noticable in the recording as it has a very &quot;warm&quot; sound and does not &quot;feel&quot; like a cold studio enviroment. In fact I would say in terms of recording quality I can't think of many albums released in the past 20 years or so that come close to having this level of &quot;organic&quot; recording. It is truly a pleasure to listen to, if you can find a vinyl copy I would strongly suggest picking it up as it's worth listening to on a quality sound system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music itself is no slouch either. Each piece is highly ambitious with many layers and interacting tracks. While it would take an eternity to unpick all the key and time signature changes that happen, all this doesn't really matter. Each piece is essentially a little look into a distinct universe, Urheim takes us on a journey - they are essentially films in musical form. Exact details matter less than the overall &quot;feeling&quot; of each piece. There are many influences throughout the album from the obvious jazz and blues, through traditional folk, surf, western classical and baroque through the middle east, hasidic and eastern musical traditions. The music slowly meanders through these styles but it never sounds forced, it is all done in a respectful and natural way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the standout pieces on the album for me is the 11 minute long &quot;After the Festival&quot; (embedded above). This piece is probably the most playful and joyous on the album, it features folk, flamenco and Carribean elements prominently along with atmospheric drones. Towards the end of the track a simple beautiful melody appears out of the chaos - what is so clever is that this melody has been there (in various forms) throughout the track it's just been obscured. This is a &quot;trick&quot; that Stein relies on for a few of the tracks on the album and it gives the project a real cohesion which I think makes it such a memorable album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/an9C8kvNjYw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another stand-out piece is &quot;Beijing Blues&quot; - which as the name suggests is a juxtaposition of eastern-classical and blues traditions, there is even a bit of an Indian raga thrown in for good measure. The subtle use of harmonica towards the end of the track just lifts the whole piece as it slowly morphs into a blues swagger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an album that is very hard to do justice through words, I find listening to it a very visceral experience. You are transported to different worlds when you listen to it. It is an album that rewards those willing to dedicate the 40 minutes or so to listen to it without distraction - I would recommend nothing more than a comfy chair and a big pot of coffee as an accompaniment. However it can also blend into the background of your day, providing a soundtrack to whatever else you are doing. Although it relies on complex arrangement and harmony in places, it is not at all distracting. It is not often you find music that can take on both of these functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a superb album that is well worth hunting down. For my money one of the best albums released in the past 10 years and a modern classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tributes and Kayon Mountain</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/tributes-kayon-mountain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tributes and Kayon Mountain" /><published>2020-09-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Tributes-Kayon-Mountain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/tributes-kayon-mountain">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-09-26-Tributes-Kayon-Mountain.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/re_O4_u9VMY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we feature a new roaster called &quot;Eighty Seven Plus&quot;, not only are they new to the blog htey are relatively new in general - being set up around 1 year ago. They take their name from their coffee ethos of only using coffees that score in excess of 87 points on the SCA scale. We have talked about the pros/cons of the SCA scale in the past so we won't start that conversation again - suffice as to say 87 is usually the threshold I look for personally when deciding on a coffee. I think 87 is a good compromise between cup quality and cost, if you limit yourself to only purchasing 90 plus coffees you will have a relatively small number to choose from and you will end up paying a lot! With 87 coffees you can generally purchase them for fairly reasoanble prices but still get some really great flavours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's worth mentioning the company also has an app (via Apple app store/Google play) - I have not used this as despite working in tech I am a bit of a luddite when it comes to using tech. It appears the app allows you to take notes about the coffees and share your tasting notes with the wider community which is quite a nice idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is (another) Ethiopian - the 4th in a row for this blog. This time however it is washed whereas the previous were all natural. Given the choice I am typically more of a fan of washed coffees compared to other processing methods since I value cup clarity most of all. Like the preceeding coffees this too is from the Guji zone in the Oromia region. the farm itself is called &quot;Kayon Mountain&quot; - this is a farm I am particularly familiar with and have had coffee from them via many different roasters over the years. As such I have a number of preconceptions about how I expect this one to taste and behave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving right in to the dry aroma: the first thing that hits me is a caramel sort of smell, this is a little unexpected for a coffee like this so it stuck out. However the major notes you would expect from a coffee like this are there: peaches and stone fruits along with florals and a hint of citrus. All coffees from Eighty Seven Plus are labelled as a &quot;filter&quot; roast which I think is fair, this coffee is not quite as light roast as some others I have seen however. As usual we start with a filter in a v60 type funnel with a chemex paper. As I remembered from drinking this coffee in the past the first thing that comes to mind for me is &quot;soft&quot; - the mouthfeel is soft and delicate and the flavours are gentle and do not punch you in the face. As with most washed coffees from this region we are treated to delicate floral notes of lavender and jasmine along with lemon-y citrus and peach notes. As it cools it becomes increasingly &quot;tea like&quot;. However there is a couple of &quot;strange&quot; notes that come back time and time again with Kayon Mountain coffees to me: the first is &quot;strawberry milkshake&quot; - a combination of flavour notes and the softer mouthfeel. And &quot;bubblegum&quot; - in this example it's rather faint so if I wasn't expecting it I might not have picked up on it. But for me it is unmistakable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso: this is an Ethiopian washed coffee roasted for filter so there are no prizes for guessing the advice I give for pulling shots on this one! Hot, fast and long are the orders of the day! Owing to the density of Ethiopian beans you'll likely find that you need to set your grinder &quot;coarser&quot; to achieve the same flow-rate as you would from a central American coffee. In the end I settled on a ratio of 1:2.75 being optimal here. This seemed to be the turning point where the shot didn't get any sweeter, pulling longer than this just ended up giving thinner mouthfeel. I was pulling these shots in around 22s with a slight pre-infusion of a couple of seconds. With a &quot;shrinking violet&quot; coffee like this without any powerful flavour notes we can often find the espresso gets a bit &quot;bland&quot; - but this one does not suffer that fate. The similar flavour profile from the filter is still there but the &quot;bubblegum&quot; is able to push through a bit more and becomes more noticable. It is a real treat to find washed Ethiopian espressos like this, given a choice this is the style I go for every time. It will come as no surprise that I'll say I recommend trying this one as an espresso (even though it is considered a filter coffee).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both the filter and the espresso this coffee is super clean and has a limited clean aftertaste. Overall a strong showing from a new roaster and hopefully indicative of what else they will offer in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto this weeks jazz. We're taking a bit of a different approach this time, I am recommending an album that was released yesterday (25th September 2020) - as such I've only listened to this a few times so far so I won't dive too deeply into what is going on since I haven't had chance to study it yet, perhaps I'll revisit this one in a later blog once I've had chance to fully digest it all and can see if my perceptions change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album is called &quot;Tributes&quot; and it is by Nordic saxophonist Marius Neset, released on the German ACT record label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/023-Tributes/Tributes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marius Neset is one of the &quot;next generation&quot; of jazz musicians, being 35 years old which is young for a jazz artist these days. He released his first album in 2008 and has 11 albums to his name currently (plus a few more as a co-leader or guest slots). I first came across him via his &quot;Golden Xplosion&quot; album in 2011 - a truly fantastic album, a little rough around the edges but it was pretty clear to me he was destined to be a leading name in jazz as he matured. After a few more great albums (including the terrific &quot;Sun Blowing&quot; with Lars Danielsson) I had very high hopes for him. But his last few albums disappointed me a little. They were not terrible but he seemed to get a little lost, the high octane energy he was known for initially disappeared and the compositions - while nice - did not set the world on fire. With &quot;Tributes&quot; however he appears to have worked out how to balance the energy with solid composition and he has created the album I have been waiting for from him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Neset sax style is clearly very influenced by Michael Brecker, as most modern sax players are, however he combines this with a strong influence of chamber music (and various other European classical movements). On &quot;Tributes&quot; as the name suggests it appears he is trying to pay homage to his idols. Brecker clearly makes an appearance, but there are also strong Rollins influneces, Coltrane, and countless others. However it is done via the Neset lens - it always sounds like him and never as a cheap impersonation. While on some of his earlier records he let the fire-breathing solos take over - here Neset is always serving the music and deploys wildness only when it is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this album he is supported by the Danish Radio Big Band (conducted by Miho Hazama) - this allows him to use the big band to create an expansive soundscape to support the composition. It is extremely accomplished and done masterfully throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this album is only a day old finding clips via Youtube to embed is a challenge. The album itself is composed of 2 longer multi-part compositions (which are the true highlights for me) along with 3 shorter pieces. At the start of this blog post we embedded the title track. This one is probably the most similar to previous Neset offerings, you can really hear the chamber music influences and the big band is shown off to the full extent. Marius takes a sublime soprano solo, which is adventurous but fits into the backdrop created by the big-band seamlessly. He manages to resist the urge to throw all his chops at the piece, something that a lot of younger players (and older players too) often struggle with.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XcKHp_LgWrg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The real stars of the album are the two extended pieces: &quot;Bicycle Town&quot; which is a hark back to the sound he crafted on the &quot;Pinball&quot; album of 2015. Michael Brecker being a clear influence with the choppy sound and use of ghost notes along with the use of symmetric and diminished scales throughout. The two parts of this composition is where he can really stretch his legs and play the most soaring and technically advanced solos on the entire album. Showing he still has the chops to be considered one of the best on the scene. &quot;Children's Day&quot; is the other multi-part composition which (after a slow build) descends into a calypso and cuban feel, very reminiscent of &quot;St Thomas&quot; by Sonny Rollins. However this is combined with a complicated harmonic and rhythmic landscape and more &quot;Neset-isms&quot;. It is perhaps the most adventurous on the album and probably my favourite piece as a result. The longer the piece goes on the more the main melody gets distorted and the composition takes on a life of its own before coming back round at the end for a final big crescendo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I am very impressed with this album and I'm sure this is going to be one I listen to regularly in the next few weeks/months. After a couple of listens I don't like to make grandiose statements but I feel this has potential to be up there with the best albums released in the last few years. Hopefully this marks a new era for Neset and he can live up to his potential. If you get a chance I strongly suggest you pick up a copy of this album through whatever means you use to purchase your music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/023-Tributes/Tributes.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/023-Tributes/Tributes.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Way Out West and Bale Mountain</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/way-out-west-bale-mountain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Way Out West and Bale Mountain" /><published>2020-09-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Way-Out-West-Bale-Mountain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/way-out-west-bale-mountain">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-09-19-Way-Out-West-Bale-Mountain.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C6Oma0WOALU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

After a brief hiatus JazzCoffeeStuff is back! We are once again looking at a coffee from the fine folks at PLOT roasting - who are fast becoming a regular fixture on this blog. Like the preceeding two posts we have yet another coffee from the Israel Degfa company, again from Ethiopia - this time West Arsi Zone, Oromia - and another natural process. This one is called &quot;Bale Mountain&quot;. This is a single farm coffee - that is every coffee bean here is from the Bale Mountain farm. This is fairly rare for Eithiopian coffees where it is common for a single washing station to process coffees from multiple individual farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have mentioned Israel and his company a few times in the past weeks, it is about time we talk about this a little more. From what we have seen so far Israel owns many farms and washing stations in the area. You may have come to the conclusion that this is somehow &quot;big business&quot; and somehow exploitative. This is not the case, specialty coffee allows farmers to get more for their crops than they would via other avenues (I'm not saying specialty is the perfect system by any means, but compared to the alternatives it is better!) Israel and company also works directly with the local communities, offers finance to farmers to help them get started and also provides education and even builds schools in the local areas. While not a &quot;pure&quot; charity it does appear Israel does good for the people of Ethiopia and should be commended for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the coffee itself - this is a bit of a memory test for me since I no longer have this coffee in front of me. Usually I write these pieces while drinking the coffee itself but recently life has got in the way of the blog and so this comes a bit late - but this coffee was so special I had to give it some kudos. The dry aroma on the nose I get a lot of floral notes but also a good whack of really sweet fruitiness. The aroma is quite powerful so suggests we could be in for a flavour-bomb of a coffee. As usual diving into the filter, the first thing I notice is that it is not nearly as punchy as the dry aroma suggested. It is a refined and elegant cup, it's not a super funky boozy natural like you sometimes find with Ethiopians. The major flavour note for me is strawberry - PLOT decided to use a &quot;red&quot; colour scheme for the label of this one and it is clear to see why. There are other fruity notes too but strawberry is by far the most prominent. It is very very sweet, if you like sugary sweet coffees this one is for you! The label says &quot;honey&quot; as a flavour note but for me it is more of a cotton candy sweetness - I associate honey with the texture as much as the flavour and there is little in the way of syrupy mouthfeel on show here. In addition to this there is a perfumed floral note, particularly in the aftertaste, it is really quite noticable and makes the cup super interesting. The balance between fruit and floral changes significantly with temperature and you can spend ages trying to unpick the flavours if that is your thing. Equally it is not so complex that it is distracting either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the espresso. It was fairly obvious where this one would like to be dialed in to, if you've read my advice on filter roasts used as espresso before you can guess what I'll suggest: pull long, pull fast, pull hot! This one didn't need to go super long into lungo territory but it was on the long side. The flavour profile was similar to the filter; strawberry at the front, floral at the back. Again it's super sweet and it is not too acidic. It has a sort of mellowness in the espresso, it's elegant and refined. This is what I really enjoy in (good) Ethiopian espressos. Overall  was very sad to see the back of this coffee. I guess you would expect a comparison to the previous Israel Degfa from PLOT (the Gelana gesha) - it's very hard to pick a favourite. They were both fantastic and really quite different prospects - if I had to choose I'd give the gesha the edge but you cannot go wrong with either and they're both worth buying if they're available as you read this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the jazz this week. When JazzCoffeeStuff was on hiatus the jazz world was celebrating one of its greatest contributors: Sonny Rollins who turned 90 years old on September 7th. To celebrate this milestone this week we are looking at one of my favourite albums of all time: &quot;Way Out West&quot; released in 1957 on Contempary Records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/022-Way-Out-West/Way-Out-West.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage nothing needs to be said about Rollins and his legacy, I don't believe anybody would consider him anything other than an &quot;all time great&quot;. His reputation far exceeds that of jazz, he's known as a commentator (very recently penning an interesting article in the NY Times about current global events and whether that leads to personal change) as well as a cultural icon - you have to have a certain level of recognition to be a major character in an episode of The Simpsons (and lets be honest: Bleeding Gums Murphy is himself a not so subtle homage to Rollins). With a recording and touring career spanning 65+ years he has played with just about every major artist in the post-bop era (and many from the be-bop era too) as well as having a string of albums under his own name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album we're looking at here is &quot;Way Out West&quot; - one I always find myself coming back to.  It is a bit of an oddball in the Rollins back catalogue, he explores americana, country and western swing through the lens of be-bop. This gives the album its own personality which I like! It's a shame Sonny didn't revisit these ideas often but I guess any attempts to do this might feel a little forced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album cover is one of my favourite album covers of all time. Sonny fully leans into the &quot;cowboy&quot; theme with gun holsters and a cowboy hat. The humour is something that is found throughout the album, the music is of course serious in terms of composition and harmony but it does not mean you can't have fun with it. Jazz has the impression of being &quot;serious&quot; so it is nice to listen to these &quot;lighter&quot; records on occassion. &quot;Way Out West&quot; does have provenance too however, it is the first album to feature a trio of the form: sax-bass-drums. This is now ubiquitous, it's hard to picture a time when this would have been considered ground-breaking. By forgoing an &quot;accompanying&quot; harmonic instrument such as piano or drums a lot of space is opened up in mix which allows Sonny to improvise much more freely - which for an improviser as prolific as Rollins is certainly a good thing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album opens up with the track &quot;I'm An Old Cowhand&quot; (embedded at the start of this blog) which was originally penned by Johnny Mercer in 1936. While the woodblock &quot;horse&quot; sounds are a little cheesy the track itself is masterfully done. Rollins takes the main melody of the tune and looks at it through the lens of be-bop - the accents and timing are essentially textbook Charlie Parker. However he resists the temptation to up the tempo (as many would have) - this combined with the sparse arrangement of having only bass and drums in the rhythm section means Sonny can have complete freedom over the tune: he can lean into the groove at points but then breathe fire on a solo for effect. By all accounts this should just be a silly, gimmicky sort of tune to fill up space on an album - but the magic of Sonny is he can elevate this into something magical. For contrast you can see the original performance of &quot;I'm An Old Cowhand&quot; from 1936 in the film &quot;Rhythm on the Range&quot; (with Bing Crosby singing). It's a long way away from Sonny's interpretation!

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jo-pApe1Kd0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

While the western vibe is prominent on 3 of the 5 album tracks (the track above, another western standard &quot;Wagon Wheels&quot; and the Rollins penned &quot;Way Out West&quot;) - this is balanced with some simply sublime ballad playing. I've said it in this blog before: I consider being able to play ballads a real test of an improvisers skill. The second track on this album is a beautiful interpretation of Duke Ellington's 1934 &quot;(In My) Solitude&quot;. This has been recorded multiple times over the years by a range of artists - but the version on &quot;Way Out West&quot; is the definitive version for me, the version I think of whenever anybody mentions the tune. Sonny manages to perfectly capture the haunting beauty in the piece while somehow providing just a glimmer of hope. It is an absolute masterclass in improvising over a ballad, and for me personally some of Sonny's best playing.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_D3zqnokaVI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

So far we have (rightly) been focussed on the man himself, but it is time to recognise the bass playing and &quot;give the drummer some&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bass we have Ray Brown - who is a legend in his own right. Having recorded with artists through the late big-band era, through be-bop then post-bop and beyond. He is perhaps best known for his work with Oscar Peterson and Ella Fitzgerald who he recorded with on multiple albums. He also has countless recordings as a leader/co-leader. Without a harmony instrument in the line-up the role of the bass player becomes crucial, often in larger ensembles the bass player has the function of keeping things grounded. In a small trio format like this that changes to driving the tune forward (which may otherwise fall to a piano player) - this was the first time anybody played in this way on record. Ray does it masterfully, I find his playing on Solitude in particular superb but he is consistently brilliant on every track. It would be very easy for this trio format to fall down by a bass player being too sparse, fortunately this is not the case here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drummer on this album is Shelly Manne - again somebody who can be considered a legend in their own right. Manne is most associated with the west coast jazz scene. In the US during the 40s-60s (roughly) there was east and west coast schools of jazz (perhaps a pre-cursor to east and west coast rap?) The west coast typically focussed on the &quot;cool jazz&quot; sound, relaxed and laid back. But also the west gave rise to some of the more avant-garde artists too - Shelly played with both the cool and avant extensively. Aside from his own work he is probably remembered most for his work with Chet Baker. On &quot;Way Out West&quot; in addition to the &quot;horse sounds&quot; with the wood block he also unleashes pure swing. In this small trio format the bass player has to &quot;cover&quot; for the harmony instruments and so the swing is largely driven by the drummer - there are few as well equipped for this role than Shelly.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9XvpsxQAZjo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The fearlessness of Sonny Rollins as a leader cannot be overstated here. Not only did he invent this new trio format (which has since been copied by pretty much every major sax player since at some point in their career) - he did so with 2 musicians in Brown and Manne who he hadn't worked with before. I think this adds to the spontaneous and playful atmosphere throughout the album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish I'll leave you with another country tune: &quot;Wagon Wheels&quot; - another examination of a piece of americana through the lens of be-bop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Way Out West&quot; is one of my favourite albums of all time, so I strongly suggest you pick up a copy via whichever medium you use to purchase your music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/022-Way-Out-West/Way-Out-West.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/022-Way-Out-West/Way-Out-West.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Riverside and Saint Semeon Abay</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/riverside-semeon-abay" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Riverside and Saint Semeon Abay" /><published>2020-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Riverside-Semeon-Abay</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/riverside-semeon-abay">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-09-05-Riverside-Semeon-Abay.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BDpJyUznSSY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are featuring a new (for the blog) roaster: Saint Coffee Roasters. Their roastery is located in Hackney, London and they have a number of cafes across the capital including Baker Street, Angel and Camden. I decided to give them a try based on this coffee in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question is an Ethiopian coffee from the Israel Degfa company (as our previous one was also). From the Adola washing station from the Aferara region of the Guji zone. It has been designated an &quot;experimental natural&quot; process - also known as a &quot;bag process&quot; whereby the coffee cherries are left to ferment in a polypropylene bag (rotating every 12 hours). This (reportedly) leads to increased development of intense fruity flavours. This particular example has an SCA score of 90.25 - regular readers at this point will know an SCA score is not the be all and end all but a score above 90 places the coffee in the top 1% of coffee globally. High praise indeed! Given this the price of the bag was fairly reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ordering this coffee there was a bit of a royal mail mishap and my original package got so wet that the address label rubbed off and sent back to Saint (it begs the question what on earth royal mail were doing with it!) Saint were quick to correct this and sent an additional bag of coffee by way of an apology - this is certainly a good way to resolve the issue from my side so I'm giving them a shout out here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly onto the coffee itself: the dry aroma gives a very big hit of chocolate/cocoa, that is the overiding note with some lighter fruitynotes hidden in the background. This coffee is roasted marginally darker than some of the roasters commonly featured in this blog, it is by no means &quot;medium&quot; but it is certianly &quot;omni&quot; as opposed to the &quot;filter&quot; styles usually featured, this will likely bring out these cocoa notes a bit more. As usual we start with a filter; as the dry aroma suggested the cocoa is a big part of this coffee and there is a big body and mouthfeel to go with it. There are the usual &quot;natural&quot; tropical fruit or bubblegum notes present but they're not as funky and as in your face as you might expect. Actually I find myself using &quot;black forest gateau&quot; as the most predominent descriptor here. As the cup cools the fruity notes come more to the front and the cocoa subsides. Overall it is fairly complex and there's a lot to pick apart here, for a natural it is also very clean tasting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the espresso, here I toyed around with shorter shots trying to make the most of the cocoa notes and body but it fell a bit flat for me, the complexity was lost. In the end I settled on pulling a little longer around 1:2.75 - at a medium heat with a decent preinfusion. This sacrificed a little in mouthfeel and body but more than made up for it in sweetness. As a coffee I found it very easy to dial in and was very forgiving. It seemed to be quite insensitive to grind size change, I had to move my settings quite a lot to notice a difference with this coffee. In the cup the tropical fruits came out a little bit more, however it is not a &quot;loud&quot; coffee and don't go expecting real deep funky notes. The &quot;black forest&quot; vibe is certainly still there and still the first thing I notice when tasting. Again it is a clean coffee and the aftertaste does not linger too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a complex and interesting coffee and one I'm glad I picked up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we are heading back to 2014 through the &quot;Riverside&quot; album from Dave Douglas and Chet Doxas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/021-Riverside/Riverside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project Douglas and Doxas pay tribute to Jimmy Giuffre. However unlike many other &quot;tribute&quot; albums this album is not just a rehash of Giuffre's tunes: instead all but 2 tracks are originals. There is only one Giuffre composition (&quot;The Train and the River&quot;) and one Johnny Mercer standard (&quot;Travelin' Light&quot;) which was a favourite of Giuffre. While the back catalogue of Jimmy Giuffre is fairly broad (from big band, through cool and even free-jazz) - on &quot;Riverside&quot; they pay homage to the blues-folk influenced stylings, but in a more &quot;modern&quot; style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The line up on the album is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dave Douglas - trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chet Doxas - clarinet, saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steve Swallow - electric bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jim Doxas - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dave Douglas is a fairly &quot;big&quot; name in modern jazz. His back catalogue is extensive covering just about every jazz sub-genre you can think of and has worked with many other artists both old and new: from John Zorn, Bill Frisell, Lee Konitz, Joe Lovano, Horace Silver and many others. He also has a background as an educator working with various universities and music institutions and also has his own record label &quot;Greenleaf Music&quot; (on which &quot;Riverside&quot; is released) which is one of my favourite current jazz labels. It is hard to summarize the Douglas &quot;sound&quot; or &quot;style&quot; in a way that does him justice given the breadth of his experience - however he typically focuses on a powerful big sound and often plays with a great deal of swagger. If you ever get a chance to see him perform live (regardless of the project) you should jump at it, he always puts on a show and is one of the most consistent out there. I try and catch him when he comes to town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Riverside&quot; appears under both Douglas and Doxas names - I have to be honest I know very little about Chet Doxas (and his brother Jim on drums). He has a relatively small back catalogue - but I've enjoyed everything I've heard to date. It may be a case that &quot;less is more&quot;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Swallow is the &quot;veteran&quot; of this line up; having worked from 1960 onwards. In fact he previously worked with Jimmy Giuffre fairly extensively which gives this album an air of authenticity. He is also known for working with Paul Bley, John Scofield, Steve Kuhn, Carla Bley and Gary Burton (among others) and has a sizeable career as a leader. He was one of the first jazz bassists to move to electric bass exclusively - and one of only a select few who plays a 5 string bass. He has a style that I would describe as intricate but relaxed, often opting to play chords when comping and playing in the very high register when soloing. He genuinely plays softly with contemplation rather than opting for big powerful bass lines. It is a sound all to himself and is instantly recognisable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &quot;Riverside&quot; the writing duties are split roughly 50:50 between Douglas and Doxas and the album has essentially 2 speeds: an upbeat chaotic swing of Douglas and the slower more meditative approach of Doxas. &quot;Handwritten Letter&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) is a prime example of the Douglas approach. The main melody is an uptempo high energy affair but there are many twists and turns as the tune progresses. The rhythmic interplay is a key feature of the album and brings a playful feel to proceedings.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3Mjkn0OX8N4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The tune &quot;Old Church, New Paint&quot; shows off the groups softer side with a down-tempo comtemplative ballad with a nod towards gospel. Doxas plays with a beautiful breath-y tone, meanwhile Douglas playing some great counter-point. The use of counter-point melody is something that appears frequently throughout the record. The rhythm section of Doxas and Swallow keeps the whole tune swinging with a blues tilt. There is a lead-in track to this piece that features a beautiful solo from Steve Swallow and gives him a chance to flex some of his chops, something that does not appear too often on this album with Douglas and Doxas taking most of the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall it is a fantastic album, slightly overlooked at the time so well deserving of a second listen. This is the sort of album that can satisfy in a number of ways: it is quite &quot;easy&quot; to listen to as it is focussed on blues-folk yet behind this there are some really interesting rhythmic and counter-point ideas should you want to investigate further. There has since been a second album for the Riverside project called &quot;The New National Anthem&quot; where they look at the work of Carla Bley - also worthy of your time.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BUolZzqECyQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/021-Riverside/Riverside.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/021-Riverside/Riverside.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Real McCoy and PLOT Gelana Gesha</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/the-real-mccoy-gelana" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Real McCoy and PLOT Gelana Gesha" /><published>2020-08-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/The-Real-McCoy-Gelana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/the-real-mccoy-gelana">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-08-29-The-Real-McCoy-Gelana.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/73VczRfu9Kg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Welcome to the 20th JazzCoffeeStuff post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week we are back to PLOT coffee roasting again. If you have read the previous blog posts you'll notice that (at the moment) there is little variation in roasters appearing on this page: this is intentional given the global situation. I recommend everybody support the businesses they like as it is a tough time for coffee roasters. As such I'm doing less &quot;exploring&quot; and am spending more of my coffee money on the usual suspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto more positive notes: this week the coffee we're looking at is kind of interesting. It is a coffee from Ethiopia and from the Israel Degfa empire. I (partly) joke about calling it an empire, Israel owns a company Kerchanshe Trading who own a number of washing stations and mills throughout Ethiopia. If you are looking at high quality coffee from this region it won't take you long to come across the Israel Degfa name. Over the past few years he has been working tirelessly to improve the quality of coffee being produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this instance the coffee we're looking at today is a natural process from the Gelana woreda in the (west) Guji zone of the Oromia Region. Guji is highly synonymous with high quality coffee and has featured on this blog in the past. Gelana is a small area that benefits from decent rainfall and fertile soil which is a good starting point for growing high quality coffee plants. Israel decided that this particular farm was a prime location to experiment and decided to plant a large number of Gesha plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have talked about varietals in the past, but I believe this is the first Gesha we have featured on the blog. Gesha first came onto the scene around 2004 through the prized Panama farm Hacienda La Esmeralda. On the cupping table it produced such vibrant floral notes that many thought somebody had &quot;smuggled&quot; some Ethiopian coffee onto the table and it couldn't possibly be produced in Panama. This sparked an obssession with the varietal and quickly Gesha lots became the hottest lots in auctions reaching crazy price levels. Through the end of the 2000s and 2010s barista competitions essentially became &quot;Gesha  shows&quot; - if you wanted to place you needed to have a special Gesha coffee to show off! But what is so special about Gesha itself? It originally hails from Ethiopia, first identified in the 1930s, samples got sent to Costa Rica in the 1950s and Panama planted samples as early as 1960s. The Gesha varietal is synonymous with &quot;floral&quot; notes particularly jasmine and bergamot and is almost always fruit focussed. They tend to be very perfumed with a big bouquet, as a result they regularly score in the 90s for SCA cup scores (remember 80 is the cutoff for specialty, getting into the 90s is incredibly rare &amp;lt;1% of coffee produced each year globally gets into this bracket - essentially the best of the best).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is particularly interesting about this coffee from PLOT is the price; for a Gesha it is simply outstanding value - it is the same price as their &quot;regular&quot; coffees. I'm not sure I've ever found a Gesha at this price point before so I was very eager to try it. Although I admit I was a little skeptical, like if you find a Ferarri in the autotrader for £1000. But given the last few coffees from PLOT I considered this a &quot;risk&quot; worth taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a dry aroma from the ground beans the fragrance is a little subdued, this is something I regularly notice about Gesha coffees - they tend to be quite &quot;polite&quot; and never punch you in the face. There is certainly a peach note and also, as expected, the jasmine floral note. Another thing I instantly notice: this coffee is a very light roast, this is certainly one you could consider the mythical &quot;nordic roast&quot; style. Onto the filter, as usual a chemex filter type, the resulting coffee is clean as they come, there isn't a hint of &quot;funk&quot; from the natural processing. I would describe the flavour profile as relatively subtle but certainly complex. The main overiding flavour note for me is peach, it is like biting into a ripe juicy peach. As the cup cools the florals come out to play and it takes on an elderflower cordial sort of vibe - the sweetness of this coffee taking on that sticky almost jammy quality. What I found most astounding however was the aftertaste: out of nowhere a ripe banana note comes out. It is only evident in the aftertaste and there is no hint of it before, it is really suprising but unmistakable for me. This is a note that PLOT did not list on the bag but for me it's one of the major characters of the coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso, a coffee roast this light can be a nightmare to dial in and you're left with a &quot;sweetspot&quot; living on a knife-edge with even the slightest change in puck-prep throwing the whole shot off. Fortunately this one was surprisingly easy to dial in on my setup, I didn't have any issues at all. In the end I settled for a 1:2.75 ratio out in 24s with my machine on maximum temperature. As with the filter the major flavour note for me was peach, the shot was super sweet with just enough acidity not to be cloying. Again it was a super clean flavour profile and there was little in the way of body or mouthfeel. Again the ripe banana note came out during the aftertaste but was slightly less pronounced in the espresso, the aftertaste of the filter lingered whereas the aftertaste of the espresso was fairly shortlived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this was a very interesting and delicious coffee. On the face of it a very simple delicate flavour profile but there was enough complexity there to keep you entertained too. It is certainly worth trying if it is still available as you read this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we are heading back to 1960s Blue Note with a hard-bop classic from McCoy Tyner: &quot;The Real McCoy&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/020-The-Real-McCoy/The-Real-McCoy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McCoy Tyner is probably best known for being the pianist in the John Coltrane band - where he featured on many seminal albums such as &quot;My Favourite Things&quot;, &quot;Africa/Brass&quot; and &quot;Love Supreme&quot;, all of which are worthy of a blog post to themselves. He also had many other dates as a sideman for the likes of Wayne Shorter, Lee Morgan, Hank Mobley, Freddie Hubbard and Joe Henderson along with many others. Today however we are focussed on his solo career which was equally prolific. &quot;The Real McCoy&quot; was released in 1967, some 2 years after he left the John Coltrane band. It was during this time he began to find his own voice as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is safe to say McCoy is certainly in the &quot;modal&quot; school of post-bop jazz - for those who do not know music theory: a mode is essentially a degree of a scale, for example taking the major scale (&quot;do, ri, me, ...&quot;) there are seven associated &quot;modes&quot; of this scale depending on which note is the root (&quot;home&quot; note). Each mode has its own flavour/mood, in a modal composition we take a specific mode and build the entire tune around that, this gives pieces a specific &quot;mood&quot; or &quot;feeling&quot;. This is in contrast to, say, be-bop where the focus is on chord changes and the melody follows the structure of the chord and so a composition may feature many different scales in passing. Modal jazz became very popular with post-bop artists and even many modern records still use a modal concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another factor of McCoy's playing is his powerful left hand playing, he often relies on big choppy chords to drive the pieces forward. This often brings an authoritative punch to the compositions and drives the music forward. There is a certain &quot;stride&quot; influence to this but it is certainly his own sound and it is unmistakable, you can often hear other players doing a &quot;McCoy impression&quot; but never quite getting it right. Of course another big part of his playing is his reliance on fourth intervals that appear throughout his work, many of his chord voicings are based around the idea of stacking fourths - he even has an album named &quot;Reaching Fourth&quot; so they clearly meant a lot to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at the rest of the line up on this album now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McCoy Tyner - piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Henderson - tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ron Carter - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elvin Jones - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the majority of albums featured on this blog: this line up is stellar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have read any of the previous blog posts you'll know about Joe Henderson at this point, one of my favourite artists of all time. As you'd expect Joe's improvisation is top notch playing some really intricate and interesting lines, he doesn't get quite as &quot;free&quot; as he does on his own albums (understandably) but he matches perfectly the energy of Tyner throughout. Joe is one of those players who is equally talented as a sideman (by not taking the spotlight away from the named artist) and leading a band himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then on the bass there is Ron Carter, again a legend who has appeared on this blog on numerous posts (although not yet as a solo artist). The magic in Carter's playing for me is his ability to accompany other players, it is an often underappreciated skill. The best accompanists have a quality that I like to describe as &quot;holding up a mirror&quot; where they manage to allow the soloing musician to sound &quot;even more like themselves&quot; - Ron has this ability in abundance. This is certainly on display in this album where you have McCoy's compositions being fairly harmonically dense and frantic solos from McCoy and Joe - if Ron came to the session with ego and not willing to allow the others to speak it could quickly turn into a car crash. The other aspect of Carter's playing that is so impressive to me is his command of rhythm, he can really find the pocket when things get complicated. He is certianly deserving of his reputation as one of the finest bass players in jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly we have drummer Elvin Jones. Without doubt one of my absolute favourite drummers of all time. Like McCoy, Elvin spent much of his early career playing as a sideman with some of the great artists: in the 1950s with Miles Davis and Sonny Rollins (appearing on the &quot;A Night at the Village Vanguard&quot; - an all time classic) and the 1960s appearing in the John Coltrane band alongside McCoy. Again the list of artists and albums he has worked with and on is basically a &quot;who's who&quot; of jazz. His playing style is very fluid, playing legato like phrases on the drums. This gives him a rubbery slippery sound that influenced jazz (and other genres) for decades afterwards and still to this day. He manages to maintain this quality while playing sophisticated polyrhymic ideas, which is not easy to do. With complex ideas like this it is very easy for the drumming to begin to sound &quot;robotic&quot; but Elvin keeps things swinging. However Elvin also had the ability to play thunderous and powerful lines when required, he was far from a &quot;one trick pony&quot;. Without a doubt one of the best drummers of all time, not just in the jazz world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album starts with &quot;Passion Dance&quot; (embedded at the start of this blog) which is the opening track and one of the album's highlights. It is a fairly dense piece with a complicated melody, however it is essentially a blueprint on band interaction and connection. Each player is solely concerned with lifting the music and not themselves. This is perhaps most evident with the rhythmic interplay between McCoy and Elvin. Joe takes a blistering solo too, tap-dancing through the chaos to play something beautiful. This focus on connection is evident throughout the album, while some of the other compositions may be less manic there is always a sense of cohesion and togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another tune that sticks out for me on this album is the closing track: &quot;Blues on The Corner&quot;

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/64lWx44RjdU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As the name suggests this is a take on the blues, however as you'd expect it is a little more sophisticated than that. While Elvin showed off his power in &quot;Passion Dance&quot; here he shows just how hard he can swing on a blues. Ron is playing with complete attitude too which gives McCoy the freedom to explore harmonically while keeping things grounded. Joe also takes the opportunity to play with his characteristic wolf notes and &quot;outside&quot; playing, it is perhaps one of the best solos he's taken and with his repertoire that is really saying something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the 2 tunes outlined here are fairly up-tempo and wild, this album also features 2 beautiful ballads. I find the modal paradigm really lends itself to ballads - it is very easy to create a &quot;mood&quot; and give the piece some character. On this album we have &quot;Contemplation&quot; and &quot;Search for Peace&quot; both of which are fantastic example of hard-bop ballads. Overall you cannot go wrong with any track on this album each one is a classic. This makes, in my opinion, &quot;The Real McCoy&quot; absolutely essential listening for anybody interested in jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/020-The-Real-McCoy/The-Real-McCoy.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/020-The-Real-McCoy/The-Real-McCoy.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Burn and Assembly Izuba</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/burn-izuba" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Burn and Assembly Izuba" /><published>2020-08-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Burn-Izuba</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/burn-izuba">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-08-22-Burn-Izuba.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nRsgMMZKh8o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we have the last of my current batch of Assembly roasted coffee in the form of Izuba a washed Bourbon varietal from Burundi. To those familiar with previous blog posts may be having a sense of deja-vu at this point: Burndi as an origin has featured multiple times, many of the coffees featured are washed process and of course Assembly is a reliable blog favourite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As regular readers will know, Assembly decorate each coffee with a &quot;swirl&quot; which somewhat reflects the flavour profile of the coffee for this coffee we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/019-Burn/Izuba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This coffee gets its name from the washing station where it was processed. The Izuba washing station is located in the city of Kayanza within the Kayanza province in the north of the country, not too far from the border with Rwanda. Typically specialty coffees are named after the &quot;smallest&quot; identifiable characteristic - in this case the coffee is named after the washing station since this coffee is made up of many small lots of local farms. In contrast other coffees could be named after a particular farm (e.g. in the Americas typically you'll see &quot;Finca ....&quot; - the Spanish for farm). In very high end coffees you might see a farm name followed by a lot number (or farm name followed by a varietal) which denotes a specific part of a specific farm. In cheaper coffees you might only see a region name (e.g. Ethiopia Sidamo) since there is no addtional provenance available. In (typically non specialty grade) you'll simply get a country name or sometimes not even that! But there is a slight caveat here: some roasters like to name their coffees, essentially as a form of branding, that have nothing to do with the farm/coffee itself. However you can usually find out the details by going onto the roasters website or provided literature with the coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big part of the specialty coffee movement is transparanency so generally the more detailed the better! However this has essentially nothing to do with quality in the cup, you might find a coffee from a very precise lot of a farm and have all the information in the world but still not particularly enjoy the taste. As always these &quot;sign posts&quot; should help you get a feel for whether a roaster is offering quality specialty grade or whether they care about their product, but not much more than that. At the end of the day it's your taste preferences that matter, there are plenty of objectively high quality roasters who just don't do it for me (and as a result will not feature on this blog!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough blabbering on; onto the coffee itself. Upon grinding the dry aroma of this coffee gives off a fruity vibe as you often expect from washed African coffees. Likely owing to its location it certainly shares a similarity to a Rwandan coffee in terms of aroma. I would describe the fruit note as being quite heavy with a dark grape or plum. There is also a faint caramel/fudge note but it doesn't immediately jump out. Overall it is not an aroma monster but is very pleasant, refined and elegant. As usual diving into a filter coffee (prepared in my usual way). First thing I notice is red wine, I almost always get this note with Burundi coffees it seems. On the taste notes assembly say &quot;Pomegranate&quot; which I think is the same note, but for me it is more wine-y owing to the heavy nature of this coffee and I did not have the refreshing &quot;zing&quot; I associate with a pomegranate. It is like a full bodied oaky red, very satisfying. There are complexities there too however, there is certainly some faint florals that jump in and out as the cup cools. A little hard to put your finger on exactly what type of floral but it's certainly there. The sweetness comes through in the form of fudge, I think owing to the texture too. For a washed coffee it is a &quot;big&quot; feeling coffee, not necessarily in terms of mouthfeel but certainly in body - it tastes huge. On the acidity scale I would say this is a medium (at least for a washed African coffee) there's certainly some there but it's not a &quot;screw your face up - battery acid&quot; coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso: this coffee was an absolute delight to dial in. I found it unbelievably forgiving, it was basically impossible to pull anything less than great on my set up. I eventually settled on a very &quot;typical&quot; 1:2 ratio in around 27s - for a filter roasted washed African this is not typical. I found that pulling like this maintained the &quot;huge&quot; feeling and gave enough mouthfeel to be really enjoyable. Pulling longer was still good but I lost a bit of texture and the espresso was already sweet enough in the shorter pull so it didn't offer much improvement there. In the cup I found that the fudge/toffee notes jumped out a bit more but the red wine was still the main note for me. The subtle florals I picked out in the filter were totally overpowered in the espresso and I couldn't find them at all. I did notice more of a stone fruit vibe in the espresso: most likely a plum flavour. But again this was subtle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I think I prefered this coffee as an espresso to a filter, both were great but I enjoyed the amped up mouthfeel of the espresso given the heavy flavour profile. This is a coffee that can work as both an &quot;every day&quot; drinker and a &quot;special treat&quot; when you want to savour the tastes and really dig into a flavour profile. As with pretty much every Assembly roast: another standout coffee. I'm sure it won't be too long before I order another batch from Assembly they're just so reliable and seem to pick coffees that just work for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this weeks jazz I'm picking an album from 2013. The band is the Mercury prize nominated, Mobo award winning - British jazz quartet: &quot;Sons of Kemet&quot; - with their debut album &quot;Burn&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/019-Burn/Burn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album comes completely from left-field and is certainly unique. You could describe this as being part of the &quot;hipster jazz&quot; movement which I feel is a little unfair, while the sound may attract the hipster crowd it has more depth and creativity than others tarred with this brush. It should appeal to &quot;serious&quot; jazz fans too. Let's start with the personnel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shabaka Hutchings - Sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oren Marshall - Tuba&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tom Skinner - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seb Rochford - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(There is also a small electric guitar cameo on 2 of the tracks but the band itself is composed of these 4 members).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a truly bizarre lineup for a band, there are no &quot;harmony&quot; instruments so of course the focus will be on melodic and rhythmic ideas opposed to harmonic ones. The tuba takes the role of &quot;bass&quot; which is kind of an interesting sound in itself as it is not something you see often, especially in small band. Then of course the dual drums, reading this you may think that the drumming duties are split with Tom appearing on some tracks and Seb on others - but you would be wrong: the Sons of Kemet sound depends on 2 drummers working together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The band leader is Shabaka Hutchings. He leads a number of other projects and has also frequently appeared as a sideman. Shabaka does not just follow the &quot;traditional&quot; jazz sound and takes great influence from electronic and hip-hop styles. His projects often feel just as home in a nightclub as they do a jazz club. &quot;Sons of Kemet&quot; is no exception. &quot;Burn&quot; has two main modes: the first I would describe as &quot;post-apocolyptic rave music&quot; and the second as &quot;spiritual contemplation&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track &quot;Inner Babylon&quot; (embedded at the start of this blog post) is an example of the &quot;post-apocolyptic rave&quot; sound. To me it always brings images of a party in a burnt out city. I had the fortune of seeing this band play live numerous times after this album was released and there was certainly a party atmosphere - it was a unique experience for a jazz gig. I remember one in particular at the Barbican concert hall where they were supporting &quot;Mehliana&quot; (the Brad Mehldau - Mark Guiliana fusion collaboration project). &quot;Sons of Kemet&quot; totally blew the crowd away, to the point that &quot;Mehliana&quot; seemed totally tame and a bit boring, I remember the crowd even heckling Brad a few times during the show... Moral of the story: pick your support acts carefully and make sure they don't show you up!

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7u8eo6hMoGw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another track I am particularly fond of on the album is &quot;The Godfather&quot;. There is a Hasidic influenceon the melodies that I find intriguing juxtaposed against the trance rhythm section. I've always found the Hasidic musical traditions to be interesting and something I have to dig into further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don't often talk about record engineering or production on this blog much, owing to a complete lack of knowledge on part of the author, but it is worth mentioning here. With a small band like this with a rather limited musical range it is easy for a record to sound &quot;small&quot;. This is not the case here, the album has an absolutely huge sound! If you're not paying attention you easily forget there are only 4 musicians playing. This is not through the use of overdubs or multi-tracking, near enough the entire album is free of this and is recorded &quot;live&quot;. Instead there is the rather ingenious use of tape echo and reverb to give the illusion of a larger soundscape. This is not done in a cynical way that sounds artifical however, you don't really notice it is there. Production duties for this album fell to Seb Rochford - one of the drummers in the band and he should be commended for the work he did here. Without this I don't think the album would have half the impact it does. (Unfortunately the youtube compression does this no favours, I'd recommend getting the album from alternate sources for the best experience, it is worth it!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seb is one of my favourite &quot;modern&quot; jazz drummers, everything he touches seems to be made better by his presence. In the jazz world you may have heard him through his band &quot;Polar Bear&quot; (another Mercury prize nominee) or playing with &quot;Acoustic Ladyland&quot;, &quot;Basquiat Strings&quot; or &quot;Andy Shepherd&quot;. He typically takes a wide range of influences from rock, electronic and world music in his jazz playing which elevates the music. However he also does session work for rock/pop acts and appeared on some of the early &quot;Babyshambles&quot; records/gigs with Pete Doherty. I've met Seb a couple of times at gigs and he is also a really nice guy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the tuba side we have Oren Marshall, before &quot;Sons of Kemet&quot; I knew of him but hadn't really listened to much of him. On this album he made such an impression I looked at more of his stuff, he has a very interesting sound. If you see him perfom live you may also see him play a custom made &quot;Orenophone&quot; a modified tuba of his own design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/019-Burn/Oren.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the release of this album Seb and Oren subsequently left the band, personally I feel a lot of the magic went with them and to be honest I've not really enjoyed their subsequent releases. But this does not take away from &quot;Burn&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish I'll share one more tune off the album: a cover of Boney-M: &quot;Rivers of Babylon&quot;. It is unlikely you've ever heard this track covered in this way. While Boney-M's version is rather cheesy and dated by todays standards; this version is full of spirituality and contemplation. I feel this forms a deeper connection with the intended meaning behind the song. It is a really fantastic track and a nice contrast to some of the more energetic cuts on the album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MoTkcYXWAJM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/019-Burn/Burn.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/019-Burn/Burn.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Go Go and Assembly Monteverde</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/a-go-go-monteverde" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Go Go and Assembly Monteverde" /><published>2020-08-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/A-Go-Go-Monteverde</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/a-go-go-monteverde">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-08-15-A-Go-Go-Monteverde.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1WPGdjZr8PI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with Assembly coffee roasters in Brixton, London. This time we move away from Africa through to South America and Colombia to be exact. The coffee is called &quot;Monteverde&quot; which is the name of the farm located in the Andean region in the Tolima department - in the centre west of the county and just west of Bogota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As regular readers will know, Assembly decorate each coffee with a &quot;swirl&quot; which somewhat reflects the flavour profile of the coffee for this coffee we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/018-A-Go-Go/Monteverde.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most &quot;interesting&quot; part of this coffee is its processing method, described by Assembly as &quot;anaerobic&quot;. The coffee undergoes a 2 stage fermentation anaerobic fermentation process where the temperature is carefully controlled between 19 and 23 celcius. The second stage is a 48 hour aerobic temperature and pH controlled fermentation. Reported to be a similar technique to Yemeni producers. I have seen these sorts of process also called &quot;semi-anaerobic&quot; and other names. This is what I would consider an &quot;experimental&quot; processing method compared to the more typical washed/natural/honey type processes we are more accustomed to. Personally I find these methods hit and miss, some of them can be great and produce interesting and complex cups but many leave me feeling cold, I find them a bit &quot;hollow&quot; (for lack of a better word) in an almost &quot;decaf&quot; sort of way. They can be intense flavour wise but unbalanced and for me not that enjoyable. As such I don't hunt out these sort of coffees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of varietal this coffee is a Caturra. This varietal is very prevelant around the Americas and represents a natural mutation of the Bourbon varietal. It is known for fairly good cup quality and yield but is considered susceptible to both leaf rust and pests. It is also a parent varietal to many hybrid or mutated varietals such as Catimor (cross with a Timor), Castillo, and others which typically offer better resistance to leaf rust and pests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the coffee itself. The first thing I notice is the beans have a slighlty &quot;oily&quot; look to them - not in an &quot;italian roast&quot; sort of way (these beans are definitely a light roast). It is slighlty strange and not something I really see in the sort of beans I buy, I wonder if it's a result of the particular processing? As a dry aroma we are treated to tropical fruits galore with this one - its a fruit salad in coffee form. Papaya, pineapple, mango, passion fruit - everything is there and it is a very intense experience. I found these beans a little odd as a grinding experience too, in my hand grinder for filter they almost had a &quot;spongy&quot; character. In the past I have experimented with microwaving beans prior to grinding and they have a similar texture. Very strange indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter the tropical fruits really carry though and it is just a fruit bomb. There is no other way to describe this coffee, big, punchy, bright but funky too. The acidity is fairly high in this one but there is a lot of sweetness too which acts to offset this. It also has a reasonably big mouthfeel and is almost syrupy. This is a very complex cup and one could spend a while trying to unpick everything in the cup. I did find it had a pretty &quot;linear&quot; heat profile though, in as much as the flavours do not evolve as the cup cools (at least very much). It does not have the &quot;hollow&quot; quality I sometimes associate with the experimental processing methods which is definitely a positive. Overall it is not the cleanest cup I've ever had but for a cup with funk it is fairly clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso. The weird grinding continued for me here, I found this one a strange coffee to work with. I found you wouldn't get many fines at all until you hit a specific grind setting and then it produced an absolute boat ton of fines. This led to me adopting a very strange recipe for this coffee: 16.5g in to 50g out with the shot pulling in 14s. By most standards this would be considered a &quot;gusher&quot; and a failed shot, if I saw a cafe pulling a shot like this I would likely walk away thinking they don't know what they're doing. But for me this just works with this coffee, going to a more &quot;traditional&quot; shot profile led to a slight acrid aftertaste note that I did not care for. One might expect a shot pulled like this to be extremely sour but this was not the case and the sweetness meant it was fairly balanced. At around a 1:3 ratio one might expect to have a very watery thin mouthfeel too, again not the case and it was quite thick and luxurious with a thick crema too. The flavour profile is similar to the filter: an absolute fruit bomb with a hint of funk. A very interesting and delcious shot of espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This weeks jazz comes courtesy of John Scofield, in the form of his 1998 album &quot;A Go Go&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/018-A-Go-Go/A-Go-Go.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album marks his first collaboration with Medeski, Martin and Wood (MMW) with whom he has recorded 4 albums - after this album they decided to record under the name: &quot;Medeski, Scofield, Martin and Wood&quot; (MSMW). The full album musician/instrument line-up is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Scofield – electric &amp;amp; acoustic guitars, whistle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Medeski – organ, Wurlitzer, clavinet, piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Wood – acoustic &amp;amp; electric basses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Billy Martin – drums, tambourine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up to this point MMW had achieved a modest cult following but it wasn't until this album that they really made it &quot;big&quot;, following on from this they released a string of fairly commercially successful records (without Scofield) mostly in the &quot;jazz-funk&quot; space. They created their own &quot;scene&quot; and attracted new listeners to jazz. However in addition to their jazz-funk side they also had their feet firmly planted in the avant-garde working with John Zorn and were also heavily linked to the &quot;jam-band&quot; scene and a certain contingent of their fans would readily describe themselves as &quot;dead heads&quot; or &quot;phish phans&quot;. In addition to recording as a trio each member has numerous side projects and collaborations in genres from more straight ahead jazz, through pop, rock and hip-hop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title artist, and sole composer, on the album is John Scofield - Sco to his friends. John needs no introduction really, since the 1970s he has toured and recorded with many of the titans of jazz: Miles Davis, Charles Mingus, Joe Henderson, Dave Liebman, Billy Cobham, Chet Baker, Paul Bley and many many more. In addition he has had a prolific career as a leader/solo artist with around 50 records to his name. If you were to ask people to list &quot;jazz guitarists&quot; it wouldn't be a long wait to hear Sco mentioned. &quot;A Go Go&quot; is likely to have a lot to do with this as commercially it is likely to be Sco's most successful release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1970s Sco was one of the first jazz players to use a distorted &quot;rock&quot; guitar sound, before this jazz guitarists had typically used large hollowbody guitars prone to feedback into clean guitar amps. As fusion came in this changed and many opted for a distorted sound - in this respect Sco was very influencial. You can argue over who the first was to do this but for me the &quot;Scofield tone&quot; is something that many tried to imitate (I find the secret being to pick very hard right next to the bridge to get his squealing cat sort of phrasing). His playing style however cannot be imitated. His style changed over the years but has always been distinctly Sco. Initially he played faster lines, but by &quot;A Go Go&quot; he slowed down significantly. His playing is all about &quot;laziness&quot; and being as far behind the beat as possible while still being in good time. The lines themselves tend to be fairly outside but the phrasing and timing presents them in a way that you sometimes don't notice. It is something that is very hard to do, I've heard many players do &quot;Scofield impressions&quot; but very few (if any) actually nail what he's doing. I once heard him described as: &quot;He knows so much music it just falls out of him&quot; - which I feel is an apt description for his playing style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On to the album itself: the album has a very strong &quot;jam-band&quot; feel from the MMW supporting cast, with more than a hint of jazz-funk throughout. As with many MMW projects the music has a &quot;get up and dance&quot; feel, even when the music itself can be fairly complex and at times intense and gnarly. Mostly though it just feels like four friends playing music together and we are just fortunate there was a tape there to capture the moment. The album kicks off with the title track &quot;A Go Go&quot; (embedded above). This track is a good signpost of what is to come on the album. It has a sort of mysterious and eerie vibe, but at the same time funky and jovial. The solos are a contrast to this where both Johns play with an attitude and swagger. There are also hints of &quot;The Meters&quot; in certain parts - an influence that seems to crop up on many tracks on the album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FHbQbIjKWro&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The fifth track on the album &quot;Jeep on 35&quot; is perhaps the most sophisticated tune on the album. I guess you'd describe it a having a &quot;fusion&quot; sound from the 1970s but that would be doing the tune a disservice. Although a &quot;jam-band&quot; feel there are many different parts and sections in the composition. Given the title and easy laid-back vibe this seems a tailor made soundtrack for a summer road trip. Sco's solo on this piece in particular is a perfect case study in his &quot;behind the beat&quot; or &quot;lazy&quot; soloing style that is so hard to imitate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another high point on the album for me is &quot;Green Tea&quot;:

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2KHeNpTzOzo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Here the tempo is brought right down from some of the higher energy funk that surround it on the album. All the music featured walks the narrow line between extremely &quot;relaxed&quot; music and extremely &quot;sophisticated&quot; - something that is very hard to do well. One of the real selling points of this album is just how strong every track is. If I were to re-write this entire post again I could choose any of the other tune to write about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you want some funky coffee then hunt down a bag of Monteverde, if you want some funky jazz hunt down a copy of &quot;A Go Go&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/018-A-Go-Go/A-Go-Go.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/018-A-Go-Go/A-Go-Go.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cornbread and Assembly Shyira</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/cornbread-shyira" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cornbread and Assembly Shyira" /><published>2020-08-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Cornbread-Shyira</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/cornbread-shyira">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-08-08-Cornbread-Shyira.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/98IWJDnmSxU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we're going to keep the blog post tight since I have been pretty busy and haven't had a lot of time to plan what I'm going to write. We are heading back to our friends at Assembly Coffee Roasters located in Brixton London. The coffee in question is called Shyira and is a red-bourbon varietal from Rwanda. Shyira is the name of the mill where the coffee is processed, it is located in the Nyabihu region of the country which shares a border with the Democratic Republic of Congo to the north.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year (May 7th 2020) Shyira and surrounding areas were subject to rather catastrophic landslides. As a result Assembly have very kindly decided to donate all profits from the sale of this coffee to the relief fund: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gofundme.com/f/Rwandan-landslide&quot;&gt;https://www.gofundme.com/f/Rwandan-landslide&lt;/a&gt; - if you would like to help feel free to donate to the page or buy a bag of the coffee at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://assemblycoffee.co.uk/collections/buy-coffee/products/rwanda-shyira&quot;&gt;https://assemblycoffee.co.uk/collections/buy-coffee/products/rwanda-shyira&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As regular readers will know, Assembly decorate each coffee with a &quot;swirl&quot; which somewhat reflects the flavour profile of the coffee for this coffee we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/017-Cornbread/shyira.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly on to the coffee itself: the dry aroma gives hints of caramel and a slight spice but the over-arching quality is vibrant and zingy with plenty of citrus fruits. From the moment you open the bag you know it's going to be in for a lot of bright acidity here. As is customary in this blog we start with a filter coffee: the flavour notes on the bag are &quot;pink grapefruit&quot;, &quot;lemonade&quot; and &quot;vibrant&quot; - and I certainly couldn't think of a better description than that, for me that is right on the money. The grapefruit is very much in your face from the getgo, the lemonade appears as a sweetness to balance but there is also an almost carbonated vibe to the coffee (not in as much as it's actually fizzy, but as a flavour as you get with carbonated water/drinks). Although acidity is the focus it is not over-bearing and is not like drinking vinegar at all, it is very well balanced. This is a truly expertly roasted coffee. In terms of mouthfeel and body it is relatively thin but not devoid of any body. The aftertaste is clean and fairly shortlived. Overall extremely enjoyable as a filter, one I very sadly miss now the bag is finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might assume with a light roast filter coffee that is very acidity focussed this would be an absolute nightmare to dial in as an espresso, I did not find this to be the case at all. It is surprisingly forgiving and I didn't have a single shot that was less than &quot;very good&quot; even when dialing in. I ultimately settled for a fairly &quot;traditional&quot; recipe of around a 2.2:1 ratio in about 27s. Usually a pull quite a bit longer than this for a lighter filter roast but with this one it could hold together at a shorter ratio and it didn't get too overbearing. It does like higher temperatures though and I was close to maxing out my machines temperature to get this shot. The flavour notes in the espresso are very much like in the filter, the grapefruit is the main quality and the lemonade is a little more subdued. The caramel, brown sugar sort of note that was picked up in the dry aroma rears its head in the espresso too, balancing the more wild grapefruit flavours. Being a relatively short shot we do get some body, but it's more silky than heavy. As before the aftertaste is relatively shortlived but is very clean and crisp. Just as with the filter this was very enjoyable and will be missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even without the donation to the landslide appeal I would say this coffee is worth tasting, given you can do some good and enjoy a great coffee I'd suggest buying a bag of this is a no-brainer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To pair with this great coffee we are going to have Cornbread. Not the southern US delicacy (although I'm sure it would go fantastically well with the coffee) but the 1967 Blue Note classic recorded by Lee Morgan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/017-Cornbread/Cornbread.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee Morgan has featured on the blog before but never as a leader. He was, and still is, one of the heavyweights of the jazz world. Many considered him to be the next &quot;flag bearer&quot; of the genre before his life was cut tragically short. Netflix (in the UK at least) currently has a brilliant documentary from 2016 called: &quot;I Called Him Morgan&quot; available, if you do not know the Lee Morgan story I strongly suggest you add it to your list of things to watch. It features interviews from some big names (most notably Wayne Shorter). Be warned it is quite a sad and tragic story, so don't go in expecting lemon drops and rainbows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/017-Cornbread/ICalledHimMorgan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee's trumpet sound for me was always clean, clear and powerful and he always played with authority. This didn't go unnoticed and he joined Dizzy Gillespie's big band and just 18 years old. Shortly afterwards appearing on &quot;Blue Train&quot; by John Coltrane and later went on to be an integral member of Art Blakey's Jazz Messengers. Progressing from being &quot;just&quot; a sideman Morgan moved on to release records under his own name as a leader, some are rightly regarded as all time classics and feature heavily in &quot;best selling&quot; album lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The personnel on Cornbread is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lee Morgan – Trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herbie Hancock – Piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Billy Higgins – Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jackie McLean – Alto sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hank Mobley – Tenor sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larry Ridley – Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many albums on this blog any one of these artists can (and in most cases have) released successful albums under their own name. Herbie of course needs no introduction and we saw Mobley in action a few posts back - he and Lee had a particularly prolific period of collaboration and have appeared on many albums together. They seem particularly well suited to each other as musicians and seem to have a near perfect sense of what the other is trying to achieve. Jackie McLean is probably a name you'd more likely associate with the avant-garde/free side of jazz (or perhaps &quot;fusion&quot;) - but on Cornbread we are all about the hard-bop and soul-jazz and he fits perfectly in this group also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with the title track (embedded at the start of this post). Within a matter of seconds it is clear that this album will be something special, you can hear the slight nervous energy and tension primed and waiting to be released. You can hear the obvious influence of Herbie in the arrangement - you feel as though this could easily feature on &quot;Takin Off&quot; or any of his other early works. There is a certain amount of Mobley in the DNA of the track too - but of course it is all about Lee Morgan. Lee takes the first solo on the track and throws it down, a lot of swagger and almost arrogance to what he's playing. As a listener it puts you completely at ease as you feel you're in safe hands. While it's not particularly &quot;outside&quot; in its approach that does not equate to &quot;harmonically boring&quot; and there's a lot to get excited about.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uRjshy_n_yE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another album highlight (for me) is the 3rd track &quot;Ceora&quot; - a beautiful ballad. I find ballads to be a real test for jazz artists, many fall down the trap of overplaying and throwing their ego at a tune. Others end up playing too &quot;inside&quot; and it just ends up a snooze-fest. Not here however, not only is the tune itself brilliantly written the solos are simply sublime. Lee in particular absolutely kills it with his solo; daring, interesting yet still simple and beautiful. Ballads are possibly not the first thing you think of when you here the &quot;Lee Morgan&quot; name but he is simply fantastic on this one. Herbie too takes a superb slow burning solo with real passion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the greatest thing about this album is the sheer consistency. From start to finish every single track is fantastic and worthy of note. From the slightly sombre standard &quot;Ill Wind&quot; (the only track not composed by Morgan on the album) or the hard-bop soul-jazz swinging groove of &quot;Most Like Lee&quot;. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8KQtco0UvHY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second track on the album is &quot;Our Man Higgins&quot; - penned as a reflection on drummer Billy Higgins (a legend in his own right). It is perhaps the most interesting of the tunes on this album, it relies heavily on chromaticism and is essentially a bridge between the &quot;free&quot; sound and the hard-bop sound. Higgins himself and of course McLean are well versed in the free side whereas Morgan and Mobley are more associated with the hard-bop side. This makes for some interesting tension throughout the piece as it sways between the styles depending on the soloist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have covered a lot of Blue Note records on this blog so far, and for good reason - they are on the whole fantastic. But one piece of the puzzle we have overlooked so far is Rudy Van Gelder the sound engineer. I bring this up in this post because Cornbread is such a fantastic sounding album, it has the quintessential &quot;hard-bop&quot; sound which helps raise the music that much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there were such a thing as a list of &quot;essential&quot; jazz albums this is certainly one I would feature. If you are looking for some jazz to listen to you can do much worse than give this one 40 minutes of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/017-Cornbread/Cornbread.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/017-Cornbread/Cornbread.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Elder Don and Round Hill Mbirizi</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/elder-don-mbirizi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elder Don and Round Hill Mbirizi" /><published>2020-08-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Elder-Don-Mbirizi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/elder-don-mbirizi">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-08-01-Elder-Don-Mbirizi.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NgYMCntcTBg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with the Round Hill Roastery with a filter roast from Burundi - an origin that has featured on the blog a few times in the past. This particular example is a washed Bourbon varietal, the coffee takes its name after the washing station where it was processed: Mbirizi. It is located in the north of the country close to the border with Rwanda. As far as I can tell this one has an SCA score of 87 and so we expect some quality in this cup!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in the previous post this coffee arrived in brown paper packaging instead of the usual baby blue you would expect from a Round Hill filter roast. As I stated I was never much of a fan of the blue/pink packaging so this was a welcome change. Yesterday however Round Hill announced a new packaging style (in the usual blue/pink colourways) - and I have to say I like it much more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/016-Elder-Don/roundhillbag.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives the coffee a more modern and clean look which I really like. I'm a firm believer that packaging matters a lot with coffees, the moment you get the bag in your hand you subconciously begin to develop expectations. If the bag is not aesthetically pleasing or looks &quot;amateur&quot; it is hard to get rid of this when it comes round to tasting the coffee itself. So I am very happy to see this new packaging and will look forward to my next Round Hill order to see how it looks &quot;in the flesh&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar way I also believe that the drinking vessel you use makes a big difference to how you perceive your coffee. I have tried a wide variety of cups for filter and demitasse for espresso and for me a few things seem to make a real difference. Firstly for filter I prefer a &quot;cup&quot; style with no handle as opposed to a mug, the hand warming sensation of grabbing a cup adds to the overall experience and feels more interactive. Secondly in terms of shape I tend to gravitate towards taller, thinner cups instead of shorter, squatter cups. The thin and tall nature of the cup means you have to tilt your head back slightly further to take a sip and so the aromatics can flow into the nostrils better, the sharper radius of the cup also means the coffee does not fill the mouth quite as much with each sip - you sacrifice a &quot;big mouthfeel&quot; but I find it easier to pick out more delicate acidic notes which are the ones I gravitate towards. I also like a thinner rim to drink from as an experience - this also helps the coffee cool quicker since there's less thermal mass. In terms of demitasse I go for much the same qualities really, although it is hard to find many thinner rim espresso cups since most want to keep the beverage hot for longer. Personally I'd rather the sensation of drinking from the thin rim in the knowledge I have to drink it quicker (since it's an espresso how long will it stick around anyway?) I also find sizing an issue with demitasse, many are larger than I would like since (I assume) they are designed in a way that allows you to make a macchiato/cortardo/etc. but I never bother with those. There is something upsetting about seeing an espresso barely make its way halfway up a cup! In terms of material I do not enjoy glass very much, although it is great to see the definition of the crema or clarity of the filter in them, so am usually looking for ceramic/porcelain. The &quot;earthenware&quot; style cups are nice to hold but again I do not like the drinking experience quite as much. And of course a paper takeaway cup is about the worst experience one can have, even without thinking about the environmental implication. But this is all personal preference so I'd suggest just trying a few different things and seeing what works for you and sometimes you may have recieved a cup as a gift and so you associate it with a loved one, in which case none of the &quot;technical&quot; stuff matters!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the coffee itself: as usual starting with the filter. This coffee is one of the most sensitive to temperature I think I've ever seen. First cup I made I took the first sip while it was still quite hot and thought I had made a big mistake. There was no flavour definition and it was just kind of muddled. However letting it cool down a few degrees and it really comes alive. The cup is fairly complex, there are orange and grapefruit citrus flavours there, I notice raspberries too and an almost red-wine like vibe to the whole thing. In the aftertaste I'm left with a tea-like floral quality that is very clean. Very nice and super interesting yet surprisingly easy to drink too. Unfortunately I find if it cools too much it starts to deteriorate and lose balance, so there's a relatively narrow temperature window for this coffee for me. I guess this would be a perfect coffee to use with a temperature controlled ember mug! As an espresso this coffee is an interesting one, based on the filter I was convinced I needed to use my &quot;typical&quot; filter roast espresso style, quick hot long pulls, but this wasn't right. By no means unpleasant but it seemed to lack a bit of punch. I dialed back to something closer to a &quot;traditional&quot; recipe and it really came alive. The red wine-y thing really jumped out at first, the citrus flavours were a little muted but that same aftertaste that I liked in the filter was still there - in fact it was a more intense aftertaste in the espresso which was certainly welcomed. Overall I enjoyed this one a lot and it is certainly quirky, I imagine with more time to play around I could uncover some more interesting things about this coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly onto this weeks jazz. This week has been a busy one in JazzCoffeeStuff HQ and so I've been craving simplicity in the music I've been listening to. One place I like to go for simplicity is the Blue Note &quot;Soul Jazz&quot; movement of the 1960s (which we have visited before with Lou Donaldson). In digging through the archives I re-discovered an oft-overlooked artist: Don Wilkerson. After much deliberation I decided to settle on the album &quot;Elder Don&quot; (but don't ask me tomorrow or I'll pick a different one from his trio of Blue Note recordings).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/016-Elder-Don/Elder_Don.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don Wilkerson is not really a &quot;name&quot; in jazz, I would go as far as to say even some hardened jazz fans might not even recognise the name. He has very limited recorded output, he has 3 records on Blue Note (&quot;Elder Don&quot;, &quot;Preach Brother&quot; and &quot;Shoutin'&quot;) and an earlier record on Riverside (&quot;Texas Twister&quot;). However it is highly likely you will have heard him play: he recorded sax solos on some of Ray Charles biggest hits such as &quot;I Got a Woman&quot; and &quot;Hallelujah I Love Her So&quot;. He is known for a powerful and confident tenor sound. This is about the limits of my knowledge about him, as I say he's very underappreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The line up on &quot;Elder Don&quot; is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don Wilkerson - tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Acea - piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grant Green - guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lloyd Trotman - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Willie Bobo - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who apart from Green (and maybe Bobo) are not what you would call &quot;big names&quot; in jazz. In fact I would struggle to name any other recrdings featuring Acea or Trotman at all. This doesn't matter however since on this album they are great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embedded above is the 3rd track, closing side A of the record called &quot;Scrappy&quot;, it is probably the most &quot;hard bop&quot; this record gets. The main melody comprising of a cool doubled line between Wilkerson and Green. The Wilkerson powerful tenor sound is there throughout his solo which is relatively simple melodically and harmonically but packs a punch. This is followed by a typical Grant Green masterclass in jazzy-blues. As a guitarist myself I've always respected the laid-back approch Green has, it's very easy for a guitarist to get &quot;too excited&quot; and throw too many notes around but Green never does this. I'm also a big fan of his guitar tone, many jazz guitarists have pretty questionable tone in my experience but Green's is always great - punchy and throaty sounding. I'm not sure but it sounds like he's using his Gibson 330 on this record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite &quot;just&quot; being a soul-jazz record &quot;Elder Don&quot; actually covers a lot of ground. The opening track &quot;Señorita Eula&quot;, as the name suggests takes a latin influence to the soul-jazz or hard-bop sound. The main left hand riff of Acea also has a strong Professor Longhair influence to it. The record thus starts with a celebratory party atmosphere. The latin influence moves to Cuba in the 2nd track &quot;San Antonio Rose&quot; - these two tunes leaning into the Willie Bobo wheelhouse which gives a feeling of authenticity. The final track on the album &quot;Poor Butterfly&quot; is a soft slow ballad, very different from the preceeding tracks and gives the album some depth.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3Ui-6AryejQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

My choice pick on the album however is &quot;Lone Star Shuffle&quot;. As the name suggests this is a simple blues shuffle. As much as I love sophisticated jazz harmony sometimes a basic blues played with attitude is all you need. Both Wilkerson and Green are totally at home playing a shuffle, their playing will not blow you away with sophistication or complexity but it has its place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the album is probably not a &quot;must listen, all time classic&quot; that you need to own in your collection. It does serve a purpose however when you don't want to think too much or perhaps you just need something on in the background there are certainly worse records to serve that purpose. There is often a bit of jazz snobbery whereby only the most complicated, sophisticated and groundbreaking records/artists get respect - but for me there's a time and place for the less adventurous stuff too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/016-Elder-Don/Elder_Don.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/016-Elder-Don/Elder_Don.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>