<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-18T07:05:16-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Tuesday Wonderland and PLOT Fidel Huancas</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/tuesday-wonderland-fidel-huancas" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tuesday Wonderland and PLOT Fidel Huancas" /><published>2020-07-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Tuesday-Wonderland-Fidel-Huancas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/tuesday-wonderland-fidel-huancas">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-07-11-Tuesday-Wonderland-Fidel-Huancas.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9VF8kxFEEsA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are heading back to a relatively new roaster for me: PLOT coffee roasters in Woolwich. Readers may remember a trio of their coffees featured on the page a couple of months ago which were heavily favoured. This is part of my second order from them. I'm hesitant to judge a roaster based on a single order so we will see if this one lives up to the previous coffees from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again I am very impressed with the packaging, the pink and black branded packing boxes through to the &quot;sound wave&quot; style logos on the bags it is all very well done. The packaging is something I always look at when judging a roaster/coffee, it is my opinion that you make judgements about a coffee from the instant you see it and having attractive packaging adds to this. You &quot;first drink with your eyes&quot; is the expression I believe! Further good packaging to me suggests that a roaster is leaving no stone unturned, they are concerned with how their coffee is perceived at every step of the coffee drinking journey - I think this is a good indicator of attention to detail and passion, both of which are crucially important to find in a roaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee today is called: &quot;Fidel Huancas - Chirinos Competition Lot&quot; - which is a bit of a mouthful. Fidel Huancas is the man behind the coffee, the producer who is responsible for ensuring the quality of the on site processing, growing, etc. Chirinos is the district of the province San Ignacio where the farm is located. This is in the north west corner of the country, not too far from the border with Ecuador. The term &quot;competition lot&quot; has sprung up more and more in recent years, it does not seem to be a protected term but is meant to be an indicator that the coffee is of a quality that it could be used in barita or brewing competitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A piece of information you often find on the label of a coffee or on the roasters website is &quot;altitude&quot; or &quot;elevation&quot; - this is measured in meters above sea level (MASL) and as one would expect represents how &quot;high&quot; the coffee bushes are grown. When I was first getting into specialty coffee many many moons ago people were obsessing over altitude, people often judging whether to buy a coffee based on this metric alone. These days it appears as though the metric is not given the weight it once was, which in my opinion is a good thing. Generally speaking a coffee at a higher altitude will be favoured as being sweeter and more complex, and so some aim for higher altitude coffees as a result. Unfortunately it is not quite that simple. Higher does not necessarily mean better, what really matters (or so it seems) is the speed at which the coffee plants grow which is related to temperature. At a higher altitude generally the temperature will be lower which means the plants will grow more slowly and develop the complex flavours and sugars we are after. However we can equally find lower altitude locations that have lower temperatures and slower growing cherries which are equally delicious!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately temperature is not something that is easy to quantify, each day the temperature will fluctuate and over the course of a growing season there may be large swings. Even the &quot;average temperature&quot; nor the temperature range tell us very much at all. As such altitude has become the proxy metric used. Personally I never look at altitude at all when deciding on whether to buy or try a coffee, I have not found it a particularly useful indicator for any particular characteristic or quality. Everybody is different though, so if you find that there is a strong correlation between coffees you enjoy and the altitude they're grown at stick with it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the tasting of this coffee. The first thing that strikes me with this coffee is the dry aroma of the beans (both whole and ground) - the smell is very intense. I'd describe it as a dried fruit sweet sort of smell laced with a delicate floral note. I usually find that the very best tasting coffees have a very intense dry aroma, it is not universally true and a great dry aroma does not always translate to a good cup but this coffee is onto a good start! As usual starting with my usual filter set up. The first thing I get hit with is apricot, this coffee has it in spades! Those that know me know that, while I'm not big on desserts, an apricot tart is one of my favourite things. This coffee reminds me a bit of that. If apricot is the head note of the coffee the heart is sweet caramel which gives some body to the coffee, perhaps apricot compote is a good descriptor given this syrupy body. As the coffee cools floral notes begin to appear and these linger in the aftertaste which is long lived and clean. Moving onto the espresso the flavour profile is much the same. I found that this coffee likes to be pulled long, about a 2.7:1 works for me. Too short and the flavours get a bit muddled and it's hard to discern individual notes. As a longer pull the flavours are defined and totally delicious! At this level the syrupy mouthfeel has all but gone but I feel this is a fair compromise. Pulling out floral notes in an espresso can be difficult, they are often dominated by the &quot;heavier&quot; notes but they manage to punch through in the aftertaste here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another stand out coffee for me from the folks at PLOT. If this one is not in my shortlist for &quot;coffees of the year&quot; I have some outstanding coffees to look forward to in the last 6 months of the year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's jazz is the 2006 seminal album &quot;Tuesday Wonderland&quot; by Esbjörn Svennson Trio (EST) on the ACT record label:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/013-Tuesday-Wonderland/Tuesday-Wonderland.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember the lead up to this album being released very vividly, at the time I was a regular reader of Jazzwise magazine and it felt like every issue for the year leading up to the release (and subsequently) had an article about this album. By this point EST were already big names in the jazz world. In the late 1990s to early 2000s jazz was in a bit of a lull, by this point the whole &quot;fusion&quot; thing had lost its way and there was a movement back towards more &quot;traditional&quot; styles, however what was lacking was a young act who won international acclaim, this is where EST came in. They almost singlehandedly kept jazz alive during this period and spawned many imitators who are still playing with the &quot;EST sound&quot; today. Unusually for an album surrounded in such hype and expectation &quot;Tuesday Wonderland&quot; not only lived up to it but possibly exceeded it, which is not something you can say often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EST style is hard to put down in words but unmistakable once you hear it. There is a clear influence of modern European classical composers (they list Bartok in particular as an influence regularly). Esbjörn's piano style also takes inspiration from Keith Jarrett to my ear. While each member plays (primarily) on acoustic instruments they layer these with multi-track recording and run electronic effects to keep things fresh. Magnus Öström is on drum duty for the band and plays with both manic urgency as well as tender subtlty, feeling most at home playing drum and bass and techno grooves. Dan Berglund on bass brings with him the thunderous weight through the rock and heavy metal influence to preceedings. EST represents &quot;fusion&quot; in its truest sense being a melting pot of ideas. In doing this they managed to create a sound all to themselves that is not like anything that came before it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite pieces from the entire EST back catalogue is &quot;The Goldhearted Miner&quot; (embedded above). It is a beautiful subtle piece with a very strong melody. It is the sort of tune I could imagine being a standard if it had been released some 60 years earlier. It does not have quite the &quot;broad influence&quot; that some of the other pieces on the album have however. Perhaps their biggest hit is &quot;Goldwrap&quot;:

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xCuGTuDsVoY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This even had a &quot;proper&quot; music video associated with it! Back in 2006 this was essentially unheard of, I can't think of another record from the era that had that sort of reach. It shows how big the band had become, I seem to remember even seeing this appear on the music TV channels on satelite television at the time. Compared to &quot;The Goldhearted Miner&quot; this one features more prominently some of the electronic effects on the instruments and some of the EST-isms that made the band so popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Live the band were also a force to be reckoned with. They managed to attract a young &quot;hip&quot; crowd that comprised of jazz fans, electronic music fans and rock fans alike. The crowd hanging on every single the note, and the band acting like a conductor whipping the audience up into a frenzy. There was also a running &quot;bit&quot; that Esbjörn did; the band would play 3 or 4 tunes on the bounce and then Esbjörn would try to announce what was just played to the crowd but &quot;forgot&quot; the names and the more eager members of the audience would shout out to remind him. I'm not sure if it was a genuine slip of the mind from being so deep into the moment or whether it was just a shtick, either way it certainly added a little humour to the gigs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately Esbjörn died tragically young, at just the age of 44, in a freak scuba diving accident in 2008 only 2 years after the release of &quot;Tuesday Wonderland&quot;. This was a devestating event in recent jazz history and he will be sorely missed. I was forunate enough to catch, what turned out to be, one of the last UK shows. It was truly fantastic and a totally memorable experience. Afterwards I even got to meet the band as they hung around for autographs and the like. Unfortunately camera phones of the day were still fairly rudimentary (at least the one I had) so I do not have a high-def picture but you can see me as a fresh-faced wee nipper below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/013-Tuesday-Wonderland/MEST.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To end this post I'll leave one of the more experimental cuts from the album called: &quot;Brewery of Beggars&quot;. I feel this really captures the &quot;melting pot&quot; ethos of the band and highlights the use of electronic effects and rockier sounds the band were known for.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3umiaQLwR38&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/013-Tuesday-Wonderland/Tuesday-Wonderland.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/013-Tuesday-Wonderland/Tuesday-Wonderland.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Grand Wazoo and Assembly Bumbogo</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/grand-wazoo-bumbogo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Grand Wazoo and Assembly Bumbogo" /><published>2020-07-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Grand-Wazoo-Bumbogo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/grand-wazoo-bumbogo">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-07-04-Grand-Wazoo-Bumbogo.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jymHINLcjlw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with the London based Assembly coffee roasters. We are drinking a washed Rwandan coffee by the name Bumbogo. Those who have read previous blog posts here will know about the Assembly &quot;paint swirls&quot; for this coffee the swirl can be seen below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/012-Grand-Wazoo/Bumbogo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many Rwandans this coffee is a bourbon varietal, which we have talked about in the blog in the past. Rwanda is a fairly small country that shares many land borders. This particular coffee is grown in the Gakenke region which is in the north of the country and is close to the borders with Uganda and the Democratic Republic of the Congo. For such a small country Rwanda produces lots of great coffees with a reasonable amount of variation. I would say the &quot;classic&quot; Rwandan style of coffee has high acidity and sweetness typically with lots of red berry type tasting notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washed African coffees roasted for filter (such as this one) can be notoriously finnicky to dial in for espresso, many do not even bother trying and stick to more developed darker roasts which are more forgiving and do not have quite as much acidity. Personally this is my favourite style of espresso and so I will talk about some things that I do to make these roasts work for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting off with the water: even as espresso a large amount of what you're drinking is water. A water that tastes good on its own does not necessarily translate to good coffee (but a bad tasting water certainly will translate to bad coffee!) A lot has been written about water for coffee and the widely held consensus is there are 2 components of the water that matter: the &quot;general hardness&quot; ions (calcium and magnesium) and &quot;buffer&quot; (carbonates and bicarbonates). Without getting too deep into the science at a very high level the &quot;general hardness&quot; carries the flavour and the &quot;buffer&quot; acts to reduce the acidity. One might think then that a large amount of calcium/magnesium in the water is a good thing as it will enhance the flavour, but this is generally not the case - too little and the coffee is hollow tasting, too much and it tastes muddy and lacking clarity. There is a sweet spot. The same with bicarbonate, too little and the acidity can be harsh and too much and the coffee tastes dull.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a bright acidic style of coffee one might assume that we would want a higher buffer content to try and &quot;tame&quot; the acidity. In my experience this is not true, I find for the lighter roasts you want a &quot;lighter&quot; water with fewer ions. This seems to let the coffee speak a bit more. I find the lightly mineralized water out of my RO unit works well, this has a remineralization cartridge which adds in some of these ions (but nothing else). For those not looking to go that far bottled water typically has a composition on the label which you can use. You can treat the water with a filter jug (for example) but the quality is directly tied to the quality of your tap water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important consideration is the grinder you use. The general consensus is you want to have a flat burr grinder as opposed to a conical burr grinder for lighter roasts since they can produce a more uniform grind distribution. A rule of thumb is the bigger the burrs the better the grinder, but there are exceptions and things like alignment matter as does burr speed. That's not to say you can't get good quality light roast espresso with a conical just typically the flat burr grinders are preffered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the dialing in process itself, in my experience there are 2 variables that really make the difference with light roasts: brew temperature and ratio. Generally you will want a hotter brew for a lighter roast in my experience, the acidity &quot;turns into&quot; sweetness with a high temperature (I'm aware that's not correct at a chemical level). But you have to be careful, turning up too high and you lose everything, all the flavours are lost and you're left with a cup of &quot;brown&quot;. Very small changes make a big difference, if your machine doesn't have temperature control then you can often &quot;temperature surf&quot; by pulling blank shots to vary the temperature but you don't have quite the same control obviously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ratio of an espresso is the weight of liquid you are left with versus how much dry ground coffee you put into the portafilter. A typical ratio for a &quot;normal&quot; espresso is 2:1 - say you put 18g coffee in the basket then you'd pull a shot that gives 36g of liquid. For lighter roasts longer is generally better, sometimes even up to &quot;lungo&quot; range of 3:1 or even more. Pulling the shot longer again accentuates the sweetness. However in doing so you lose body and if you go too far you'll end up with a weaker &quot;watery&quot; type shot that is not enjoyable. As a starting point 2.5:1 is generally my go to and I adjust from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read a guide online to dialing in espresso there will be a lot of talk about &quot;timing&quot; and how the &quot;perfect&quot; shot will take 27-32s to pull. While this might be a decent yardstick for a more normal roast for light roasts this will lead to disappointment in my experience. Lighter roasts like to be pulled in a different way, typically a longer slower pre-infusion stage (this lightly saturates the puck with water to &quot;prime&quot; it and raise the temperature of the coffee puck) followed by a much quicker pull - possibly in the region of 20s. I don't use timing as a variable I &quot;target&quot; I let the timing fall as it falls but I keep a note of it for consistency reasons, if I'm pulling a shot again and it's much slower/quicker it might suggest I've done something else incorrectly in my prep!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few other smaller considerations that seem to help in my experience: firstly tamping, a light tamp is your friend (up to a point!) tamping hard is unnecessary and seems to lead to more channeling and other issues. I also like to dose less with light roast coffees whereas I might normally dose 18g for a more developed roast I might go down as low as 15g for a particuarly light roast as that seems to work a bit better. In addition to this I find that underdosing a basket (e.g. putting those 15g of coffee into an 18g basket) helps with ensuring the pre-infusion is slower and more gentle - although this might just be an artefact of the setups I have used rather than a universal truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But back onto Bumbogo itself: starting as always with the filter. We have the typical &quot;red berry&quot; Rwandan type thing coming to the front. Assembly describe this as a &quot;cranberry&quot; note which I don't disagree with at all - it has that slightly tart/sour note in there. This is supported with a caramel or burnt sugar sort of note which helps balance the acidity. I like to taste the coffees before reading the tasting notes and one thing I wrote down is a green grape like finish which Assembly did not note. Overall it is quite a clean tasting coffee but with a thick syrupy sort of body. It is not the most complex coffee I've ever had but it is certainly delicious. Onto the espresso I was a little amazed at just how forgiving this was, I struggled to make a &quot;bad&quot; shot. I found that it worked best at very high temperatures and around a 2.2:1 ratio. There the cranberry and red currant notes really come to the front and the body is syrupy and has hints of a heavy red wine like quality. Overall a very good little coffee!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This weeks album is likely to be a little contenious: Frank Zappa - The Grand Wazoo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/012-Grand-Wazoo/Grand-Wazoo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some may argue &quot;but this is not jazz!&quot; - but I've never been particularly concerned with defined boundaries to musical genres, some of my favourite albums straddle the line between multiple styles. This might mean the jazz police will knock down the doors of JazzCoffeeStuff HQ but that's a price worth paying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years Frank made some rather disparaging comments about jazz which didn't do much to endear him to the jazz community. However looking at the personnel in some of his bands I think it's safe to say we should take some of the comments at face value, many great jazz musicians played with him over the years. He also famously had Mahavishnu Orchestra open for him on a few tours, the experience left such an imprint that Frank completely tore down his band a built a new band and sound up in its place.In addition he wrote a piece dedicated to Eric Dolphy (although not on this album) - if Eric didn't die so tragically young we can only imagine what would have happened had he recorded with Frank. I find the &quot;Dolphy influence&quot; quite strong through a lot of Franks work, I can only assume it is through the love both of them share for composer Edgar Varese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frank composed, recorded and released this album in 1972 while he was in rehab following his assault by a fan in London a year earlier. It follows on in the vain of Waka/Jawacka which itself follows on from Hot Rats in terms of Frank's jazz-fusion offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Grand Wazoo is a bit of an outlier in the Zappa back catalogue. It features a large band (22 members) and some brilliant arrangements. It is possibly the &quot;jazziest&quot; of Frank's jazz fusion offerings. I have to admit I sometimes struggle with fusion when it attempts to employ a &quot;rock&quot; feel. A big part of rock is the attitude and often on fusion records a jazz guy will add some distorted guitars and think that is enough and the whole thing ends up sounding nerdy rather than cool. Given Frank is at home in a rock context the blend is much more seemless than many. The album is almost entirely instrumental apart from a few vocal lines on &quot;For Calvin (And His Next Two Hitch-Hikers)&quot; (which tells a narrative of 2 warring musical factions according to the liner notes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern classical influence is also noticable on this album. Given when it was released this was probably one of the first examples on record of Frank playing with these ideas, the time spent alone following the assault probably gave him a chance to better explore these ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me the two standout pieces are the two closing tracks. &quot;Eat That Question&quot; (embedded above) is an absolutely raucous affair starting off with a short intro from jazz-keyboard maestro and long-term Zappa collaborator George Duke. Before breaking into the main theme which is one of the strongest melodies in the Zappa canon and one he came back to many times when performing live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final track on the album is called &quot;Blessed Relief&quot;:

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/x-Qk8VxUwuM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This is a much more mellow and chilled out affair. However the melody isn't any less strong and features some absolutely beautiful arrangement. Some Zappa tunes can get a bit &quot;complicated for the sake of complicated&quot; which sometimes has its place, however on this one we see Frank is just as able to write a &quot;straight&quot; tune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a guitar player Frank was always what I consider a &quot;visceral&quot; player, he doesn't aim to have perfect technique he just plays what he feels. Most of the time he solos over one chord vamps, sometimes for 10-20mins at time. Many guitarists look down on him for this but being able to play for an extended time over a one chord vamp is a real skill, you very quickly end up aimlessly noodling without any changes to drive your ideas forward. It is always noticable on Zappa records where the supporting musicians solo over the changes of the compositions but when it comes time for Frank's turn they revert to a simple vamp. On &quot;Blessed Relief&quot; however we are treated to hearing Frank play the changes, which is certainly note worthy in itself! He doesn't approach this in the way a jazz player might and he's only following the changes in a fairly loose sense but it is great to hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most &quot;jazzy&quot; of all the pieces on show however is the title track &quot;The Grand Wazoo&quot; (depending on the pressing you own of the record this may be the first or the second track!) Clocking in at over 13 minutes it is by far the longest and most ambitious piece on the record. While the tempo is quite frantic the music itself slowly glides through the various themes and motifs present throughout the piece. In some sense it has the &quot;swan like&quot; quality of many of the successful jazz big-bands - elegantly gliding along but under the surface paddling manically! There are some brilliantly wild brass and woodwind solos dotted throughout the piece but it is really the arrangement itself that is so memorable. You could easily dedicate a blog post (or more) analysing every technique and trick on show here but ultimately the proof is in the listening:

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4ceVq2v3nVs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Overall I consider this album one of the strongest in the Zappa catalogue and one certainly worthy of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/012-Grand-Wazoo/Grand-Wazoo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/012-Grand-Wazoo/Grand-Wazoo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Expectations and Assembly Raimutin</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/expectations-raimutin" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Expectations and Assembly Raimutin" /><published>2020-06-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Expectations-Raimutin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/expectations-raimutin">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-06-27-Expectations-Raimutin.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/W27fqMOaun0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

In this blog post we're heading back to Assembly coffee roasters located in Brixton, London. For my money Assembly are consistently one of the best roasters in the country and one of my favourites since they seem to share very similar taste preferences to me - no matter what I buy from them I'm always left impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee this week is called Raimutin, it is naturally processed and is made up of a lend of Timor, moka and typica varietals. In a previous blog post we learned that &quot;most coffee varietals can trace their lineage back to either typica or bourbon&quot; - in this case that is not true. To understand the Timor varietal we need to take a step further back in coffees history. Coffee plants can be split into two broad camps: Arabica and Robusta (there are a few others but they're rare and for arguments sake this is a good description). The &quot;typica-bourbon&quot; lineage exists in the arabica side. Arabica is typically favoured for higher cup quality and depth of flavour - specialty coffee is almost entirely dominated by Arabica. The &quot;downsides&quot; of arabica are lower yields and lower caffeine content. The Timor varietal is essentially a hybrid between arabica and robusta. It retains a lot of the robusta hardiness and is more resistant to leaf-rust, pests, etc. while retaining some of the arabica cup quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raimutin is from the country of Democratic Republic of Timor-Leste. You would be forgiven for not having heard of this country before since it only found its sovereignty in 2002. It shares a small island with Indonesian-Timor to its south-west. It is located in south-east Asia - between Indonesia and Australia. For those who enjoy a pub quiz it is also the only Asian country to be entirely located in the southern hemisphere. In recent years coffee production in Timor-Leste has increased and every now and again their coffees pop up in quality roasteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit I am not usually a fan of Asian coffees, I tend to find them a bit heavy for my taste and they often seem to have &quot;smokey&quot; or &quot;tobacco&quot; style notes I personally do not care for (although I understand why people love them). I have heard through the grapevine that the &quot;best&quot; Asian coffees do not leave the area and you have to travel to the area to really try the best the area has to offer. Having never travelled there let alone tasted coffee there I don't know if there is any truth to this. Since this coffee was roasted by Assembly I thought I'd try it however as I've yet to have a coffee from them I disliked (in fact this is my second bag of this coffee - I ordered a &quot;mystery bundle&quot; of a random selection of coffees and this one was included.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't mention the Assembly roastery without mentioning the packaging, the most stylish beautifully designed packaging I have ever seen! Plus they're not foil backed bags so they're easy to recycle which is a positive. I know many will say packaging doesn't make a difference, but I disagree entirely. From the moment you pick up a bag of coffee you make subconcious assessments about it. These definitely carry over to the cup. Unfortunately with current world events it appears they are struggling to source their usual bags so the coffee arrived in &quot;interim packaging&quot; (their phrasing) which is still quite nice (but not quite as elegant as the usual offering). What I really like about the Assembly aesthetic is their &quot;paint swirl&quot; logo designs. For this particular coffee this is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/011-Expectations/Raimutin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know if I have a very mild form of synesthesia or what but I definitely taste &quot;in colour&quot; - by which I mean the first thing that pops into my head when tasting anything is &quot;this tastes green&quot; or &quot;this tastes yellow&quot;, it then takes me a while to translate this &quot;green&quot; into a grape or the &quot;yellow&quot; into a banana flavour note. I tend to find the paint swirls for individual coffees to be a good match to the flavour notes of the coffee inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting off in the usual way with a pour-over filter brew: the first thing that hits me in the face is &quot;purple&quot; - in this case for me this is shows as plum and cherry brandy. I tend to find some natural processed coffees to have this &quot;boozy&quot; fortified alcohol sort of quality to them and this one certainly has that. However it is not a super-funky natural, there is some funk there but it is more a Bruno Mars pop record influenced by funk rather than a full blown George Clinton and Parliament Funkadelic. The mouthfeel of the coffee is big and juicy yet it still remains fairly &quot;clean&quot; tasting for a coffee of this style. There is some acidity cutting through the sweetness and body however, for me it takes the form of a lime sharpness and it really helps balance everything out. I find this one needs to cool down a bit before it really comes alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso (in the last blog post we didn't touch on espresso so it's nice to bring it back) - for me this is where it really shines. The big body really comes to the forefront and you are left with a really pleasing thick shot even when you pull it slightly longer (which is recommended). The boozy notes are still there in force and it is really rich and indulgent. The acidity is still there but it's just there for ballast to support the bigger bolder notes. For a fairly light roast coffee I find this one of the easiest to pull espressos out there, it is super forgiving and you can really swing the grind settings around and still get super tasty shots out of it. My &quot;recipe&quot; for this one was 16.5g of coffee in to 38.0g of coffee out. I set the temperature of my machine to almost as high as it goes. I pre-infuse for around 5-10s and then my shot time comes in at around 22-24s. For me this is the sweetspot - you still get the lovely indulgent mouthfeel but it's long enough that the flavours don't get too lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a super fun enjoyable coffee! In both filter and espresso there is a (very) long aftertaste which is satisfying, it pretty much mimics the flavours in the cup itself and is clean and pleasant, no hint of any sourness or acrid qualities that sometimes come with these long aftertastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To pair with this coffee I have settled on an album from 1972 from Keith Jarrett called &quot;Expectations&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/011-Expectations/Expectations.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album was released on the Columbia record label, Jarrett having recorded with Miles Davis on this label previously. It is Jarrett's only record on Columbia under his own name. He then moved onto the ECM label and played a large part in the success of that label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At JazzCoffeeStuff I try and not be negative but I am going to break that rule today. Not through the music on this album or Jarrett's music in general which is fantastic, but about the man himself. Jarrett has always tried to paint himself as a &quot;saviour&quot; or &quot;holier than thou&quot; sort of figure which I've personally never taken to. As a result he essentially bans any extraneous noise in his concerts, as a result they have an atmosphere more akin to a morgue than to a place of enjoyment. For me the community aspect and audience &quot;participation&quot; of a jazz concert is part of the magic, cutting that out kills the music. I know he's trying to elevate the music to that of &quot;high art&quot;, and I get that, but for me it loses all that is important about the art form. I remember a few years ago he was playing at the London Jazz Festival (I didn't go to that particular concert) and through a friend I understand he heard a &quot;whirring&quot; in the audience so stormed off stage - it turned out to be a person in a wheelchair. Eventually he was persuaded to come back on stage but offered nothing in the way of an apology. I have heard plenty of other &quot;horror stories&quot; about his concerts, it's a real shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second complaint with Jarrett is the &quot;Jarrett grunts&quot; - when improvising he will very loudly grunt and it is completely atonal and has nothing to do with what he's playing. He doesn't need to do it because I've heard him play many times without doing so, I'm not really sure why he does this. You can here some of this in the clip below (but take nothing away from the sheer quality of the piano playing)

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LWEe1JKY7mI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

With those rants out of the way lets get onto the album itself. Thankfully in 1972 Jarrett hadn't yet gone &quot;full grunt&quot; and so there isn't a whole lot of this to distract on the album. After a short introduction piece the album kicks off proper with &quot;Common Mama&quot; (embedded at the start of this blog post) - and what a start it is. Keith is joined by Paul Motian on drums, Charlie Haden on the Bass, Sam Brown on guitar, Dewey Redman on tenor sax and Airto Moreira on percussion. In addition there are uncredited string and brass sections. The main melody of Common Mama is so strong you can be humming it for weeks after hearing it. By having both drums and percussion the rhythm section is really grooving and it allows Dewey a chance to really let loose and get wild! The combination of Motian/Haden/Redman is something you're more likely to hear on a purely &quot;free&quot; album, it is interesting to hear them in the context of &quot;prettier&quot; music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The free side doesn't stay hidden for long however and by track 4 &quot;Roussillion&quot; we're treated to a piece that wouldn't be out of place on an Ornette Coleman album. In fact the main melody itself does have a tinge of &quot;Lonely Woman&quot; about it. Motian is absolutely in his element here driving the complex melody throughout and directing the soloists with ease. Motian is one of my favourite drummers in that respect and is probably deserving of more kudos than he gets.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9Ci3jq0aY1A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Being a double album there is a lot of music on show, and it is an extremely eclectic mix. Ranging from the more latin world-music influences of the opening number, through more typical &quot;Jarrett&quot; classically inspired pieces through to the rampant free-jazz. Along the way there's also glimmers of soul-jazz and jazz-rock fusion and at points even &quot;calypso&quot;. As a result this is quite a hard record to &quot;classify&quot;, it is almost a microcosm all to itself. That is probably why this is an often overlooked album in the Jarrett back-catalogue. However it shows what a tremendous talent Jarrett has as a band leader, composer and improviser. For my money it should be celebrated as a masterpiece and one record that is surely worth your time. We'll end with the beautiful title track which is definitely the &quot;most Jarrett&quot; piece on the album:

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Od2z6yDhBnY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/011-Expectations/Expectations.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/011-Expectations/Expectations.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Clifford Brown &amp;amp; Max Roach and Gold Box Cupping</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/clifford-brown-and-max-roach-cupping" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clifford Brown &amp; Max Roach and Gold Box Cupping" /><published>2020-06-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Clifford-Brown-And-Max-Roach-Cupping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/clifford-brown-and-max-roach-cupping">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-06-20-Clifford-Brown-And-Max-Roach-Cupping.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vJ7tDo-TOOw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

For my tenth post on this blog we're going to do something a bit different this week. Instead of focussing on one particular coffee we are going to look at many! I purchased a &quot;taster&quot; pack from the folks at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goldboxroastery.com/&quot;&gt;Gold Box Coffee Roasters&lt;/a&gt; and decided to do some cupping! Unfortunately the tasting packs are small (around 30g each) and so I will not be able to talk about espresso this week (but that will surely change in the next installment).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought one sample in particular that I did not want to form part of the cupping as I wanted to investigate it fully. It is a Bolivian Gesha varietal with a semi-anaerobic processing. This is one of the &quot;fancy new&quot; processing methods that has sprung up in recent years, in essence we can think of most of these as being variations on a natural processing but with more measurement/controlled conditions. In this case the coffee spends part of its processing life in sealed air-tight containers where the fermentations can be controlled. I tend to find these experimental processing methods a bit hit and miss, sometimes they produce wild and interesting flavour notes but sometimes they will impart a &quot;hollow&quot; vibe somewhat akin to a decaf process in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolivia is one of my favourite origins, when I was first getting into specialty (c2008) there were a lot of Bolivians on the market and they form some of my favourite early coffee memories (I remember a particuarly good one from Monmouth and a few from Hasbean). However over the years the specialty coffee production has decreased in the country owing to the country allowing the growth of Coca (used to make cocaine) which offers more dependable money to farmers, sadly as a result many coffee plants have been torn out and possibly lost forever. There are still some high quality coffees coming out of the region however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gesha varietal has become a bit of a poster-child for the specialty industry lately, in any barista/roasting competition it has basically become a showcase for Gesha varietals. The varietal is believed to have originated in Ethiopia but it rose to prominence thanks to a particular farm in Panama which bumped the price of the varietal into the stratosphere. The varietal itself produces very floral and fragrant coffee. The flavour profiles tend to be delicate or muted but they are notoriously &quot;marmite&quot; with some people not liking them at all. I've had my fair share of Gesha and while it's great I don't like to spend the big bucks on them as I tend to find the value proposition is better elsewhere. This particular coffee from Gold Box, however, piqued my interest because I have never had a Bolivian Gesha so wanted to give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm really glad I gave it a try! But I'm a little annoyed at myself for not buying a full bag (I had 50g only - about 3 cups worth). It is a truly special coffee, it has that delicate floral nature and all the fragrance you would want. There is a strong ginger note to it too which I'm not sure I've noticed in another coffee before. With the floral nature it is a little like having a good quality black tea and a ginger nut - but all in one cup! It's complex enough to keep you interested and coming back for more yet not so challenging as to be a distraction from whatever else you are doing. I would describe both the sweetness and acidity as medium, it is very down the middle (in a good way). There is some body there but not too much, you still get a lot of clarity in the cup. There is no hint of the &quot;emptiness&quot; of a fancy processing method, I'm not sure whether if this is because it has only spent part of its life anaerobically or whether it is just done particuarly well. Overall I'm very impressed with it, I would certainly buy again and I'd love to see how it performs as an espresso (Geshas tend to be a bit difficult to dial in). Hopefully this is a sign of things to come with the cupping!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll quickly outline my cupping methodology, I don't follow a specific guideline and I like to do things a little differently to some. I am not a professional cupper nor do I do it very often. Coffee should be fun however  so with any method you should tailor it to suit you! In total I have 8 coffee samples from various origins. As soon as the coffee arived I removed the labels and replaced them with a randomly generated 3 alpha-numeric identifier (storing the key on my computer to look up after!) I like to use codes like this when blind tasting as opposed to &quot;coffee 1&quot; or &quot;coffee A&quot; as that naturally sets up an expectation that &quot;1&quot; is better than &quot;2&quot; and so on. I then left the coffees for a week so that there would be very little chance I'd remember the codes I set up (it's safe to say it worked, I can't even remember what origins there were let alone specific coffees!) So this is about as blind as I can make a test on my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/010-Brown-Roach/cupping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the cupping itself I used 7.5g of coffee to 125g of 100 degree water. I lined the bowls with filter paper so I could scoop out the grinds in one go (I hate the gritty feeling of grinds in the bowl so I removed them - I know this is not traditional). I grind fairly coarse at around a french press level and I leave them to brew for 3 minutes before removing the grinds. I do not like doing large cuppings with many different coffees as I find it hard to keep track so I broke the 8 coffees into 2 groups of 4. On the first day I cupped 4 and selected the best 2, the second day I took the other 4 and selected the best 2 and on the final day I took the &quot;winners&quot; and played them off against each other to find which one I enjoyed most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many different types of scoring one can use, I prefer a simple scoring system. I have 5 categories: Aroma (broken down into dry and wet), Acidity, Sweetness, Body and Aftertaste. Each gets a score out of 10, I sum them up and double it to get a score out of 100. I then allow myself an &quot;adjustment&quot; to that score should I feel it needs it, for example a coffee may not have a lot of body but overall I like the taste more than another so want to correct for that. This is only in exceptional circumstances however, typically the score will not be adjusted. My scoring does not match the SCA system in any way. Since I only cup coffees that are specialty grade that have already passed numerous tastings it's unlikely I'll find anything under an 80 on the SCA scale - my scoring gives we scope to go below this if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/010-Brown-Roach/score.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;My Scoring Card&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will just briefly summarise my findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Day-1&quot;&gt;Day 1&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#Day-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YEY&lt;/strong&gt; - Tis coffee presented with a fruity round smell. The acidity was delicate with a dried cranberry sort of vibe. The sweetness was very high and there wasn't too much body. The aftertaste was clean and fairly shortlived. &lt;strong&gt;73/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INQ&lt;/strong&gt; - A big punch in the face of a coffee. Strong caramels and nuts combined with dried and fragrant stone fruits on the nose. Fairly high in acidty and syrupy sweet. Not much mouthfeel but a big body. Aftertaste was neutral. &lt;strong&gt;80/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TYH&lt;/strong&gt; - Not much of anything at all, it's as if the coffee is a bit stale. These came vac-packed without roast dates so it might be an old sample. &lt;strong&gt;56/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TUU&lt;/strong&gt; - A medium sweet medium acidity coffee with a lower body. In the aftertaste I picked up a note I wasn't 100% happy with so given the strength of competition it got marked down harshly. &lt;strong&gt;60/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Day-2&quot;&gt;Day 2&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#Day-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OWR&lt;/strong&gt; - Cherry and red-fruit aromas with caramels and honey. The acidity was nice and balanced and easy to drink. The sweetness reminded me of rosehips with a hint of florals. Overall very good. &lt;strong&gt;73/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M2X&lt;/strong&gt; - Just not my sort of coffee, heavy, dense, thick. Very nutty and chocolate-y with a malty-biscuity sort of vibe. Nothing wrong with it, just not for me. &lt;strong&gt;60/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CXH&lt;/strong&gt; - Similar to OWR - it was difficult to seperate these two. Very sugary sweet with honey-like qualities. Overall OWR pipped it to the post thanks to the subtle floral note. &lt;strong&gt;72/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K2E&lt;/strong&gt; - Now this was a complicated coffee. Totally different to the others so hard to compare them fairly. So many florals! Also a peachy-blueberry sort of fruitiness. This one came alive when it cooled down. It is not particularly sweet or acidity so the score suffers a bit. &lt;strong&gt;74/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Playoffs&quot;&gt;The Playoffs&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#The-Playoffs&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now moving onto finding the best of the best. The finalists are: &lt;strong&gt;INQ&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;K2E&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;YEY&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;OWR&lt;/strong&gt; - ranked by their first round scores. As I'm not a professional cupper nor do this often enough I do not put much weight on my scores day to day - it's highly swayed by my mood or whatever else I have eaten/done that day! My findings on the final cupping day were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OWR&lt;/strong&gt; - The honey caramel notes on the nose are more prominent. I'm picking up an orange note this time more than a red-fruit vibe. Again the acidity was balanced and not overpowering at all. In terms of sweetness this was the sweetest on show for me, the honey caramels really shining through. Probably the thinnest body of all of them however. The aftertaste is punchy with orange and caramel but it dissipates very quickly and doesnt linger. Overall very easy to drink but a touch one-dimensional. &lt;strong&gt;72/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INQ&lt;/strong&gt; - Much as before this one is a power-house absolutely out-muscling the other coffees on show. If you're after a flavour-bomb this one is probably it! There are chocolates and caramels there but also a lot of dried and stone fruits and through it all still a floral note underlying it all. It has the biggest body of all on show. Despite its power the aftertaste is not too overbearing and does not linger too long. &lt;strong&gt;79/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K2E&lt;/strong&gt; - Again the most complex coffee here by quite a long way. Super interesting and at a certain temperature it just comes alive. Florals are the name of the day, it is like filling your mouth with lavendar and rose petals. This is combined with a peach-y sweetness and a creamy mouthfeel. The aftertaste is highly perfumed and lingers a long time. &lt;strong&gt;81/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YEY&lt;/strong&gt; - Red-fruits are prominent on the nose throughout combined with a caramel note. The acidity is crisp and reminds me of a green apple or a lime. The red-fruits come out in the sweetness in the form of cherry candy! As it cools a floral note presents itself. It is neither as sweet as OWR nor as floral complex as K2E. The aftertaste is sweet and long lasting. &lt;strong&gt;76/100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there we have it the winner is: &lt;strong&gt;K2E&lt;/strong&gt;.  Noting that this is just my pallette. There are a couple of other things I noticed before I look at what the coffees actually were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OWR and CXH are remarkably similar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would be very surprised if K2E is anything other than an Ethiopian (I would guess a Guji natural if pushed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don't have a clue what INQ is - it has many different qualities. Whatever it is it is done well!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OWR has to be a honey processed coffee from the Americas - I'm thinking Costa Rica&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think M2X has to either be a Brazilian or a particularly heavy Colombian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Reveal&quot;&gt;The Reveal&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#The-Reveal&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The coffees were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K2E&lt;/strong&gt; - Hambela Halaka (Ethiopia Natural)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INQ&lt;/strong&gt; - Bolivia Caranavi (Bolivia Washed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YEY&lt;/strong&gt; - Rwanda Ruvumbu 035 (Rwanda Washed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OWR&lt;/strong&gt; - Costa Rica Juanachute Canet (Costa Rica Honey)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CXH&lt;/strong&gt; - Costa Rica Los Urena (Costa Rica Honey)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TUU&lt;/strong&gt; - Los Pirineos Pacamara (El Salvador Natural)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M2X&lt;/strong&gt; - Brazil Santo Andre Mondo Novo (Brazil Natural)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TYH&lt;/strong&gt; - Ethiopia Rocko Mountain (Ethiopia Natural)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully most of my predictions turned out to be reasonable! I don't have to hand in my membership card to the coffee bloggers union. It is interesting that the Ethiopian Rocko Mountain was last - this is a coffee I have had many times before from various roasters and always enjoy. It just had no oomph in this test, it could be the preperation method, user error or slightly stale beans. But I do usually find Rocko is better suited to espresso. It is also interesting that I couldn't place the Bolivian coffee as stated above the production yields have fallen drastically in recent years and so I've not been able to drink as much as I would like so am less familiar than I used to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also interesting that the ordering of the coffees ended up pretty much matched my expectations - that is if you just listed these coffees and made me put them in preference order it would very closely match this list (minus the Rocko anomoly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Jazz&quot;&gt;The Jazz&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#The-Jazz&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;With all the coffee stuff taken care of let's move onto this weeks jazz. Usually I try and link the jazz to the particular coffee or theme I want to write about. This week I can't really do that so it is a completely free choice, which is tough. I ultimately decided on an absolute classic released in 1954: &quot;Clifford Brown &amp;amp; Max Roach&quot; - with which we can hardly go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/010-Brown-Roach/cliffordroach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Released on the Verve record label this was a highly anticipated record. Clifford Brown and Max Roach being titans of their field, there was hope that this would pave a new path for bebop in the 50s following on from the earlier Bird and Diz work of the 40s. The record did not disappoint and instantly got recognised as one of the most important jazz records to date. The line up on the record is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clifford Brown – trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harold Land – tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Morrow – bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Richie Powell – piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Max Roach – drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Brown and Roach are the &quot;stars&quot; here but what really stands out to me is the call and response interplay between Brown and Land. It is one of the greatest examples of this interplay ever put onto a record. They work together seemlessly creating highly intricate shared ideas that never feels like &quot;8 bars for you, then 8 for me&quot;. This is displayed clearly on the 2nd track &quot;Parisian Throughfare&quot; (embedded at the start of this post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the power and restless energy of Roach keeps the whole thing moving along. This is not easy to do, it is all to easy to lose sight of the swing and just start throwing chops at a tune. Max, and the other top tier drummers, actually listen to the music and only let loose when the music calls for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The understated work of Morrow should also not be understated, with everything going on in the music there is always a need to keep things grounded. The musician filling that role rarely gets the recognition they deserve so this is a shout out to George Morrow in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting part of this album is the juxtaposition of the harder bebop-focussed tunes paired with simple sweet lyrical ballads. It makes for an album that keeps you on your toes from start to finish. A great example of this is a beautiful take on the standard &quot;These Foolish Things&quot; 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/oOJK1S3zUK4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Here Richie Powell (who did not quite reach the level of stardom of his brother Bud) absolutely shines through with understated lyricism and beauty, he and George Morrow fitting together perfectly. Max Roach leaving his ego at the door picks up the brushes and plays, perhaps, his simplest drum lines to date but it is just what the tune called for. Clifford Brown actually sits out the entire tune - on a tune that appears under your own name this requires a great deal of self control and keeping your ego in check!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any talk of Clifford Brown is not complete without talking about his tone. His sound is completely recognisable, it is big round and warm. Unlike others at the time who were typically searching for a colder harsher sound. This inspired a generation of players including Lee Morgan, Donald Byrd and Freddie Hubbard through to later artists such as Roy Hargrove. To make the most of this sound he played longer flowing lines as opposed to the shorter stocatto trumpet lines that came before him. It is a shame he died so young (in a car crash) - we only have 4 years worth of his recording. Despite this he was and still is a huge inspiration, he achieved in 4 years what many musicians fail to achieve in a lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In jazz there are a few albums that are so great they are essentially &quot;no-brainers&quot; for me this is certainly one of them.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kneLw04C4qI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/010-Brown-Roach/cliffordroach.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/010-Brown-Roach/cliffordroach.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Injuries and Long and Short Prince</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/injuries-prince" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Injuries and Long and Short Prince" /><published>2020-06-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Injuries-Prince</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/injuries-prince">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-06-13-Injuries-Prince.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MSd4PIzU9-k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

In this blog we are looking at the last of my (current) order from the Long and Short roastery ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://longandshort.london/&quot;&gt;https://longandshort.london/&lt;/a&gt; ) of the last few blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we are travelling to Burundi and the Tangara region. Burundi is a small east African country sharing borders with Rwanda to the north, Tanzania to the west/south and the Democratic Republic of Congo to the west. Given its shape it is sometimes called the heart of Africa. In recent years I have find Burundi to be one of the main challengers for &quot;most improved&quot; - every year that passes the cup quality seems to improve. Despite its small geographic size I also find great variety in the coffee from the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The particular coffee in question is called &quot;Prince&quot; - after Prince Bigayimpunzi who was a significant individual to the history of coffee farming in the Tangara region. As last week the varietal is a Bourbon, in particular red Bourbon. According to googlemaps this coffee was grown around 200km away from last weeks Rwandan &quot;Bingo&quot; - given they're both Bourbon varietals and naturally processed we would assume that the coffees would be remarkably similar: this is not the case. The Rwandan was polite, refined and not at all funky. In contrast the Burundi Prince is a wild child!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I like to start with any coffee: on the nose we are punched in the face with berry fruitiness! It is really quite striking and is certainly intense. There are some supporting notes there too, a chocolate-y sort of smell and it gives the impression of &quot;sweetness&quot; but first impressions are this will be an acidity bomb! There is not a huge amount of &quot;funk&quot; on the nose, in fact it's difficult to really tell it's a natural. Based on smell alone I might guess it is a washed Kenyan, it gives off that sort of acidic fruit-bomb vibe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on, as always, to the filter: again I rely on my trusty Hasami Brewer. I've not written much about brewed coffee yet in this blog so I will take a brief de-tour to talk about my set up and how I approach filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At heart I will always be a &quot;filter-boy&quot; - it is what first attracted me to coffee and is my most common form of coffee. I particularly love it for judging coffees as the coffees really speak for themselves when presented this way. I have tried (and still use) many different types of brewer, drip, pour-over, infusion, you name it! But for many years for me Chemex was king. One thing I always look for in a coffee is cleanliness, that is the quality I hunt down most - it is why I favour (much) lighter roasts than many. The Chemex with the very thick filter papers accentuates this quality in a coffee so it has always been a favourite of mine. If the pour-over world is split into Chemex and v60 fans I am firmly in the former camp! I also think as an item the chemex is a beautiful item to behold and an iconic design - I am a firm believer that we first taste with our eyes. Having a beautiful brewer/decanter and mug will improve how you perceive your coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/009-Injuries/chemex.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;A Chemex brewer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However I have a bit of a love-hate relationship with the performance of Chemex brewers. I find them quite finnicky and have a few issues. Most notably is that the &quot;funnel&quot; walls are smooth, this can cause the filter paper to &quot;stick&quot; to the sides and create a vacuum preventing the water from passing through the coffee. The pouring lip is meant to prevent this however it doesn't always work. It is certainly not an issue that affects every Chemex brew but it happens enough to make you angry when it does. Another issue I have with the Chemex is the glass walls mean heat escapes quickly, I believe the trick to good filter coffee is keeping things as warm as possible but the Chemex makes this a losing battle. Perhaps worst of all however is that the funnel and carafe are joined together and the neck is narrow, trying to clean a Chemex gets frustrating fast and they quickly look tatty. Not to mention how fragile they are, if you drop one it's likely it's gone for good!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My solution for a while was to instead use the v60 brewer and carafe but use the thicker Chemex papers. This is a fair compromise, the v60 has swirling &quot;ridges&quot; that reduce the chance of the paper sticking to the walls. You can pick up a plastic v60 cone for very little money so it is cost effective and long lasting. However unless you spend considerably more I don't find the v60 particularly visually appealing. About a year ago I came across the Hasami brewer, having bought some of their saucers to use for my espresso cups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/009-Injuries/Hasami.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;A Hasami brewer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has a definite &quot;style&quot; but I am a big fan of the way it looks and feels. Like the v60 it has &quot;ridges&quot; (but straight instead of swirling) but they are deeper so if anything more effective. The brewer itself is &quot;insulating&quot; in the sense that it is made of hollow ceramic/porcelain which helps heat retention. It also comes with a &quot;lid&quot; that I like to place on between pours to further prevent heat loss (I've not tested the efficacy of this but it makes me feel better!) It is also an easy clean which is a big plus. The Chemex papers provide a good fit. Overall I'm very happy with it (although I do appreciate it is a very expensive brewer not offering much in the way of tangible benefit to a v60!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My filter technique is generally quite simple and I do not change it very often. With filter I feel that if you're trying to &quot;dial in&quot; every coffee you're doing something wrong - you should look for a consistent technique that you can easily repeat. My technique involves (typically) getting the water very hot, I tend to set my kettle to 100c (although for certain coffees I might knock that back a few degrees depending). My grind setting is constant for all coffees, I do not vary it to target a specific drawdown time. I follow a &quot;pulse pour&quot; approach. I like to pour a small amount of water every 15-20s in order to keep the water level low in the brewer - I find this helps keep the extraction levels higher and helps with consistency. Unlike most others I do not favour agitation of the brew; the extraction yield isn't quite as high but for me the quality improves. The no-agitation approach increases clarity and cleanliness which is generally my main aim. For a typical cup I will use 14-15g coffee and 200g water - this ratio is a little higher than some suggest but it is where I like it, I feel the little extra coffee makes up for the lack of agitation in terms of total extraction but you end up with a cleaner cup out of it. I might pour 40g, leave for 30s then pour 20g of water every 15s as a typical recipe. Between pours I put the kettle back on to heat up if it needs it and I will place the Hasami lid on to reduce the amount of heat loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back onto the coffee in question after this detour into the world of brewing: as a filter this coffee is fairly wild! The acidity is very prominent from the get go. Blackberries and redcurrants come through strong but this is balanced by a chocolate note and a sweet butterscotch taste and mouthfeel. It is an interesting cup for sure, very complex. Of the long and shorts this is my choice as a filter, it is just more &quot;my style&quot;. As is often the case with Burundi's there is a floral note I can't quite put my finger on also, I have a hard time describing it and it's not particularly loud but it is there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso: again this is a wild child! The long and short roast profile again is more developed than my &quot;typical&quot; coffees which makes it very easy to pull shots from. If you wanted a &quot;gateway drug&quot; to the wilder more acidic espressos I don't think this one would be a bad starting point as it is so forgiving. Again the acidic blackberry-redcurrant notes are in the forefront and are by far most dominant. The acidity offers almost a &quot;drying&quot; experience in the mouth (but not in a bad way). There is enough sweetness to balance things out but it is not something I can really pinpoint down as a &quot;sugar&quot; or &quot;caramel&quot; or &quot;chocolate&quot; its just there to balance things. In terms of mouthfeel and body there is not much to talk about it is fairly &quot;thin&quot; - some may not like that but I've never really placed much value on body. It is certainly a clean cup and thoroughly enjoyable. Again there is that floral note lingering in the aftertaste that I wish I could put a finger on, maybe I'll have to try some more floral tasting foods to try and really dig down into what this &quot;Burundi note&quot; is!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as this weeks coffee is a wild-child we also look at a wild album as this weeks jazz pairing: Angles 9 - Injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/009-Injuries/Injuries.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Angles 9 - Injuries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit I do not know a huge amount about the various &quot;Angles&quot; bands (led by saxaphonist Martin Küchen), there are many incarcerations in many &quot;sizes&quot; - this album being a nonet - or nine piece. This places it firmly in the &quot;big band&quot; camp, something I feel is being under-represented currently. This particular album was released in 2014 and was my first exposure to this band. The full personel are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alexander Zethson - piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andreas Werliin - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eirik Hegdal - baritone sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goran Kajfes - cornet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Johan Berthling - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Magnus Broo - trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martin Küchen - alto and tenor sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mats Aleklint - trombone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mattias Ståhl - vibraphone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music itself is more at the &quot;free&quot; end of jazz (which in itself is odd for a big-band) - but there is still great focus on creating a groove, this is &quot;free jazz&quot; for those that enjoy getting up on their feet and dancing. Some of the playing is wild and ferocious, intellectually stimulating and challenging. Yet they manage to keep thrings under control by not losing sight of the groove and relying on the occassional minimalist section to allow the music to breathe. This is a great example of why &quot;free jazz&quot; can still rely on great composition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angles 9 have a sound completely of their own, you can identify them within a playlist almost instantly. To me this is the sign of a great artist. Their sound is neither too modern nor too dated, it is just right in that sweetspot where you have some familiarity but it is not &quot;boring&quot;. You can tell every musician in the group plays with swagger and has complete confidence in each others abilities, if the musicians were even slightly on edge the whole thing would fall apart into one big mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening track (embedded above) &quot;European Boogie&quot; is an absolute fire-cracker that sets the stage for the rest of the album. It is bombastic, swinging and with just the right amount of ego. It also shows that this project is not just content on making music, they're also trying to make a statement as many of the earlier free-jazz adopters were. However unlike the negative outlook many jazz artists take (and rightly so) - this album presents celebration, peace and hope at the forefront. They manage to combine many cultures into the music seemlessly, from the African and Latin inspired percussive beats through European classically inspired melodies. It is &quot;fusion&quot; in the true sense of the word.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SD5aj4yOwig&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The track &quot;Eti&quot; is another particular highlight of the album for me, it really captures the celebrative euphoria and just straight having fun. This is punctuated by the more minimalist freer sections, as if to show that &quot;low periods&quot; help accentuate the joy when it is there. What is also remarkable about this track is also the strength of the main theme, the melody itself reminds me of Russian classical pieces in particular. There are not many &quot;free&quot; albums where you will be humming the melody for days after you hear it. There are even fewer free-jazz albums that you feel like dancing too (admittedly a strange sort of dancing!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album is released on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cleanfeed-records.com/&quot;&gt;Clean Feed&lt;/a&gt; record label out of Lisbon, Portugal. In recent years I have found this to be a highly dependable label. I like labels to have their own &quot;sound&quot; or &quot;style&quot;, this is something that the early labels had in spades. You can pick up any Blue Note recording from the '50s-60s and you know what to expect. Cleanfeed does not hark back to the &quot;good old days&quot; trotting out tried and tested music, they're very ambitious. The music tends to be very free and experimental but never for the sake of it. It also helps that their recording quality is always top notch too, again they're progressive and modern - they aim for a very &quot;clean&quot; hi-fi quality to recording, not putting any &quot;faux-patina&quot; on during the recording to conjur up nostalgia. Yet the records remain open and warm, never cold nor clinical. Something that's very hard to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all &quot;Injuries&quot; can only be described, in this author's opinion, as a modern masterpiece. I don't like to make claims of &quot;album of the decade&quot; or similarly grandiose terms but for jazz released in the 2010s this has to be up there in any &quot;best of&quot; list. It is mindboggling to me this album did not get wide recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will leave with the track from the album: &quot;Ubabba&quot;. It is the least &quot;free&quot; of all the tracks but shows this band can still swing as hard as anybody else out there! Albeit in their very unique styling. After listening to free-jazz it's often nice to end on something more straight as a pallette cleanser:

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iBAe6u9MhWM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

And there we have it: a wild coffee in Prince from Long and Short and some wild jazz from the boys in Angles 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/009-Injuries/Injuries.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/009-Injuries/Injuries.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fat Albert Rotunda and Long and Short Bingo</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/fat-albert-rotunda-bingo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fat Albert Rotunda and Long and Short Bingo" /><published>2020-06-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Fat-Albert-Rotunda-Bingo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/fat-albert-rotunda-bingo">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-06-06-Fat-Albert-Rotunda-Bingo.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RokybiFVa1I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

In this blog we are sticking with the Long and Short roastery ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://longandshort.london/&quot;&gt;https://longandshort.london/&lt;/a&gt; ) from last time. Again we have another natural processed coffee, this time a Bourbon varietal from Rwanda called &quot;Bingo&quot; (with cupping score 87).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically Rwanda is known for their washed coffees, so it is a little unusual to find a natural coffee from there - not exceedingly so, but enough to be note worthy. The bourbon varietal is certainly ubiquitous throughout Rwanda however. Coffee varietals are important in the same way grape types are important to wine. From a preservation standpoint varietals are also important for genetic diversity, currently coffee plants are not particularly diverse and so highly susceptible to pests and disease. The creation of new varietals might help coffee survive long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethiopia is widely regarded as the birthplace of coffee and it is has the highest diversity of varietals (~95% of all varietals can be found in Ethiopia by some estimates). Outside of Ethiopia most coffee varietals can trace back to Yemen where there existed 2 main varietals: Typica and Bourbon (which is itself a mutation of Typica). Essentially every coffee outside of Ethiopia can trace its lineage back to Typica or Bourbon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bourbon takes its name from the island of Bourbon (now Réunion) where it was originally grown before being exported by the French to Latin America and Africa. Compared to Typica the Bourbon varietal has a higher yield (although still low yield compared to many other varietals.) Both are renowned for producing good quality coffee, unfortunately both types are highly susceptible to pests and disease which makes them hard to grow. Bourbon is in some sense &quot;the specialty coffee varietal&quot; given its prevelance and enduring popularity. To continue the wine analogy: &quot;Bourbon is the pinot-noir of the coffee world!&quot; The varietal can be further broken down into &quot;red bourbon&quot; (the original bourbon), &quot;yellow bourbon&quot; (a natural mutation of the red bourbon) and more recently &quot;orange/pink bourbon&quot; (another natural mutation). The colour names refer to the appearance of the coffee fruit prior to processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto Bingo itself: on the nose the beans give off a strong, rich caramel/burnt sugar sort of vibe - certainly enticing! As with the previous Long and Short coffee the roast level is what I would describe as a true medium-light: not a really light delicate filter roast but also not a medium where you start to see &quot;roasty&quot; notes that mask the natural acidity and sweetness in the coffee. As a filter this coffee shows a reasonable amount of complexity, there's certainly a tea note present which is strong upfront but also lingers as an aftertaste. The caramel note on the nose is also there but plays more of a supporting role. The real intrigue in the coffee is the blend of the sweetness and acidity - on the bag they describe it as &quot;bittersweet&quot; which is a very good description. As an espresso we are treated with a decent amount of mouthfeel and body. With this one I found pulling a little shorter helped stop the tastes getting lost. The flavour profile in the espresso is much like the filter although the caramel note is amplified somewhat and the tea note dialed back (especially in the aftertaste). All in all an enjoyable cup!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing we normally associate with natural coffees is &quot;funk&quot;, this coffee is not particularly funky. But this week's album is:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/008-Fat-Albert-Rotunda/fat-albert-rotunda.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Herbie Hancock - Fat Albert Rotunda&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally appearing as the soundtrack to Bill Cosby's animated special &quot;Hey, Hey, Hey, It's Fat Albert&quot;.  and released in 1969 &quot;Fat Albert Rotunda&quot; was Herbie Hancock's first dalliance with jazz-funk, a sound he would come back to with &quot;Head Hunters&quot; in 1973. Upto this point Herbie was known for his sophisticated harmony in more &quot;classic&quot; jazz settings and for his &quot;fusion&quot; work with Miles. &quot;Fat Albert Rotunda&quot; was instead heavily influenced by funk and soul music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album features quite a large ensemble cast of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herbie Hancock: Piano, Eletric Piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Henderson: Tenor Sax, Alto-flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Garnett Brown: trombone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Johnny Coles: trumpet, flugelhorn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buster Williams: electric, acoustic bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Albert &quot;Tootie&quot; Heath: drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Devens: percussion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With additional appearances on some tunes. Having such a large core-band really adds to the funk/soul vibe and affords Herbie more freedom in arrangement. Again blog-favourite Joe Henderson appears to provide some fire-breathing solos, the funky backdrop allows him to show off some funky chops and get a little freer. This is Joe's 3rd appearance in 8 blog posts - no other blog offers as much Joe Henderson per square inch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album starts with &quot;Wiggle Waggle&quot; (embedded above), which is an all time classic. It's a tune I feel many people will recognise but may not attribute to Herbie, like a few other tunes in his repertoire. It is based around a simple 12 bar blues guitar riff with the horns providing embellishments. The music really grooves with an r&amp;amp;b/soul vibe and Joe's solo is a wild start to an album. If you can listen to this track without, at least, tapping your feet you should probably go to your doctor and get them to check if you're missing the funk gene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually find jazz artists tend to express themselves in one of three ways: some are melody driven, some are harmony driven and some are rhythmically driven. Herbie is part of a rare breed that is adept at all three and this album displays this. After listening you'll find yourself humming the melody of some of the pieces and while it's playing you'll get intoxicated with the groove. To break up the funk however there are a few harmonically rich jazz pieces. My choice cut being &quot;Jessica&quot; on side 2:

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NKGLsLd4jIY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Which showcases Herbie's skill for harmonic composition and arrangement, a piece he revisited on 1977s &quot;V.S.O.P&quot; album. It is one of my favourite Hancock compositions, it is made all the more striking and beautiful on &quot;Fat Albert Rotunda&quot; where it is bookended by &quot;Oh! OH! Here He Comes&quot; and the title track - both of which are fat greasy funk grooves through and through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another track of note is the 2nd on the first side: &quot;Fat Mama&quot;. The distorted guitar groove with more than a passing resemblance to &quot;Cissy Strut&quot; by The Meters (which was released around the same time). Instead of being pure Meters funk there is more sophistication in &quot;Fat Mama&quot; (as to be expected with Hancock).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herbie is still out touring regularly and I have been fortunate enough to see him a few times live (I remember a duet gig with Chick Corea being particularly good!) Since he is such an &quot;all-star&quot; in the jazz world I've only seen him in larger concert halls, I'd love to get a chance to see him in a more intimate &quot;jazz club&quot; setting, although a gig like that would sell out almost instantly so I may need to take out a mortgage to fund tickets from a tout if that ever happens here in London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather in London today is overcast and grey, strong winds and intermittent rain showers. On days like this you need comforting coffee and uplifting music: Bingo and &quot;Fat Albert Rotunda&quot; it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/008-Fat-Albert-Rotunda/fat-albert-rotunda.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/008-Fat-Albert-Rotunda/fat-albert-rotunda.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Natural Soul and Long and Short Dambi Udo</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/natural-soul-dambi-udo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Natural Soul and Long and Short Dambi Udo" /><published>2020-05-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Natural-Soul-Dambi-Udo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/natural-soul-dambi-udo">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-05-30-Natural-Soul-Dambi-Udo.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OtBEP48y0H4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

In this blog post we're going &quot;natural&quot;. At the moment I'm finding most of the interesting coffees out there, at least the ones catching my eye, are naturals so it seems only fitting to embrace that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To those that may be new to the coffee world by &quot;natural&quot; we are referring to how the coffee is processed before being roasted. A coffee &quot;bean&quot; is in fact a seed inside a coffee cherry fruit. The job of processing is to remove this fruit so that the beans are dried and ready to roast (and ultimately end up in tasty and delicious drinks). One option is &quot;washed&quot; processing where, as the name suggests, the coffee cherry is removed with water. Of all the processing methods this produces the &quot;cleanest&quot; cup since (essentially) all the cherry is removed. A &quot;natural&quot; processing method however involves leaving the bean inside the coffee cherry longer, typically in the sun. The natural sugars in the fruit ferment during this time. Eventually the fruit is seperated from the seed, producers have some control over how long the drying stage takes which can impact the qualities in the cup. Typically natural coffees are more complex, have bolder and wilder flavour profiles typically at the expense of being &quot;clean&quot;. In some cases where the fermentation stage is particularly long the coffee can take on &quot;funky&quot; characteristics, I tend to associate these with &quot;bruised fruit&quot; or &quot;fortified alcohol&quot; flavour notes. In the extreme they can taste slightly &quot;rotten&quot; which is a bit of a marmite thing, I've not found many really funky naturals for a few years though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question this week comes from the Long and Short ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://longandshort.london/&quot;&gt;https://longandshort.london/&lt;/a&gt; ) team in Walthamstow East London. I've never purchased from these guys before but what caught my eye was an understated aesthetic and some rather high-quality coffees for reasonable prices. Coffee quality is often assessed using an SCA cupping score ranging from 0-100, to be called specialty the coffee needs a score of at least 80. The cupping score is not perfect but I find is a reasonable benchmark if looking at a new roaster. Typically I'll look for a score of around 87 or higher, this seems a good yardstick for me - going into the 90s typically means spending much much more dropping down to near 80 does not reduce the cost too much, it is a bit of a sweetspot in the diminishing return curve. To sweeten the deal Long and Short offer 20% off a first order if you sign up to their newsletter. Their regular prices are fair but 20% off is unbelievable - I don't think you'll get much more bang for your buck, they must be selling at cost with the discount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/007-Natural-Soul/Longandshort.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Credit: https://www.instagram.com/longandshortcoffee/&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee I selected was called Dambi Udo, it is an Ethiopian from the Guji region and has an SCA score of 89. It is worth noting however that a single score like this cannot tell you anything about the flavour profile or even if you'll enjoy a coffee. If you hate really bright acidic cup profiles regardless of the SCA score a washed Kenyan might not be the one for you! Ethiopian naturals are really a &quot;tale of 2 halves&quot; in my experience - on the one side you get some really elegant fairly clean cups and on the other you can end up with complete madness (one of my most memorable cups of coffee ever was a particularly funky Yirgacheffe natural, it was right on the edge of being too &quot;rotten&quot; tasting but was a really smash in the face of flavours). The Dambi Udo is definitely on the more polite and elegant end of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in the interests of honesty this coffee is roasted slightly darker than my typical coffees. It is by no means dark, a medium-light is more of a fair description but I tend to go light to very light in my preferences. However by developing a bit further the acidity can be managed slightly. The result here is a very easy to drink cup that is very balanced, I'm not feeling as though I'm sacrificing anything by going a touch darker than usual. This also makes pulling espresso shots so much easier, I find this coffee incredibly forgiving - it's basically impossible to pull a bad shot if you get at least within the ballpark of a reasonable &quot;recipe&quot;. I find this one likes to be ground a bit coarser than others (like many natural Ethiopians in my experience) and only a medium sort of heat. I have had good results from pulling very short (1.85:1) to fairly long (2.5:1) - living up to the Long and Short name!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto the cup itself. After grinding the beans have a caramel and jammy sort of vibe on the nose for me along with some very delicate floral notes, very enticing. On the eyes the beans are quite clearly natural (I find there is a certain &quot;look&quot; to natural coffees) but on the nose there isn't a typical natural funk. In the filter we find the natural processing imparting body and mouthfeel which is really satisfying. The flavour profile is fruity though and through, there are tropical fruits like mangos and watermelons but also a blueberry type note. The caramel on the nose goes more to a sugar-syrup or jam in the cup, there isn't a hint of a &quot;roasty&quot; note. In the espresso I find this coffee amps up the jam even more both in texture and flavour. The floral notes also come out to play, if I had to describe the type I'd suggest elderflower is an apt descriptor. The acidity is not too high at all in my opinion, I could see this being a good gateway for those that find African espresso too acidic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're looking for a satisfying cup that is complex yet not too challenging I'd certainly recommend the Dambi Udo. Especially for the discounted price it is truly exceptional. I also want to make a couple of shout-outs about Long and Short:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They win the record for the quickest turnaround of an order I can remember. From placing the order I got the tracking information for delivery within 17mins. Very very good!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is nice to see packaging that is recyclable, many coffee bags are a pain to recycle but these bags can go into regular recycling (with the 2-way valve removed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album in this blog is one slightly (but not massively) under the radar the 1962: &quot;The Natural Soul&quot; by Lou Donaldson.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/007-Natural-Soul/The_Natural_Soul.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cover art is fairly typical in style with the black/white picture being brought to life with a flash of colour and the impactful block lettering. Lou Donaldson albums are somewhat synonomous with featuring beautiful women on the covers, but I believe this is the first one (jazz historians feel free to correct this!) &quot;The Natural Soul&quot; would have been all the more striking at the time for featuring an African-American woman with a &quot;natural&quot; afro hairstyle, kudos to Blue Note records for being willing to create cover art like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music on this album represents one of the first &quot;Soul-Jazz&quot; records that came in the post-bop era for which Lou Donaldson was a major artist. Soul-Jazz focussed less on intense musicianship and blistering lead lines and more on groove taking inspiration from soul and r'n'b. The tunes were mostly variations on a blues or simply a one-chord vamp and the solos were all about blues-y lyricism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The line-up on this album is simply incredible, Lou on alto, Tommy Turretine on trumpet, Grant Green on guitar, Big John Patton on organ and Ben Dixon on the drums. The Green/Patton/Dixon trio at the time being one of the pre-eminent organ trios around with a reputation for being one of the funkiest/grooviest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music presented is firmly in the Soul-Jazz tradition but with more than a foot remaining rooted in the blues. The opening track &quot;Funky Mama&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) is a perfect example with a hard hitting Soul-Jazz groove based around a 12 bar-blues. Most of the compositions take the form of a turnaround - for any musicians wanting to navigate a turnaround this album (along with many in the Donaldson catalogue) is a great place to start. Lou uses simple pentatonic blues phrases to great effect throughout, Green uses his minimalist style to keep the groove going and Big John Patton acts as the rock keeping things moving. To simply label the playing as &quot;simple blues&quot; is a mistake however, there is still plenty of bop virtuosity on display for example in the opening of side 2 &quot;Sow Belly Blues&quot; where the soloists let loose a bit more.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VO5SKRN0-hI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Lou Donaldson (nickname &quot;Sweet Papa&quot;) was also known for his humour and this is certainly on display throughout the album with upbeat progressions and jokey expressions (although the music is anything but a joke). I was fortunate enough to see him live a few years ago, at the time he was nearing 90 years old but still put in a hell of a show. He may have needed to sit down, rest and take trips back stage while others were soloing but it was still a memorable gig. His humour was on display that night and he said 2 things that I will always remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;This next tune is a Miles Davis number... You know, back when he actually played jazz.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A long talk about how in his old age his &quot;performance&quot; was suffering and his experiments with viagra (some of which cannot be printed in a family oriented blog like this!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great character, great performer and all around nice guy. He no longer performs live (at 93 years old at time of writing) so I feel fortunate to have got a chance to see him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you're in search of something fairly easy to listen to that doesn't compromise on musicianship while providing fat grooves: &quot;The Natural Soul&quot; is not a bad way to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/007-Natural-Soul/The_Natural_Soul.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/007-Natural-Soul/The_Natural_Soul.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Graffiti and PLOT Panchita Irureta</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/graffiti-panchita-irureta" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Graffiti and PLOT Panchita Irureta" /><published>2020-05-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Graffiti-Panchita-Irureta</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/graffiti-panchita-irureta">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-05-23-Graffiti-Panchita-Irureta.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yFtY19HRPks&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This weeks jazz album is the 2015 offering from JD Allen: Graffiti. I wanted to feature a more modern offering this time. In jazz it is all too easy to get caught up in history and yearn for the &quot;good old days&quot;, as such many modern artists seem to get overlooked. JD Allen is one such example, in my opinion one of the greatest modern players who deserves much more recognition for the work he is putting out. (This is exemplified by his allmusic.com entry which is woefully sparse and is missing all of his releases post 2013!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/006-Graffiti/Graffiti.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing jazz being performed live is one of lifes great experiences, it is great listening to the old Blue Note records but nothing compares to the thrill of a great gig. I have seen JD a few times when he has performed in London, everytime a fantastic performance. Some artists rely on stage patter to lift performances, JD (and his group) does not instead letting the music speak for itself. This almost forces you to really pay attention to the music itself and the whole room feels &quot;part of something&quot;. If he is performing in your neighbourhood I'd wholly recommend getting a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album itself (Graffiti) is one of my favourites from him. It features Rudy Royston on drums and Greg August on bass, this rhythm section featuring on many Allen recordings upto 2019s &quot;Barracoon&quot; where he brought in some fresh blood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music on Graffiti walks that fine line between &quot;in&quot; and &quot;out&quot;, sometimes straying to an almost &quot;free&quot; structure but then pulling you back into something more comfortable. However there is a strong backbone of blues to everything to keep you grounded. There is almost a sensation of movement to the music, you can feel yourself being pushed and pulled by some external force as the music weaves between the swinging and the chaotic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many modern band leaders like to express themselves through dense harmonic structures, the music can feel somewhat rigid as a result as this closes off many avenues for improvisation since any solo has to essentially be a regimented tap dance to avoid falling down. This can be fun, but Graffiti instead keeps a looser feeling. Instead of relying on harmony for expression JDs music relies on rhythm to make a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite cuts on the album is the 2nd track: &quot;Jawn Henry&quot;. Allen's playing with the use of wolf tones in the main melody and the overall vibe reminds me of Joe Henderson (who is one of my all time favourite players). It has its own thing going however, there is the very evident JD DNA through the whole piece. Rudy's quite chaotic drumming helps fill the space in the composition and shows off some monster chops. Despite the technicality however Rudy manages to maintain a solid groove and swing which is no mean feat. With so much going on with the sax and drums you need a bedrock to keep things under control and this is where August comes in. You can tell this band is totally comfortable with each other, with music like this it can quickly turn into disaster if the band isn't tight. The track is a good illustration of the &quot;out but in&quot; vibe that JDs music is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the tracks on the album are solid, it is very consistent start to finish. It does not feel like any track is there as filler to turn an EP into an LP. The closing track &quot;Disambiguation&quot; reprises the main theme from &quot;Jawn Henry&quot; and acts to tie the whole album together and acts as a resolution leaving the listener satisfied. Some other tracks I particularly enjoy on the album are &quot;Sonny Boy&quot; which has some real swagger to it (and based on the name I assume is a tribute to Sonny Rollins who is clearly an influence). Another piece that sticks out is &quot;Indigo (Blue Like)&quot;, in the liner notes JD says: &quot;the most avant-garde thing that a jazz musician could do today is try to straight up and down swing&quot; and he is totally right. This tune swings hard but with some Monk inflections and humour thrown in along the way, you can tell they had great fun recording this.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_PyYkauCxVk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

If you're looking for some &quot;no-nonsense&quot; hard hitting modern jazz that respects the past but isn't a prisoner to it; check out &quot;Graffiti&quot; through whichever medium you use to purchase your music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee this week is the last of my current batch from PLOT a Peruvian: &quot;Panchita Irureta Atipanaku Competition Lot&quot;. It is a fully washed Caturra coffee. Peru is not an origin I naturally gravitate towards, but for any real reason. Maybe it's just their seasonality coinciding with other origins that I favour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter you are greeted with a fairly rich and very sweet cup. Notes coming through cherry and a dark forest gateaux sort of vibe. There is also a reasonable amount of mouthfeel, texture and body to the cup. Both the flavour profile and the mouthfeel don't scream &quot;washed&quot; you would more naturally associate these things with some sort of natural processing, which is kind of interesting. On the acidity scale I would classify it as a medium, leaning more to sweetness than acidity on a sweet-acid scale. It's certainly an intriguing cup but despite the complexities it is (very) easy to drink and quite satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit I have struggled to dial in a great espresso with this coffee. It's not that the coffee is &quot;unforgiving&quot; (like say a light roast washed Kenyan that ends up like battery acid if you're not careful) - it is fairly easy to get something nice to drink, but getting it to shine took a bit of work. I'm used to dialing in very light roasts (and this is a filter roast afterall and probably on the lighter end of filters even) - I eventually found something that works but it is a little counter-intuitive. Although this coffee is a light washed I found it better to think of it as a medium roast natural coffee (somewhat mimicking its flavour profile in the filter I guess).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My espresso machine is a Londinium-R lever machine. It is a fairly simple machine based around a spring-loaded lever group. It has the addition of a digital pre-infusion module that allows you to vary the pressure of the pre-infusion stage which is akin to changing the temperature on some other machines. This pre-infusion pressure is the only variable you really have with this machine. Personally I think this is great, I am not a fan of profiling machines in general as I feel you always end up with a sense of &quot;if only I varied XXXX a bit I could make this better&quot; - which leads to a lot of wasted coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/006-Graffiti/Londinium.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Londinium-R&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the bright filter roasts I use for espresso a general rule to follow for the best results is to get the machine very hot and pull a long shot (~2.5:1 typically) quickly (~22s). This does not work for this coffee however, following this procedure and you're left with something quite muted and flat. The major issue seems to be the heat, this coffee does not like heat at all! I dialed back to a temperature more suited to a medium roast espresso and things began to liven up. I than began to systematically fine the grind up a bit, reduce the volume of the shot and extend the time. I eventually settled on a &quot;typical&quot; espresso recipe of 2:1 in 27s. It's quite odd to pull a shot like this these days with the sorts of coffee I drink, usually the longest/slowest I'd go is 2.2:1 and 25s and even that is rare. The results of the espresso investigation led me to change my filter technique for this coffee too, I usually set my kettle hot and re-heat between pours. With this coffee I reduced the temperature by 5 degrees celcius and didn't re-heat, the coffee thanked me for it (but I doubt I'll be using these settings for my next bag of coffee!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once dialled in however the coffee really speaks as an espresso, it's bold and vibrant with the black forest gateaux hitting you in the face with full force. As in the filter it's (very) sweet but there isn't a mountain of acidity. I could imagine this coffee not being too off-putting for those used to a more developed espresso roast, however being roast less means the flavours are incredibly clean. The mouthfeel is quite syrupy with lots of body, again it's a complex but satisfying affair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall of the 3 PLOT coffees I tried this was (eventually) my favourite espresso of the 3, which is some achievement as they were all great in their own ways. You might need to work at it a bit but I think it's worth the hassle for the results in the cup! And it is especially to suited to being consumed while listening to JD Allen's Graffiti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/006-Graffiti/Graffiti.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/006-Graffiti/Graffiti.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Moanin and PLOT Abera Ararso</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/moanin-and-abera-ararso" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moanin and PLOT Abera Ararso" /><published>2020-05-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Moanin-and-Abera-Ararso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/moanin-and-abera-ararso">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-05-16-Moanin-and-Abera-Ararso.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cv9NSR-2DwM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Following on from the previous blog post; the second coffee from my PLOT order is the Abera Ararso. This is a fully washed Ethiopian coffee from the Yirgacheffe region. Washed Yirgacheffes have become one of the icons of third wave specialty coffee, they tend to have high cup quality and a certain &quot;style&quot;. Over the years we have almost become spoiled by how great they can be. At the moment it's trendy to have ever more complex fermentations, drying and yeast based processes to gain more &quot;complexity&quot; in the cup - but for me nothing compares to a Yirgacheffe washed coffee. They're like your favourite jacket that can be dressed up or down, the Yirgacheffe can satisfy your lust for complex flavours yet at the same time is equally suited to when you just want a cup that is easy to drink on a lazy Sunday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular example from PLOT is a very floral affair, not the &quot;loudest&quot; coffee you'll drink compared to say a natural process fruit bomb. However for a floral it still packs a hefty punch. As a filter there is also a fair amount of sweetness in the cup - it reminds me of candied lavender that you get in fancy cocktail bars. The cocktail comparison is probably fairly apt too as the cup oozes of sophistication and elegance. As with most washed Ethiopians there isn't a whole lot in the way of mouthfeel. As an espresso the florals pop even more especially on the nose - it is a very fragrant espresso. Washed Yirgacheffes are not always favoured for espresso since they can easily get lost in milk and can be a little too polite for some but personally I like them a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bag the taste notes are listed as: &quot;Peach, Parma Violets and Bergamot&quot;. I feel these are fairly apt descriptors, the fragrant bergamot notes are particularly prominent to me. I usually try and ignore specifics in flavour notes when choosing coffee to buy, I tend to just look for &quot;trends&quot; for example: is the coffee floral? Stone fruits? Tropical fruits? and so on rather than hunting down a very specific note. I often seen new coffee drinkers post online &quot;I can't taste the XXXXX note, what have I done wrong?&quot; which I think leads to disappointment. I think the SCA's attempt to standardize taste descriptors through the flavour wheel is helpful as I feel as though the industry has got a bit carried away in recent years. Can anybody really tell me they can taste the difference between a coffee with a &quot;strawberry&quot; note versus one with a &quot;wild strawberry&quot; note? I feel as though these grandiose descriptors just lead to disappointment and turns more people away than attracts them to specialty. (Note: this is no reflection on PLOT who seem to use reasonable descriptions, it is just a topic that has been on my mind recently).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/005-Moanin/flavor-wheel.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One positive trend I've seen with Ethiopian coffees in the past year or so is the movement away from the &quot;Heirloom&quot; varietal - for those readers who perhaps aren't as well versed in their terminology: a coffee varietal is roughly the equivalent to a grape variety in a wine. So while in wine you might have a chardonnay, pinot noir or malbec grape in a coffee you might have typica, red bourbon or caturra varietals. Ethiopia is widely considered the birthplace of coffee and occurs &quot;naturally&quot;, in other regions the coffee plants were introduced. By introducing specific strains and careful farming outside of Ethiopia it is fairly easy to identify the specific varietals on a particular farm. In Ethiopia the coffee plants are much much older, they have naturally evolved over time and so an individual farm may have many different varietals mixed together, some of which may never have even been classified. In the past the industry used the term &quot;Heirloom&quot; to denote an Ethiopian coffee with a &quot;mix&quot; of natural varietals. This is not ideal since different farms can be composed of entirely different varietals yet both be labelled the same. In the past year or so there has been a move to classify these varietals better. In the Abera Ararso from PLOT we have Kume, Diga and Wolisho varietals. Being relatively new names I haven't yet got a good handle on the characteristics of each - but hopefully in time I can gain a better understanding of these differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this weeks coffee is a classic, it feels only apt to pick one of the classic albums in Jazz history to pair with it. In this case I have settled on &lt;strong&gt;Moanin'&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Art Blakey and the Jazz Messengers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/005-Moanin/art_blakey_moanin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jazz Messengers have a long and complicated history, originally formed via a partnership between drummer Art Blakey and pianist Horace Silver who left after a couple of years to lead solo projects under his own name. Thereafter Blakey became the leader and director of the group (but also released some music under his own name). Under Blakey the Jazz Messengers had a reputation for attracting young talent and &quot;making them stars&quot;. The groups alumni include some of the greatest names in jazz and one would have to include Blakey in any list of &quot;greatest band leaders&quot;. The Blakey mantra to band leading was to find talented youngsters and then &quot;getting out of their way&quot; rather than using the &quot;apprentice&quot; model that other senior band leaders often favour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this record the &quot;big name&quot; is Lee Morgan who would have been 20 years old at the time of recording, already having some noteriety from appearing on Coltrane's &quot;Blue Train&quot; a year or so earlier. However it wasn't until a few years after the release of &quot;Moanin'&quot; that he became a household name. Although not quite having, in hindsight, the star power of Morgan the other musicians on the record are no slouches either: Benny Golson on tenor sax, Bobby Timmons on piano and Jymie Merritt on the bass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with most LPs on the Blue Note record label from the 50s and 60s Moanin' features an iconic cover with the classic Reid Miles block lettering and a rather sombre looking Blakey (who is usually much more upbeat) in a photo by Francis Wolff. The Blue Note DNA runs through to the music too; during this time recording and rehearsal was relatively expensive. As a result many records released on other labels featured track lists mainly consisting of standards that they could record quickly in few takes. In contrast Alfred Lion and Blue Note paid for rehearsal time for the artists which allowed them to be more creative and develop new music. The album here featuring only one standard: Johnny Mercer's &quot;Come Rain or Come Shine&quot; as the final track, and even that has been largely reworked. All other tracks being originals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music itself is gutsy, soulful and with a clear influence from blues and gospel music. The late 50s was an interesting time for jazz music in general, be-bop had started to become a little stale. Artists were trying to find a new voice. Shortly after this jazz began to fragment into new sub-genres (as is the case with any music that lasts long enough). Blakey grew up with big bands and later became associated with be-bop groups - through the Jazz Messengers he became one of the figureheads of the hard-bop movement combining some of the hard hitting swing of big band with some of the dense harmonic structures of be-bop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album starts off with the title-track penned by Timmons, the opening motif being one of the most powerful and recognisable in all of jazz. Everybody on the record is on top form and they were clearly up for it. From Blakey's muscular powerful swinging groove, Timmons offering blues-y block chords and Lee Morgan offering up some killer soulful solos offering a glimpse of what is to come in his later career. The whole record has swagger, swing and total confidence - this is important in jazz records, the musicians often take great risks harmonically and played without confidence it leaves the listener on edge. Part of the beauty of jazz is the feeling of being &quot;in safe hands&quot; while doing something completely reckless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other high points on this album, if we can even pick high-points given every cut on the album is a classic, is &quot;Along Came Betty&quot; on side 2 written by Golson. It is perhaps the most sophisticated track on the album with an almost Ellingon-esque horn arrangement. Blakey's energy lifts the soloists to new heights however, Golson in particular plays out of his skin on this one.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CTzRHq_cH5E&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

If you're looking for a reminder of why the classics are classics because, maybe, you have become a bit complacent you can't go far wrong with either Abera Ararso from PLOT nor &quot;Moanin'&quot; from Art Blakey and the Jazz Messengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/005-Moanin/art_blakey_moanin.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/005-Moanin/art_blakey_moanin.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Point Of Departure and PLOT Rodrigo Sanchez Valencia</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/point-of-departure-rodrigo-sanchez-valencia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Point Of Departure and PLOT Rodrigo Sanchez Valencia" /><published>2020-05-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Point-of-Departure-Rodrigo-Sanchez-Valencia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/point-of-departure-rodrigo-sanchez-valencia">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-05-09-Point-of-Departure-Rodrigo-Sanchez-Valencia.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main impetus behind this blog post is a new coffee I have been drinking recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question is from the folks at PLOT Roasting ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://plotroasting.com/&quot;&gt;https://plotroasting.com/&lt;/a&gt; ). I believe they are a relatively new roaster on the scene, starting around the mid-end of 2019 based in Woolwich east London. I'm usually quite suspicious of new roasters and usually like to try their offerings in cafes before purchasing a whole bag. The past few years quite a few sub-par roasters have appeared in London. What made me try PLOT then? For one their website suggested they know what they're doing and there appeared to be a coherent brand and aim - not a list of specialty cliches. The service was good with quick delivery and a hand written thank you note, which although doesn't change the drinking experience I appreciate when I see it. The packaging is very nice also, you build up your expectations prior to even viewing the beans so it's nice to see nice well thought out packaging (although packaging alone will not save a subpar coffee of course!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself I'm writing about today is from Huila, Colombia and is called: Rodrigo Sanchez Valencia. There are 2 main pieces of interest on the spec sheet: the first the varietal is (entirely) pink bourbon - a hybrid between red and yellow bourbons (there also exists another hybrid orange bourbon). This varietal is super-rare and hard to produce so you don't often see it and when you do it tends to be expensive. PLOT however price this, in my opinion, fairly reasonably - higher than average but not to crazy-Geisha levels. The second point of interest is the processing method: a washed cold fermented processing. Essentially the coffee is picked and pulped then stored to ferment at a low temperature for a few days and then treated as a fully washed coffee would be. This is the first coffee of this processing type I have tried to the best of my knowledge, my instinct tells me to expect the funky notes of a natural but without the &quot;body&quot; and &quot;dirt&quot; you get with a natural. I have to admit I am not a big fan of some of these fancy new processing techniques, while interesting and different I don't find many to be particularly enjoyable - I often find a certain &quot;hollowness&quot; or &quot;emptiness&quot; to these coffees that sort of reminds me a decaf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/004-Point-Of-Departure/banner.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Credit: PLOT Roasting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the cup we go, starting with the filter - using my goto rig of the OE Apex, Hasami brewer and chemex paper. The ground beans have a different texture between the fingers from the last few coffees I've had, a more jagged and &quot;dry&quot; feeling - I'm not sure if this is directly attributable to the processing, varietal or just coincidence. On the nose the beans give off a very wiry almost vinegar aroma - certainly &quot;different&quot; but not unpleasant. Brewing to my usual recipe the first thing I notice in the cup is a cider smell - like a cloudy &quot;craft&quot; cider as opposed to a mass produced cider. This carries through to the cup, there is a fair amount of acidity present. The sweetness is there but it's certainly on the acidic end of the scale. The boozy funkiness from the fermentation only amplifies the cider comparisons. The body and mouthfeel are very light and thin, it is certainly an odd experience since the funky notes tend to come with increased body. As an espresso I get much the same qualities, this is certainly not an espresso for those looking for a more traditional and developed espresso (note: I believe PLOT only suggests this for filter - but I like low development espressos). There are some light other fruity notes present with this coffee (the tasting notes suggest pineapple and melon - I'm not sure I really pick out those at least in the first few cups I've had so far).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a very interesting, somewhat challenging coffee. I'm certainly glad to have tried this one. I'm also glad that PLOT appears to be a very high-level establishment, I could easily see this coffee being destroyed by a less capable roaster. I'm sure I will be ordering from them again, it's nice to find another high quality roaster especially in London - I hope they achieve success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking of an album to pair with this coffee has been a bit of a struggle, I try and somehow link my album recommendation to the coffee somehow - through an idea/thought or through some indirect means. Given the coffee's qualities in the cup I feel a more avant-garde offering is appropriate - challenging but rewarding. I finally settled upon one of my favourite offerings in this style: Andrew Hill's Point Of Departure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/004-Point-Of-Departure/andrew-hill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album was recorded by Rudy Van Gelder, like many of the great Blue Note records. Released in 1965 it features a blockbuster line-up that would challenge any album you care to mention in terms of prestige: Andrew Hill (piano), Kenny Dorham (trumpet), Eric Dolphy (alto sax and flute), Joe Henderson (tenor sax), Richard Davis (bass) and Tony Williams (drums). This is ilustrated by Reid Miles' inimitable artwork where title, artist and supporting cast are given equal size fonts. While not the most creative or iconic Blue Note artwork it certainly still packs a punch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music on this cut is typical Andrew Hill - slightly chaotic, partly dense and partly sparse. The opening theme on &quot;Refuge&quot; is a twisting and turning affair that lets you are not in for a &quot;typical&quot; Blue Note hard-bop romp. As was the style for the earlier &quot;free&quot; recordings there is still a fair amount of structure to the composition rather than just a free-for-all -typically following a form of: a theme/phrase to open, an extended modal static section for soloing and then closing with a variation on the opening theme. The themes themselves, however, are looser and more angular than typcially found on bop records often having more dissonance, extended voicings and odd timings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the soloists, as expected, Hill and Dolphy are in their element. The latter in particular producing, in my opinion, some of his best soloing - wild and on the edge of completely losing control yet still having a sense of swing. Dorham in contrast is not somebody who you would expect to see on a date like this, he is best known for his understated deeply melodic and lyrical style. He still brings that quality here but the magic of Hill's compositions are that this still fits - by dialing back the crazy at some parts and turning it up at others it allows all the musicians to find their voice. This is something that is difficult to do, especially on dates where there are a lot of &quot;star names&quot; vying for the limelight. If you have read my first blog post you'll know I'm a big Joe Henderson fan, he is allowed to be looser and freerer here than he is on other records - but being surrounded by Hill and Dolphy he acts as a transition between the frenetic of these two and the soulful mastery of Dorham. As he always does showing his mastery as a side-man a fitting into any role you throw at him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the underrated star of this record that pulls the whole thing together is Tony Williams (credited as &quot;Anthony Williams&quot; as he was earlier in his career). During recording of this record he would have only been 19 years old (the other members being in their 30s-40s), which shows what a prodigious talent he was. Williams is probably best known for his later work in jazz-fusion settings where he devloped a very forceful driving drumming style which later influenced Billy Cobham and the likes. On Point Of Depature however he offers up a much more fluid loose style, while not a strong driving sound he controls the mood masterfully - the chemistry with Hill and Dolphy is fantastic having just recorded the equally seminal &quot;Out to Lunch&quot; under Dolphy's name only a month prior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My choice track is the opening to side 2 on the vinyl recording: &quot;Spectrum&quot;. The playing and composition are incredible and there is a certain Monk-esque humour to the theme. Coming up to 60 years old this recording sounds like it could have come from any time period. While not the easiest start into the world of jazz it certainly rewards those that make an effort.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cCWuT5MFzog&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

If you are looking for comforting or easy the coffee and jazz on offer today will not satisfy you. However if you want to open yourself up to something a bit challenging, new and possibly exciting you could do a lot worse than give either of these a try!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/004-Point-Of-Departure/andrew-hill.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/004-Point-Of-Departure/andrew-hill.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>