<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-02T08:32:07-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Intangible Between and Round Hill Rimiro Natural</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/captain-black-and-rimiro" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Intangible Between and Round Hill Rimiro Natural" /><published>2020-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/Captain-Black-and-Rimiro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/captain-black-and-rimiro">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-05-02-Captain-Black-and-Rimiro.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit of an experimental blog post today; yesterday (May 1st 2020) marked the release of the new record from Orrin Evans Captain Black Big Band on Smoke Sessions records: &quot;The Intangible Between&quot;. I'm going to blog my reaction to hearing this album for the first time. If you are looking for a more detailed review this is not going to be it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/003-Orrin-Evans/Orrin-Evans-The-Intangible-Between.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Captain Black Big Band project is quite interesting to me. Big bands have largely fallen out of favour, there aren't many bands out there making records. I assume it's a financially motivated thing: touring with 12 musicians is more expensive than with a trio - you can't charge four times as much on the door! It makes big band records such as this exciting. The first Captain Black album was released in 2011 and I believe they have 3 out previously before this one. I've always been a fan, they tend to be quite a rambunctious group heading towards the &quot;freer&quot; side than your traditional big band. The influence of the Mingus big bands is clearly evident. Around the mid 2010s Orrin Evans joined the Smoke Sessions record label who have put out some of the best jazz of recent years in my opinion. I was a little dis-heartened to see Orrin had joined The Bad Plus, who I'm indifferent towards, but glad to see he's still releasing music under his own name. As such I am excited to see what this album has in store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My liquid accompaniment for these preceedings is a naturally processed Burundi called Rimiro, another coffee from the fine folks at the Round-Hill roastery. I normally favour &quot;clean&quot; tastes so I sometimes struggle with naturals that are too funky. Thankfully there is no issue of funk here, it is on the elegant end of the spectrum. Flavour wise in the filter I get a big hit of red-wine, the natural processing leading to the familiar &quot;boozy&quot; notes as they often do. It is fairly refined as a drinking experience with a lot of fruit and acidity in the cup. As an espresso you gain a big mouthfeel and tonnes of body, the red wine is still prominent but there's a candy-bubblegum sort of vibe that takes over - paired with the mouthfeel it reminds me of a milkshake! A very cool coffee indeed, I have found Burundis have really improved over the past few years. Now it's one of my favourite origins and often really impresses. Overall I think I marginally preferred the Claude but you cannot go wrong with either of these coffees. Hopefully this is a good omen for the jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with &quot;Proclaim Liberty&quot;, opening with a fairly traditional brass arragement - quickly subsiding into the main theme led by bass and piano. The band makes use of its full ensemble with a lot of rich harmony but as with other Captain Black records when soloing many musicians drop out leaving the soloist space to express themselves. As he usually does Orrin plays with his choppy stacatto piano style. Towards the end of the piece the tempo raises and things get a little more out there, overall a positive start to the album. Listening I couldn't help but notice a certain similarity to some of the Frank Zappa jazzier offerings (such as &quot;The Grand Wazoo&quot; and &quot;Waka/Jawaka&quot;) in some of the melodies - no bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second track &quot;This Little Light of Mine&quot; again makes use of the number of brass instruments, big lush full harmony washes over you. As the name suggests this is a reworking of the gospel classic. The drumming brings a frenetic quality to the whole affair though. This is mirrored in the opening sax solo which has some cool angular lines. Orrin carries on the urgency with an athletic piano solo spanning the instruments range. The outside playing does not feel forced however, it always feels natural. Something that cannot be said for a lot of modern jazz players - it feels modern yet at the same time could have been released at any time.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Bk_RI7OtD-8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;A Time for Love&quot; is the third track, as a stark contrast to the raw energy of the previous number it's time to slow things down. The only word to describe the melody here is beautiful. Nobody is overplaying on this piece, with down-tempo numbers there is sometimes a tendency to throw too much technique at the tune - not the case here. The use of a fender rhodes mid-tune just fits the mood perfectly. This is a very accomplished take on a standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous tune is just the calm before the storm however as &quot;That Too&quot; starts with a powerful Mingus-esque melody full of attitude and swagger. Again I here some Zappa-isms in the arrangment. At this point in the album, approximately a quarter of the way through, you can tell that they really went for it on this album. This is not a safe album, they're taking risks and trying to really make a statement - so far it is working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next tune is instantly recognisable as &quot;Off Minor&quot; by Thelonious Monk. Orrin's playing has always reminded me a little of Monk - it's very rhythmic and choppy in contrast to many other players who play smooth flowing sort of styles. I tend to think covering Monk brings out a lot of joy in the musicians and gives them a chance to playful. That does not seem to be the modus-operandi here however - again they seem to want to make a point. So far this is the most free and outside of the tunes on this album. The tempo modulates up and down through the piece and there is some wild soloing throughout. Very cool!

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xi1MKmGuf3A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Into Dawn&quot; brings us back down to reality again, starting off with some much less challenging harmony. The arrangment feels largely similar to the Roy Hargrove original - of course the musicians here throwing the &quot;Captain Black&quot; spin on things. Given the recent (tragic) passing of Roy Hargrove this feels a particularly fitting tribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extended take &quot;Tough Love&quot; begins with a poem - one doesn't have to look very hard to see the obvious Mingus influence here. The references to black-lives matter, school-shootings and general hate strike a mournful tone, the suggestion the poem suggests that letting in love, while challenging, could change everything. I don't want to try and unpick the deeper meaning here as I'm unlikely to do this justice on a first listen. I think this will provide a challenging and thought-provoking quality to any future listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last tune on the album is &quot;I'm so Glad I Got to Know You&quot; - it doesn't take much to uncover the underlying theme of this piece. Evans penned this as a tribute to Lawrence Lo’ Leathers who the jazz community also lost far too early. Starting with a contemplative solo piano intro it breaks into a more upbeat swinging big-band arragement - I presume illustrating the nature of loss. The tune ends with a chorus singing the tracks title - a very fitting and heartwarming end to the album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vEAwZAvhSp4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Overall this album has been a moving and sometimes challenging listen, but the quality is unmistakable. It is certainly worth hunting down through whatever medium you consume your music. I will be giving this another listen (or two) in the coming days. Walking the line between free and more traditional styles is tricky, especially as a big band, but this album shows Orrin knows how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/003-Orrin-Evans/Orrin-Evans-The-Intangible-Between.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/003-Orrin-Evans/Orrin-Evans-The-Intangible-Between.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lester Young with the Oscar Peterson Trio and Round Hill Spring Claude</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/lester-young-oscar-peterson-spring-claude" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lester Young with the Oscar Peterson Trio and Round Hill Spring Claude" /><published>2020-04-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/Lester-Young-Oscar-Peterson-Spring-Claude</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/lester-young-oscar-peterson-spring-claude">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-04-25-Lester-Young-Oscar-Peterson-Spring-Claude.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I'm going to write about 2 main themes: the first being contentious opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm just going to come out and say it: I don't like Oscar Peterson. I know admitting this will cause the jazz police to come over to my house and beat down my door, but it's true. I find his playing to rely on too many flashy tricks played at break-neck speed. The music, in my opinion, tends to suffer as a result. Don't get me wrong I can appreciate what he could do and of course he played with some amazing artists (Lester Young being one such example) - but he just ends up leaving me cold and so I never normally reach for one of his albums. I think in the jazz world we do get caught up in &quot;hero worship&quot; a bit too much, certain players get elevated to god status and can do no wrong. Miles Davis for example, the early stuff is obviously fantastic and he deserves all the praise he gets. But some of the later synthy-pop stuff? You'd be hard pressed to argue some of that has much artistic merit - a player without his reputation would be crucified for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the coffee side I also have a rather contentious opinion: I tend to not be overly impressed with Colombian origins. For me there are (obviously) some great ones but a large number of the coffees strike me as rather &quot;meh&quot;. Also certain areas in Colombia are renowned for their big body, nutty sort of flavour notes - these are not what I favour at all. I look for delicate florals and fruit notes first and foremost. As such it is rare I will order a bag of a Colombian origin given the choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads me onto the second theme of the day: pleasant surpirses (when they really shouldn't be surprising at all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1954 Lester Young stepped into the studio with Oscar Peterson (and others) to record the album: &quot;Lester Young with the Oscar Peterson Trio&quot;.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/002-Lester-Oscar/Lesteroscar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
A fun fact about this recording: it featured the Oscar Peterson Quartet rather than the trio as the name would suggest. Originally released as 3 seperate albums but has since been combined into 1 volume. Given my relationship with Oscar Peterson I did not listen to this album for years, despite Lester Young being one of my all time favourite artists - more fool me, since the album is fantastic from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lester Young was a curious fellow, he had a rather natty dress sense (with a particular perchant for pork-pie hats). While some of his contemporaries relied on technique and muscling their way through the changes, Lester took a much more laid back approach, sitting right in the pocket and playing relatively few notes with a more lyrical style. This was perfectly exemplified on his recordings with Billie Holiday, their styles blending perfectly. This laid back sax vibe was a reflection of his persona too, very laid back and &quot;cool&quot; - he was known for creating much of the jazz &quot;lingo&quot; of the time which is still being used today (including the term &quot;hipster&quot;). His friends call him &quot;Prez&quot; or &quot;the president&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The record itself poses an interesting counterpoint: Oscar wanting to up the tempo and play fancy lines while Lester wanting to sit in the pocket. The result is each player compromises - Lester plays some of his fastest most intricate lines on this record and Oscar dials back. It all just works, I would love to have sat in on the session I could have easily seen this going off the rails one way or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We shouldn't just focus on the 2 named artists however, the &quot;backing&quot; band is also fantastic (and could have lead other dates) featuring Ray Brown on bass, JC Hoard on drums and Barney Kessell on guitar. As a guitarist Barney is one of my favourites, he was very clearly in the Charlie Christian school of jazz guitar (which is no bad thing). On this record he plays some great solos for example on &quot;Tea for Two&quot;. Barney also had one of the best guitar tones I ever heard with his Charlie-Christian pickuped guitars and you can tell he is using one here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album itself is almost entirely made up of standards from &quot;On the Sunny Side of the Street&quot;, &quot;There Will Never be Another You&quot; and &quot;Stardust&quot;. On modern reissues there is also a cool outtake &quot;(It Takes) Two to Tango&quot; which features Lester singing (as far as I'm aware the only recorded track of him doing so). If I had to pick one tune to exemplify this recording though I would pick &quot;Just You, Just Me&quot;:

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0JmGh_bjZJE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Focussing now on this week's coffee; as you may have guessed it is a Colombian origin from La Vega in Tarqui, Huila. The coffee in question is roasted by Round Hill Roastery ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://roundhillroastery.com/&quot;&gt;https://roundhillroastery.com/&lt;/a&gt; ) and is their &quot;Spring Claude&quot; offering. Every season (I beleive) the folks at Round Hill release a &quot;special&quot; coffee in special packages under the &quot;Claude&quot; name. Claude being a cat:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/002-Lester-Oscar/claude.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
You can follow Claude's exploits on his instagram: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/monsieur_claude&quot;&gt;https://www.instagram.com/monsieur_claude&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always I opt for the filter roast, I prefer the less developed roasts even for espresso and given a choice I will opt for the filter roast even if it is to be used as an espresso. This coffee is roasted particularly light, I don't have an agtron/tonino (yet) to measure this however&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter you're not greeted with a very pungent aroma, there are gentle berry type smells but they're quite mellow. On first sip however you get smacked round the face with sweetness. This is one of the sweetest coffees I've had in a while, it has a candy-floss or sugar-syrup vibe. There is also a hit of red berry type flavours, I would describe as a raspberry. It is very easy to drink, a cup can disappear before you've even noticed - which is always a good sign. There is some balancing acidity to the sweetness but predominently it is all about the candy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a lighter roast pulling an espresso can be a bit of an issue. With coffees such as these I recommend pulling shots slighltly longer (around 2.25-2.75:1 sort of range) at a higher temperature than normal and quickly! However this coffee is fairly forgiving, it is not particularly acidic so I didn't end up with any super-sour shots. When dialed in the sugary goodness comes through, however you also have a reasonable amount of body coming through. It really gives off a syrupy vibe. The raspberry note is still there too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this coffee a lot, more than I expected to given the origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However I should really not be surprised by my enjoyment from either the album or the coffee. Lester Young constantly provides inspiration and I find Round Hill one of the most consistently great roasters in the UK. It goes to show that sometimes preconceptions can get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/002-Lester-Oscar/Lesteroscar.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/002-Lester-Oscar/Lesteroscar.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Inner Urge - Joe Henderson and Assembly Los Urena</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/inner-urge-los-urena" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inner Urge - Joe Henderson and Assembly Los Urena" /><published>2020-04-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/Inner-Urge-Los-Urena</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.github.io/blog/inner-urge-los-urena">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-04-16-Inner-Urge-Los-Urena.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my bleary-eyed haze of an early morning I paw at the laptop trying to get some music to play.  Before my morning coffee my creativity levels are low; I reach for an old favourite: “Inner Urge” by Joe Henderson. This album holds a special place in my heart, it is perhaps the most important album in my jazz appreciation. It was the album that converted my thinking from: “this jazz stuff is quite cool” to a full-blown obsession. I’m not one to believe in fate or superstition but this album was recorded on my birthday (albeit many years before I was born) – which is kind of a neat coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/001-inner-urge/InnerUrge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It starts with the title track; McCoy Tyner’s powerful opening chord stab sets the tone for the rest of the album. A dark and brooding, contemplative album throughout, all the time walking the fine line between sophisticated bop and chaotic free jazz – Joe with his albums from the mid-60s seamlessly blended these ideas like no one else.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dYxgci2uPno&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As the music is playing I grab a bag of coffee off the shelf, today’s offering is a Costa Rican from the folks at Assembly Coffee ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://assemblycoffee.co.uk/&quot;&gt;https://assemblycoffee.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt; ). The coffee is called Los Urena and is a honey processed typica from the Tarrazu region. Opening the bag (some of the nicest packaging in the business for my money), I’m greeted with a warming floral honey aroma. I doubt that this is going to be a big “punch in the face” sort of flavour bomb of a coffee, it is more a refined easy drinking elegance. I move onto preparing the beans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/001-inner-urge/20200214-Assembly-Packshot-Los-Uren_720x.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second track is now playing: &quot;Isotope&quot;. This is perhaps my favourite track on the album – it has a joyful playfulness yet angular ugliness to it. When I first heard this, I’d not heard anything like it – little did I know it was penned as a tribute to Thelonious Monk who I got (really) into many years later. Listening back now the Monk-isms are unmistakable an absolute joy to listen to. As the track ends I finish preparing the filter coffee.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ud0HIA-sEfQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Giving the cup a cursory sniff, I get mostly the same notes as from the beans – a sweet rich honey and some light florals. I wait a little for the cup to cool down and let the Latin influence of “El Barrio” cries out, Joe’s improvisation is incredible on this track. Others from the era might have played faster or had a more sophisticated sense of harmony but for my money Joe is the best improviser (possibly ever) – his lines are never neat or fall nicely under the fingers, it’s as though there is zero resistance between mind and the instrument.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/h3viBGZRgz8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The first sip of coffee acts like a big warm comforting liquid hug. This coffee will never go down as one of the most complex cups, but it is sophisticated. The thing that often strikes me about Assembly roasts is they tend to be very clean (which is a quality I always look for in a coffee) – these honey processed Americans can often get a bit “blurry” tasting but not here, everything is refined and elegant. I am thoroughly enjoying this cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through my years of drinking specialty I usually find that during each year there is one origin that is particularly spectacular, I can only assume that it is down to particular weather patterns in each region – much like certain wine vintages are so sort after. This year it seems like it is going to be Tarrazu Costa Ricans, this is the 2nd this year that has been great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finishing up the cup and the next tune begins, a change of pace and a beautiful ballad called “You Know I Care” penned by Duke Pearson. I often think ballads are underappreciated, playing over ballads requires just as much skill as blowing over crazy bop changes. Here Joe shows his lyricism, you can feel every single note and phrase. Not content with playing it straight he throws in a few more angular phrases but they never feel out of place.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fjgh1ZTXj74&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

It’s now time to test how this coffee behaves as an espresso. This coffee is intended to be used as a filter I believe; it is a light but not super-light roast. Being a honey processed American it is quite easy to extract and fairly forgiving. The espresso has some body to it but is not syrup monster like a darker roast would be. Like the filter it is not a flavour bomb but refined and clear, the florals pop a bit more and there is a bit of fruity acidity coming through overall fairly balanced. The flavour notes from Assembly say “Molasses, Blood Orange, Mellow” – I don’t get the blood orange too strongly but don’t disagree with their assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the clean coffee aftertaste lingering for a few moments the final track is playing: a Cole Porter classic: “Night and Day”. This is not your typical take on the standard though, an up-tempo fire-breathing hard-bop romp through the changes. As the music fades and I’m suitably caffeinated I finally feel ready for the day ahead.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8hFsKbEh4OI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/001-inner-urge/InnerUrge.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/001-inner-urge/InnerUrge.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>