<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-30T05:53:51-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Virtuoso and Icon 10</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/virtuoso-icon-10" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtuoso and Icon 10" /><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Virtuoso-Icon-10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/virtuoso-icon-10">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-10-23-Virtuoso-Icon-10.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wI0Fz8kUXmQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we have another &quot;Icon Series&quot; coffee from Plot Coffee Roasting in Woolwich, London. As you may recall the Icon series represents some of the more sort after and rare coffees available, and as part of the 10th installment in this series we have another special coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many of the Icon coffees its the cultivar that makes this coffee unique: in this case we have a &quot;Wush Wush&quot; cultivar. You can think of Wush Wush as the precocious younger brother to the Gesha cultivar. Like Gesha it has its origins in Ethiopia but has since been exported to other areas, with most (that I've seen at least) being grown in Colombia. Also like Gesha, Wush Wush is low yielding and quite difficult to grow - but the cup profile makes up for this. At date of writing the Wush Wush cultivars haven't quite gained the popularity of Gesha, and while not &quot;cheap&quot; they typically don't reach quite the stratospheric prices of the most prized Gesha coffees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to cultivar this coffee is interesting for its processing which is described as a &quot;Honey, Carbonic Maceration&quot;. The fruits are picked and fermented for 24 hours before being pulped and paced in a carbonic maceration tank to (anaerobically) ferment for another 24 hours. The coffee is then dried for a total of 20 days split between a drying structure and a poly-tunnel until the desired humidity levels are reached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all of this is moot unless the resulting coffee tastes great, so let's dive into it. On the dry aroma the first thing I note is &quot;sweet&quot;, upon opening the bag you can tell this one will be a very sweet one. I would describe the sweetness as being like a honey or quite a dark caramel type sweetness. Alongside there are some fruity notes but they're hard to pick out due to the honey being dominant. I also pick up some florality but again it's somewhat masked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual moving onto the filter cup: the sweetness I picked up on the nose is instantly noticable here. This is a very sweet cup indeed. Whereas a Gesha might lean more onto floral notes the Wush Wush is known for leaning more into sweetness. The fruity notes on the nose become clearer in the cup and I would desribe them as being like a pommegranate or sharp citrus. This is not a highly acidic cup but there is enough there to cut the sweetness. As the cup cools the cup becomes more complex and some of the floral notes come out. Elderflowers, jasmines and chamomile type notes are present as the cup cools. The tasting notes include &quot;lemongrass&quot; as a descriptor but this is not something I really notice personally. I would describe the body of the cup as being a medium, I've certainly had chewier cups but there is something there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso I found this coffee to be very strong also. I ultimately landed on a 1:2.5 sort of ratio in around 22s (as is typical with my new grinder). Again the major note in the cup is the honey sweetness. As an espresso you can really notice just how &quot;clean&quot; this coffee is too. Unfortunately some of the more complex notes are a little harder to pick up on but it is still a fantastic cup and very drinkable. I would say as a filter is where this coffee shines however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point the Plot Icon series has gone 10 for 10 in terms of picking some great coffees, I'm very interested to see if they close out the year with a bang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the iconic jazz this week I found myself dusting off a 1973 release: &quot;Virtuoso&quot; by Joe Pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/078-Virtuoso/Virtuoso.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Pass is widely considered to be one of the all time great jazz guitarists. He often played with the likes of Oscar Peterson and, perhaps most famously, Ella Fitzgerald. In addition he also recorded with the likes of Milt Jackson, Zoot Sims, Herb Ellis, Count Basie and many more. His discography reads like a &quot;who's who&quot; of the jazz world spanning from the early 1960s through to his death in 1994. He has inspired countless jazz guitarists (and other musicians) through the years and is one of the first names you'll hear if you ask anybody to name a jazz guitarist - and for good reason.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wgnaxuVv6Ag&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Virtuoso&quot; is considered one of the highlights of his career. We have to start by mentioning the title, it takes a certain amount of balls to release an album called &quot;Virtuoso&quot;. In doing so you essentially put a target on your back and every other musician picking up the album listens with an attitude of &quot;oh really?&quot;. This goes to show the ability of Joe, since nobody holds that against him (and in fact he even released follow up albums &quot;Virtuoso no.2&quot;, &quot;Virtuoso no.3&quot; and &quot;Virtuoso no.4&quot;). In fact &quot;Virtuoso&quot; even became somewhat of a blue-print for how all future solo jazz guitar should be played. Even now we can hear the influence in (for example) a modern player like Pasquale Grasso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &quot;Virtuoso&quot; Joe manages to combine his chord playing (although he didn't refer to them as chords rather: &quot;grips&quot;) with single note lines. While his chops are, obviously, impressive - it is the musicality with which he plays that is the real star. The album is made up of (almost) entirely standards and so there's a certain amount of &quot;respecting the tune&quot; that is required. There is often a temptation, especially when playing solo, to just throw all your chops and re-harmonization ideas at a tune. When the album is called &quot;Virtuoso&quot; that temptation is likely even stronger. But Joe manages to toe the line perfectly, managing to show off his enviable abilities but at the same time create something that is enjoyable to listen to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice of tune on the album is fairly &quot;basic&quot;: they're pretty much all &quot;crowd pleaser&quot; type standards that we all know and love. This adds another level of pressure to the performance since we've all heard these tunes performed in all variety of ways previously. There is one Joe Pass original on the album &quot;Blues for Alican&quot;, which as one would expect is a swinging jazzy blues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picking out my &quot;choice tunes&quot; on the album is very difficult here, each tune is a masterclass in jazz guitar and worthy of investigation. From the opening &quot;Night and Day&quot; which is pure Joe, through the improvised take on &quot;Cherokee&quot; featuring some manic single note lines, through the dark an pensive rendition of Monk's &quot;'Round Midnight&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the highlight of the album, however, is the stunning take on &quot;All The Things You Are&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). Which manages to mix some beuatiful voicings on the main melody with some toe-tapping high tempo swing and dazzling single-note lines. When I think of &quot;Virtuoso&quot; this is usually the first tune I think of. Another track that comes to mind is &quot;Have You Met Miss Jones?&quot; (above) - partly because it's not a tune that I know many good renditions of, but also due to Joe's use of walking basslines throughout. The album closer &quot;The Song Is You&quot; (below) is another highlight owing to Joe's playful use of timing throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all of the &quot;Icon Series&quot; albums: &quot;Virtuoso&quot; is certainly in the &quot;essential listening&quot; category. If you are a fan of jazz guitar, or jazz in general, you owe it to yourself to check out Joe if he is new to you - and &quot;Virtuoso&quot; is possibly the best place to start.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0EnuWgTVQUU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/078-Virtuoso/Virtuoso.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/078-Virtuoso/Virtuoso.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">For Centennial Reasons and Montero Gesha</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/for-centennial-reasons-monteros-gesha" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="For Centennial Reasons and Montero Gesha" /><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-10-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/For-Centennial-Reasons-Monteros-Gesha</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/for-centennial-reasons-monteros-gesha">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-10-16-For-Centennial-Reasons-Monteros-Gesha.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VBSTuXo6OOM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we have a bit of a special coffee on show. Whenever a gesha cultivar ends up in JazzCoffeeStuff HQ it is always a cause for celebration, but in this case the excitement doubles since it is from one of my favoruite coffee roasters (and one I don't get to purchase from as much as I'd like) - Morgon, located in Gothenburg, Sweden. Unfortunately this means there is a high level of expectation behind this coffee so let's see if it can live up to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have featured Gesha cultivars a few times in the blog before. As a quick reminder for those unfamiliar: the Gesha varietal quickly became the &quot;in&quot; cultivar during the mid-2010s owing to a coffee competition in Panama. This combined with how difficult it is to grow has led to prices reaching stratospheric levels. Of course as the popularity and demand increase there is also an increase in &quot;lower grade&quot; Gesha cropping up. These don't have the subtlety and flavour profiles of the top Gesha coffees and you're a bit beholden on importers/roasters to pick out the best lots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately the roaster in question this week is Morgon. They have featured a few times in the blog in the past and are an all time favourite of mine. I've yet to have anything less than stellar from them and I've had some of my favourite coffees of the past few years from them. What I particularly respect is their &quot;no nonsense&quot; approach to coffee roasting, they don't try and claim there's any &quot;magic&quot; in what they're doing. They just pick good green coffee, treat it with respect and let it speak for itself. I was particularly interested in trying a Gesha from them because this slightly goes against the ethos I associate with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself was grown in Tarrazu, Costa Rica. I have a bit of a soft spot for Costa Rican coffee as one of the first coffees that made me take specialty seriously was a Costa Rican. In this case the coffee comes from a farm owned by Carlos Montero - one of the most respected growers in Costa Rica. The processing is described as being &quot;natural&quot; but I do not have the exact details behind this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's just dive in: as usual starting with the dry aroma I get the sophisticated floral bouquet you associate with Gesha. It is not a heavy hitter in this regard (nor would you expect it to be) - but it gives a hint towards the complexity in the cup. Alongside florals I get a sticky-fruity type of sweetness on the nose, perhaps reminiscent of boiled sweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter using my trusted method: the first thing I notice is the sweetness of this coffee. This is not something I normally associate with Gesha, but I guess it is the &quot;Costa-Rica-ness&quot; coming through. I would describe the sweetness as being apricot or peach like and the bag descriptor of &quot;strawberry fields&quot; also seems relvant. Alongside of course you also have all the floral notes you would expect, these seem to come to the fore as the cup cools down a touch. The cup itself is very clean with just enough acidity to avoid being cloying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso: for this coffee I found I had to grind very fine on the dial. With my new grinder I still had enough play to get to reasonable levels but I could forsee some grinders struggling to get fine enough to produce a good shot. Ultimately I landed with a 1:2.5 ratio is about 22s for best results on my set up. The flavour profile is essentially the same as the filter just more concentrated. Whereas the filter might be &quot;apricot juice&quot; the espresso is &quot;apricot syrup&quot;. As is typical with these sorts of coffees some of the more complex floral notes are lost at the more concentrated levels of espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the espresso is very good, for me the extra complexity from the filter makes it the more natural choice for this coffee. Despite the very high expectation levels I had for this coffee it certainly lives up to it. Morgon once again showing they know their stuff when it comes to coffee roasting and green selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this weeks jazz we're hopping back to 2019 with the John Pizzarelli Trio and their tribute to Nat King Cole: &quot;For Centennial Reasons&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/077-Centennial-Reasons/Centennial-Reasons.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album is a bit different to others featured on this blog: it is the first album that (prominently) features singing. (The more eagle eared will note that there are some previously featured albums that do have &quot;singing&quot; but these tend to be 1 or 2 tracks on the album as opposed to the majority). This is simply down to my preference, I tend not to listen to many jazz vocalists.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cHBvegYWsYQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

John Pizzarelli is perhaps best known as being the son of jazz guitar legend Bucky Pizzarelli. Bucky was one of the true pioneers and one of the first (along with the likes of George Van Eps) to push the use of a 7 string guitar for jazz - something that John has since carried the torch for. John started his career in the early 1980s often working with his father. After releasing a string of albums under his own name he has gone on to work with the likes of Paul McCartney and James Taylor. He also has a brother Martin Pizzarelli - a double bassist who appears on much of his recorded works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John has also listed Nat King Cole as the main influence on his career. As such &quot;For Centennial Reasons&quot; is not the first tribute album he has recorded. There is also the 1994 release &quot;Dear Mr Cole&quot; and the 1996 follow up &quot;PS Mr Cole&quot;, you will also find countless Nat King Cole songs (or songs associated with him) dotted around his other albums. Following a couple of decades of career development and working on his craft I feel &quot;For Centennial Reasons&quot; is the most polished and complete of these however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a first vocalist to appear on this blog John Pizzarelli might appear a bit of an odd choice. He does not have a particularly strong nor unique voice, but what he does have is bags of charisma and charm to pull it off. As a live act he is one of the most enjoyable around and always puts on a great performance consisting of great music interspersed with jokes and anecdotes. I remember seeing an interview with him a few years ago where the reporter asks: &quot;on the New York scene your music isn't viewed as very cool, have you ever thought about changing your style?&quot; to which John responds: &quot;If you want to listen to a certain kind of music: my band is the best around. What can be cooler than that?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you would expect from a tribute album the majority of the material comes from the Nat King Cole canon. John does however pen 2 original pieces: &quot;A Hundred Years from Now&quot; which one could certianly mistake for an undiscovered Nat King Cole recording. And also &quot;Nat King Cool&quot; one of two instrumental pieces on the album where John and the band can flex their chops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the album is all about the swing however, over the years John has clearly fine-tuned every piece to find the optimal tempo and groove. With the focus being on swinging his way through a bunch of well known (and some less well known) tunes it is easy to overlook just how good a guitar player John is too. Some of the guitar solos and his trademark guitar-scat style is mindblowing on this album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the selected tracks this week I have taken the 3 tunes that John recorded promo videos for (each embedded in this blog). First we have the album opener &quot;Straighten Up and Fly Right&quot; - here John plays with the tempo and note accents of the original to make a track that really swings. Compared to his earlier recordings of this tune the version here just feels more polished and allows more of his personality to come through. This is one of the highlights of the album. Next we have the signature tune &quot;Get Your Kicks on Route 66&quot; - a signature tune for both Cole and Pizzarelli. Again by just subtly tweaking the timings and groove the song takes on a new life and it becomes an instant crowd-pleaser. The last select tune is &quot;It's Only a Paper Moon&quot; - perhaps a tune that one wouldn't necessarily associate with Nat King Cole, but it is one of my favourites. It is also one that features heavily in the John Pizzarelli repertoire. The version on the album represents the arrangement of the tune that John has been using live for the past decade or so and I think the only studio version he has of this arrangement so it is nice to get this one of disc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;For Centennial Reasons&quot; is a record well worth hunting down if you've not heard it before. If you're a Nat King Cole fan you'll recognise a lot of the tunes here (even if you're not you'll recognise a few). If you're new to jazz or come from a &quot;pop&quot; background and sometimes struggle with the density of some of the instrumental music featured on this blog this might be a good record to use as a &quot;gateway drug&quot; into jazz.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JtIdpTLoYSo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/077-Centennial-Reasons/Centennial-Reasons.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/077-Centennial-Reasons/Centennial-Reasons.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Out Here and Banko Gotiti</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/out-here-banko-gotiti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Out Here and Banko Gotiti" /><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-10-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Out-Here-Banko-Gotiti</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/out-here-banko-gotiti">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-10-09-Out-Here-Banko-Gotiti.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fQVeWl6hqDc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we head back to Devon based roaster: Crankhouse Coffee. Crankhouse have appeared on the blog a few times before and they're a very dependable roaster and regularly provide stellar coffee. As of late I've noticed they're particularly good for the &quot;funkier&quot; styles of coffee with more ambitious processing methods. And this weeks coffee provides an example of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This weeks coffee comes from Yirgacheffe, Eithiopia - one of the more recognizable and prized growing regions within Ethiopia. The name of this coffee is: &quot;Banko Gotiti Anaerobic (Strawberry)&quot;. Banko Gotiti is the name of the wet-mill where the coffee is processed. As you would expect this coffee has undergone an anaerobic processing step within sealed containers at a specific temperature, this allows more complex and interesting flavours to develop. This particular lot has code-name &quot;strawberry&quot; which gives some indication as to what we can expect in the cup. As with many Ethiopian coffees the cultivar is just listed as &quot;heirloom&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive straight in to the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I am initially hit with a somewhat typical &quot;boozy&quot; note you'd expect from a Yirgacheffe natural, however alongside this are some strong fruity notes and hints of chocolate and baking spices. Before even making a cup you can tell this is going to be a very complex cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter the &quot;strawberry&quot; from the name is instantly apparent, along with the other notes we had on the nose. The best way I can describe the flavour is a dark chocolate liqueur with a strawberry cream type filling. But I could also be persuaded by a &quot;black forest gateau&quot; as a descriptor. As you would expect from a funky flavour profile such as this the cup is not the cleanest you'll ever have in your life but it is certainly not a &quot;farmyard&quot; natural either. The sweetness is very high and the acidity somewhat muted while the mouthfeel and body are fairly high. While the flavour profile is quite complex this cup is quite &quot;linear&quot; with temperature and the profile doesn't really change much as it cools. This quality means that while it's complex, you can enjoy it just as much as an everyday cup while doing other acitivities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving over to the espresso side of things now. As you may recall I recently bought a new espresso grinder and I'm still getting to grips with it. Usually I like to talk about how easy a coffee is to dial in, but that is hard until I get a good baseline with this grinder. That said I didn't have a single &quot;sink job&quot; with this coffee so I feel it can't be an absolute pig to dial in. I found that I liked a fairly short ratio with this one, around 1:2.1 or so, as with other coffees on this grinder I liked a pull time of 22s. Keeping things shorter emphasised the body and mouthfeel a bit more and going longer didn't really increase sweetness or clarity any more. The flavour profile is much the same as the filter and the &quot;dark chocolate strawberry liqueur&quot; comes through even stronger. To me this is really where this coffee shines, the filter was good but the espresso spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you'd expect from Crankhouse another good coffee that will be missed. I also like the price-point that Crankhouse hit with this (and other coffees) where it's a bit more expensive than your &quot;typical&quot; coffees but not an over-the-top unobtainium pricing. It allows you to try more of these super interesting quality coffees without busting the bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I found myself digging out a 2013 release: &quot;Out Here&quot; from the Christian McBride Trio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/076-Out-Here/Out-Here.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christian McBride is one of the most critically acclaimed and in-demand jazz bassists out there today. His career started in the early 1990s and he has been consistently active ever since. He has worked with some of the greatest jazz musicians ever including:  Joe Henderson, Pat Metheny, Chick Corea, Freddie Hubbard, McCoy Tyner, Herbie Hancock, Roy Haynes and many more. Outside of jazz he has even worked with the likes of Paul McCartney, Sting, Isaac Hayes, Carly Simon and others. Through the 2000s and 2010s he saw his career shift from being a &quot;new kid on the block&quot; to one of the pre-eminent artists in the jazz world. This is something that does not come easily. His personality and demeanour likely helped with this as he is one of a select few jazz musicians who can combine chops with genuine charisma and stage presence. This is very evident in his radio show on NPR &quot;Jazz Night in America&quot; - which is well worth a listen as it is always fulled with insights, stories and of course great music.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/51S2lWEUH-o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

On &quot;Out Here&quot; Christian is joined by two younger up and coming musicians in the form of: Christian Sands on the piano and Ulysses Owens Jr on the drums. Both of whom also appeared on McBride's other 2013 release &quot;People Music&quot;. While &quot;People Music&quot; leant more into original compositions in the post-bop style within the quintet format; &quot;Out Here&quot; is more of a straight swinging trio affair with 7 of the 9 tracks being standards. I feel this makes &quot;Out Here&quot; very approachable as an album, but that is not a slight at the musicianship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playing such &quot;simple&quot; swinging tunes there is no place to hide and as jazz has grown to become increasingly complex finding younger musicians who can really swing is increasingly rare. Under McBride's tutelage Sands and Owens do a fantastic job. The tunes are energetic amd the solos wild but respectful of the music. I'm sure many other young musicians would have come in and thrown down needlessly show-y solos which would feel out of place. Sands in particular really stands out to me and this was probably the album that made me really take notice of him as a musician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When curating an album of (mostly) standards track selection becomes crucially important. Obviously there are &quot;crowd pleaser&quot; standards that people want to hear, but an album consisting of these will typically get quickly forgotten. Instead you typically want to balance these with &quot;non-standard standards&quot; - tunes that few musicians have thought of interpreting. McBride has done a great job here, we have a few crowd pleasers: &quot;Cherokee&quot;, &quot;East of the Sun&quot; and the fantastic rendition of &quot;My Favourite Things&quot; (above) along with some slightly more obscure standards like &quot;Hallelujah Time&quot; (at the start of this post) and &quot;Easy Walker&quot; and then perhaps the highlight of the album: a take on Johnnie Taylor's &quot;Who's Making Love?&quot; (a Stax record classic). 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OvrHiNVNoTo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Albums like &quot;Out Here&quot; are easy to forget about or overlook, so it is fun to look back at these every now and again. While not a &quot;groundbreaking&quot; album in any sense, it acts as a great example of what happens when you get three musicians into a room and just let them play. It is a joy to hear the energy between all the musicians here. Of course the real standout is McBride's band leading and it is a shining example for any bass player on how to drive a tune forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/076-Out-Here/Out-Here.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/076-Out-Here/Out-Here.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Extrapolation and Gakuyu Ini AA</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/extrapolation-gakuyu-ini" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extrapolation and Gakuyu Ini AA" /><published>2021-10-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-10-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Extrapolation-Gakuyu-Ini</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/extrapolation-gakuyu-ini">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-10-02-Extrapolation-Gakuyu-Ini.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/A_nbAw_p9UE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This weeks featured roaster is Curve Coffee Roasters from Margate. As you may recall Curve have featured on the blog a few times and rarely disappoint. For my money they're one of the most dependable roasters around and I don't think I've ever got a &quot;bad&quot; coffee from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I ordered a Kenyan coffee from them. It is called: Gakuyu-Ini AA. It is a washed processed lot consisting of the classic Kenyan cultivars SL28 and SL34. As with other Kenyan coffees the &quot;AA&quot; refers to the screen size of the beans - AA being the largest size. When I first got into specialty coffee there was a lot of talk around whether AA or AB or PB are better in the cup, I don't believe there is any relation truth be told. I have had great coffees in all screen sizes and some duffers too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't often go for Kenyan coffees, I enjoy them when I do but they're just not something I hunt down. I think everybody who's into coffee remembers the first time they tried a Kenyan coffee however because it is such an iconic and distinctive flavour profile. It is probably the easiest terroir to recognise. In recent years there have been movements within Kenya to produce more honey and naturally processed coffees (owing to the water usage of washed) - but I've not yet tried any of them. It would be interesting to test how much of the &quot;Kenya-ness&quot; comes through with alternative processing methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive right into the coffee itself: as you would expect on the dry aroma there is a strong whack of blackcurrant. Before even tasting there is no confusing the origin of this coffee. Alongside there is a delicate herbaceous and perfumed note, but it takes some concentration to find these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving into the filter: the first sip greats you with a big juicy cup. The blackcurrant note is so intense it is almost like Ribena and it has that sticky almost jammy mouthfeel also. If you favour flavour intensity this is definitely a good choice of coffee for you as it is a cup that smacks you round the head with the juicy fruity notes. Alongside the blackcurrant I noted down notes of rosehip and hibiscus as well as an almost mint-like herb note. As a cup it is quite complex and one to ponder over. Sometimes Kenyan coffees can be overly acidic, but this is not the case here. The acidity levels are high but not to the point of being uncomforable, owing to the great roasting by Curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving in to the espresso: this is where I often struggle with Kenyans. The acidity can get too much (especially for a coffee like this that is roast for filter) - but I found this one never got too battery-acid-y. I settled on a 1:2.5+ ratio for this coffee, going shorter didn't really increase the mouthfeel or body so it made sense to amplify the sweetness with a longer pull. As is the case with my new grinder I was running a 20s pull for optimal results (some would now call this a &quot;turbo shot&quot; or before an &quot;EKspresso&quot; but I just call it a shot, the names just feel like marketing). Some of the complexity of the filter is lost as an espresso but you're left with a very intense hit of blackcurrant jam. This is one of the best Kenyan's I've had as an espresso in a while. It is easy to drink and highly enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected Curve produce the goods again with another great coffee. I have no doubt that they will be a featured roaster on the blog again in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I found myself digging out an album I had not listened to for many years: the 1969 debut recording from John McLaughlin: &quot;Extrapolation&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/075-Extrapolation/Extrapolation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John McLaughlin needs no introduction, he is one of the most commercially successful jazz guitarists of all time with a career spanning 7 decades (just about). He could have comfortably fit into the &quot;Icon&quot; series of posts because he is surely an icon (and I'm sure he'll end up there soon enough with some of his other work). His &quot;big break&quot; came when working for Miles Davis on the &quot;In a Silent Way&quot;, &quot;Bitches Brew&quot;, &quot;A Tribute to Jack Johnson&quot; and other Miles hit albums. He is however best known for his work with fusion super-group &quot;Mahavishnu Orchestra&quot; which he formed and led. He is one of the revolutionaries of jazz guitar and was hugely influential in how distorted electric guitars were used in jazz.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/quhIqwG-sLU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Extrapolation&quot; appeared before all this fame and acclaim however, upon its release John McLaughlin was relatively unknown. THe album was released on an independent British record label: Marmalade Records initially. Following John's fame from his work with Miles the album got re-released by Polydor records. The album features an all British line-up of McLaughlin on guitars, John Surman on saxes, Brian Odgers on bass and Tony Oxley on drums. At the time of recording they were all relatively unknown British musicians with very few select releases under their own names and a few side-man appearances. I think this is what gives &quot;Extrapolation&quot; such vibrancy, each player is playing with complete freedom not being tied down to tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John is obviously most associated with &quot;fusion&quot;, but &quot;Extrapolation&quot; is perhaps the most &quot;jazz&quot; album in his his discography. If you have listened to Mahavishnu Orchestra and it's too much, then &quot;Extrapolation&quot; is a good place to start. You still get the signature &quot;widdly&quot; guitar playing of McLaughlin but it is less in your face. Reportedly jazz guitar supremo Joe Pass (who disliked Mahavishnu Orchestra and didn't consider it jazz) said upon hearing this album &quot;I guess he can play jazz&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the album is closer to a traditional jazz sound than other records in the McLaughlin discography that doesn't mean it is not an ambitious project. The album takes a thematic approach to composition, John establishes a theme in one piece and then it might appear again later and be resolved. It is for that reason it makes most sense to listen to this album in one sitting from start to finish rather than picking out individual tracks. Owing to the format of this blog I can't really embed an entire album so consider the tracks here just a &quot;taster&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McLaughlin's compositional voice and guitar playing obviously take centre-stage on this album, but some of the most memborable parts come from saxophonist John Surman (certainly a musician who is underappreciated). While the album is not &quot;free-jazz&quot; in the strictest sense, Surman does bring an edge of free-jazz to keep things interesting.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6L9uP_TfuIQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

If &quot;Extrapolation&quot; is not an album you've heard before it is definitely worth checking out. You can hear some of the early formings of the McLaughlin sound so if you're a Mahavishnu fan you'll definitely get a kick out of it. Conversely if you are not a fan of Mahavishnu it is far enough away from that sound to keep you entertained. The album manages to remain fresh even after all this time, if you were to tell somebody this was released in the 2020s they'd unlikely question it. Even the recording quality for a (relatively) low-budget release on an indy label is pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/075-Extrapolation/Extrapolation.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/075-Extrapolation/Extrapolation.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wolo So and Jacu</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/wolo-so-jacu" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wolo So and Jacu" /><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Wolo-So-Jacu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/wolo-so-jacu">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-09-25-Wolo-So-Jacu.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yWZBvAiI1MM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

On the blog this week we feature the latest coffees from my KaffeBox subscription. This time they feature Jacu Coffee Roastery ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacu.no/&quot;&gt;https://www.jacu.no/&lt;/a&gt; ) another roastery I haven't tried before. The coffee blog this week may be a little shorter than usual as I also recently took delivery of a new coffee grinder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/074-Wolo-So/Lagom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffees supplied by KaffeBox this month were used as the first coffees to try this grinder out and compare to my old grinders back to back. As such I wasn't really giving the coffees themselves as much attention as usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the filter side we have a washed Ethiopian coffee: Chelchele. The cultivar is just listed as &quot;Heirloom&quot; - which we have talked about many times in the past. Aside from this and the altitude (2000masl) I don't have all that much information about this one. On the nose I get the usual &quot;washed ethiopian&quot; profile of florals and stone fruits, but in addition a hint of spice. These flavour notes carry over to the cup along with a lemon citrus note. The cup quality is very clean as you would expect and the body and mouthfeel are quite low. It's not the sweetest nor the most acidic cup you'll ever have but it is very balanced. As a filter it is very easy to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have another Ethiopian coffee, but this time a natural: Tula. This time the cultivar has been listed as 74110 - one that I often see identified. It is always nice to see the cultivar listed, hopefully in time I will have enough of a back catalogue of coffees to really know how the 74110 differs from the Krume (for example). On the nose this coffee is completely different to Chelchele - it has a much bigger tropical fruit hit. These overpower any hint of floral or stone fruit notes that may be present. As an espresso I found this coffee rather flat using my old grinder compared to my new grinder which made it sing. Since the bag was small (125g) I couldn't dial each in to perfection but the difference was noticable. The coffee itself came across as quite a &quot;clean&quot; natural coffee and the tropical fruits were striking: I noticed notes of pineapple, passionfruits and papayas. Alongside these was quite a sharp acidity that I would describe as being a bit like a gooseberry. While this coffee does have the sweetness that comes from a natural process it definitely leans towards the acidic. I also found it likes to be in ratios longer than 1:2.5 - so you don't get too much in the way of body (which is fine by me!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given my love of Ethiopian coffee it was really great to see a pair of Ethiopians arrive as part of this month's KaffeBox delivery. Both of these coffees were very high quality and I'll definitely keep an eye out for Jacu again, I might order from them again in a few months after I really get to grips with the new grinder so I can tell how much of my enjoyment I can attribute to the grinder versus the coffee itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we're going to take a quick look at another 2021 release from UK based: Balimaya Project, with their album &quot;Wolo So&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/074-Wolo-So/Wolo-So.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Balimaya Project may not be a name familiar to you, they were certainly new to me. By chance I was making my way through the 2021 jazz releases and &quot;Wolo So&quot; instantly grabbed my attention. The music is daring and complex yet still has heart and authenticity.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/X13iJt9swt8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Balimaya Project is a &quot;big band&quot; consisting of 16 members, led by Djembe player Yahael Camara Onono. The make-up of the band is not your typical &quot;jazz big band&quot;, the instrumentation consists largely of the traditional instruments used by the Mandé people of West Africa. As such this group falls into that &quot;no-mans land&quot; between Jazz and World Music where lots of great music lives but rarely gets the recognition it deserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music itself is said to be based around the Mandé traditions and folklore, but having no experience with this I have no idea how closely Balimaya Project sticks to those traditions. What I can say however, is that music is fantastic. Alot of the focus is placed on creating a dense and multi-layered percussion track. There are plenty of polyrhythms and odd note groupings to get your teeth into. Despite this the music is incredibly easy to listen thanks to the &quot;party&quot; vibe to the music, you can get your music nerd on and try and understand what is going on rhythmically - or you can just get up and dance to it. This combination is something that is incredibly difficult to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the focus is definitely on celebrating the culture of the Mandé people, Balimaya Project combines this with contemporary jazz stylings. There are horns and electric guitars there too, and they do not feel out of place. At times there are even hints of Frank Zappa, modern fusion and even prog-rock. Naturally perhaps the closest analogue in the jazz world is Sun Ra's Arkestra - but this comparison gives both artists a disservice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's rare to find such a fresh and unique sound, almost every release you can tie back to a specific set of influences. &quot;Wolo So&quot; manages to create an entire vibe all to itself, it feels almost pointless trying to describe the music itself - to understand it you have to listen to it. For me this is definitely a contender for &quot;album of the year&quot; and its a record that will be in my rotation for a while. It is definitely worth hunting down a copy, especially if you enjoy the few tracks dotted through this blog post.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YEatijyb_EA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.balimayaproject.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.balimayaproject.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/074-Wolo-So/Wolo-So.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/074-Wolo-So/Wolo-So.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ascenseur Pour L’échafaud and Icon 9</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/ascenseur-pour-lechafaud-icon-9" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ascenseur Pour L'échafaud and Icon 9" /><published>2021-09-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Ascenseur-Pour-Lechafaud-Icon-9</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/ascenseur-pour-lechafaud-icon-9">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-09-18-Ascenseur-Pour-Lechafaud-Icon-9.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/icJw9HXXoXA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we take another trip back to the Plot Roasting Icon Series - this is the 9th instalment of this coffee subscription that has so far offered up some fantastic coffees. As you may remember the Icon series is meant to represent the best, most interesting and rare coffees that Plot offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee featured is another from Diego Bermudez - a farmer who has featured many times on the blog previously. One of the true masters of the &quot;alternative processing&quot; methods. This time the coffee showcases how a careful processing can elevate even the most humble of cultivars: in this case a Castillo lot. The Castillo is the result of years of experimentation to develop a cultivar that is suitably resistant to leaf rust. It can trace its lineage through the &quot;Colombia&quot; cultivar which is itself a hybrid of robusta and arabica (specifically the hybrid of Timor Hybrid and Caturra). The Castillo (named after researcher Jamie Castillo) is favoured for its resistance but the cup quality is not quite as sought after as some other cultivars - if careful processing can make a big difference to cup quality this offers many positives for the future of coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process undertaken on this &quot;Red Plum&quot; lot is: an initial fermentation at 19 celcius for 28 hours followed by a pulping and another fermentation for 40 hours at 21 celcius. The seeds then undergo a &quot;thermal shock&quot; washing first at 40 celcius then at 12 celcius. The coffee is then dried for 28 hours at 42 celcius and a relative humidity of 25% until the moisture content is 10-11%. It is no wonder that coffees from Diego Bermudez end up costing so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike earlier Icon offerings this coffee was offered in a reasonable sized bag which means I was able to dial in both espressos and filter coffees this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving right into the dry aroma: as you would expect from the processing the intial hit is sweet tropical fruits. This is certainly a &quot;fruit bomb&quot; style aroma that is very punchy and intense. The smell when grinding is also incredible and fills the room, who needs an essential oil diffuser?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the filter the first thing I noticed was the intense sweet-candy quality to this coffee. The flavour notes on the bag say: &quot;like a bag of skittles&quot; and frankly that is a perfect descriptor. You also get a candy-floss sort of quality too, it's quite a &quot;clean&quot; sweetness of candy-floss as opposed to say a caramel. Alongside you also get the tropical fruit notes on the nose: watermelon and papaya are the two I wrote down, the official flavour notes say strawberry and pineapple. The sweetness is balanced with some acidity but it is note a battery acid coffee by any means. The body and mouthfeel are low, some might even say a bit hollow. If you're a fan of more traditional &quot;big&quot; feeling coffees this won't be one for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto the espresso: I had one issue here, this coffee grinds very coarse - so even at the minimum setting on my grinder I could only get to a 1:2.5 ratio in about 25s. Thankfully this is where this coffee liked to be so it was not a big issue, but with different equipment I could see this coffee being a real hassle. When dialed in however you're left with a more intense and concentrated version of the filter coffee - full of candy and tropical fruits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I prefered this one slightly more as a filter but it was still great as an espresso. Plot knocked it out of the park again with the Icon series and I'll be eagerly awaiting what the 10th edition holds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the iconic jazz this week I decided to introduce Miles Davis to the blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/073-Miles/Miles.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miles is somebody who I've been in two minds about including on this blog. The first reason being that the world doesn't need yet another recommendation for &quot;Kind of Blue&quot; (although it is fantastic). Miles is so well known and there's so much information out there already I'm not sure I have much to add. The second reason is: personally I do not enjoy anything Miles released from &quot;Bitches Brew&quot; and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead I have decided to take a bit of a different track with this post and talk about: &quot;Ascenseur Pour L'échafaud&quot; - both the album/soundtrack and the film itself (in the English speaking world this is typically referred to as: &quot;Elevator to the Gallows&quot; or sometimes &quot;Lift to the Scaffold&quot;).

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GUb9MOeQBGo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Elevator to the Gallows&quot; is a 1958 film from Louis Malle adapted from a 1956 novel of the same name by Noël Calef. Outside of jazz and coffee I also enjoy classic film-noir - &quot;Elevator to the Gallows&quot; is not strictly a noir but it does have many elements that could be considered noir. As a film it also helped establish some of stylistic elements of French New Wave and New Modern Cinema.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot revolves around a pair of lovers Florence and Julien who decide to kill Florence's husband. Julien does this by climbing via a rope into the husband's office, shooting him, then leaving the scene to look like a suicide. Unfortunately he leaves the rope outside and so has to re-enter the building to retreive it. It is at this time he boards the elevator just as the security man turns off the power to the building for the evening and so Julien is stuck in the elevator between floors. As this is happening Julien's getaway car gets stolen by low level crooks who then find themselves accidentally (and unbeknownst to them) involved in a murder. The film follows how this whole situation begins to spiral out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is clear to see why many associate this film with &quot;noir&quot; given the plot-line, however stylistically it is very different. It is shot in a much more &quot;artistic&quot; way than a typical noir - some might even say more &quot;pretentious&quot;. It is certainly a style that will divide people, but personally I think the blend of the noir and new wave is seamless. The biggest departure from typical noir however is the soundtrack from Miles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The soundtrack is fairly brief, in its original form around 26 minutes in length (with alternate takes and so on current releases are much longer). The magic of the soundtrack however is the fact the entire thing was improvised when watching the film. This in itself is quite remarkable, but add to that the soundtrack also features some incredible jazz and memorable hooks that stick with you. It is really a testament to how good of a musician Miles really was, he manages to capture the mood of the film perfectly. Without his soundtrack I do wonder how good this film would be, often film soundtracks just fade into the background - but in this case it is an integral part of the whole vibe the film gives off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of choice tracks the most memorable is likely &quot;Générique&quot; which accompanies Jeanne Moreau walking through the French streets (embedded at the start of this post). It creates the perfect melancholy and loneliness that required and truly transforms the scene. As a result this has become one of the most iconic and best loved scenes in film history, without Miles it would not have this acclaim. Another piece that stands out to me is &quot;Sur l'autoroute&quot; (above) - a frantic bop inspired piece that captures the spirit of a getaway drive. My other choice track is the below &quot;Chez le photographe du motel&quot; - which features at the films climax (which I shall not give spoilers to). It manages to encompass the entire film's feeling and provide a resolution and closure.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wAscNqX8uqA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Ordinarily I talk about &quot;essential listening&quot; in these Icon series posts, in this case we have &quot;essential watching&quot; - as great as the soundtrack is as a standalone piece of work, to truly appreciate it I think you need to watch the film to see how it all fits together. So if you've exhausted Netflix and are looking for a piece of classic cinema to watch you could do much worse than hunting down &quot;Elevator to the Gallows&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/073-Miles/Miles.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/073-Miles/Miles.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Times Tales and Bombe</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/times-tales-bombe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Times Tales and Bombe" /><published>2021-09-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Times-Tales-Bombe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/times-tales-bombe">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-09-11-Times-Tales-Bombe.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yCg8qGKJcFg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are heading back to a roaster who has appeared on the blog before: Curve Coffee Roasters located in Margate. The guys and girls at Curve really know what they're doing and I've not been disappointed from them in the past. I was, therefore, very much looking forward to this coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the washed Ethiopian coffees have started to become available it comes as no surprise that this coffee is another washed Ethiopian. These are the coffees that really get me excited and given a choice what I would choose at least 90% of the time. I don't have a huge amount of information about this coffee, I know that it has undergone a dry fermentation process, the cultivars are &quot;heirloom&quot; and it is produced my a collection of small-holder farmers located in the Bombe Mountains within the Sidama region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado let's dive into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma you get everything you would expect from a coffee from this region. You're greeted with a big hit of peach and stone fruits along with the usual jasmine florals. Alongside this is a sweet honey type note to pull everything together. The aromas are punchier than you might ordinarily expect from a washed Ethiopian coffee but you could hardly describe it as a heavy hitter. It's the sort of aroma that makes you want to start brewing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we'll start by looking at the coffee as a filter. I usually find this is the best way to judge a coffee (at least compared to espresso) since the technique is not too demanding - although the forum, discord, YouTube and Insta coffee communities do enjoy making things more complicated than need be. In the cup I would describe this as quite a &quot;soft&quot; coffee, it is not one that will demand your attention and it is very balanced so you don't get distracted by it. It's the sort of cup that can fit into your day: if you want to sit and appreciate flavours you can, but if you don't want to that's cool too. The flavour profile itself is the same as on the dry aroma: peaches, florals and honey. The flavour leans heavily towards the peach and stone fruit end of things, the florals are there but they're not &quot;in your face&quot;. This is a cup that improves as it cools (up to a point) in my experience, so try to hold off slurping it down in a few seconds - although that does take some restraint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto all things espresso: this one is fairly forgiving on grind size and recipe, as long as you don't do a super slow pull things should be tasty. I find 1:2.5 is about right and I look for around 7s pre-infuse then a 24s pull. What you're left with is concentrated peach juice sweetened with some honey. The body and mouthfeel is not very big no matter what you do so pulling a little longer than a standard 1:2 allows for a bit more flavour separation which is a good compromise in my book. The aftertaste is extremely clean and not long lived, it makes Bombe very easy to shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes as no surprise that Curve did a good job roasting this coffee, and it's another solid washed Ethiopian. It seems like the washed Ethiopians are very strong this season (although it might be I have just been waiting for so long). I'm sure Curve will feature on the blog again and I'm certain this won't be the last from Ethiopia we'll see this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I found myself digging out an album from 2014: Jeff Ballard Trio's &quot;Time's Tales&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/072-Times-Tales/Times-Tales.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Ballard may not be a name you are instantly familiar with. However, if you have any familiarity with jazz you have likely heard his playing before. As a side-man he has appeared on albums from Chick Corea, Joshua Redman, Pat Metheny and Kurt Rosenwinkel. He is probably most famous for being the long-term drummer in the Brad Mehldau trio, having been appointed to that position in 2005. Given the popularity of these artists he is likely one of the most successful modern drummers based on album sales (although I have not crunched any numbers for this).

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/flPQcl5XZXc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The Jeff Ballard Trio consists of Jeff Ballard on drums (unsurpirsingly), Lionel Loueke on electric guitars and Miguel Zenon on alto saxophone. Lionel Loueke is one of the more interesting modern jazz guitarists around, he takes a lot of his influence from West African music and combines this with Xhosa-inspired vocal lines using the &quot;click&quot; sounds in a similar way to the &quot;scat&quot; sounds more familiar to jazz listeners. Miguel Zenon is no slouch either, it is safe to say he is firmly in the &quot;free&quot; camp in terms of jazz and has a strong influence of Ornette Coleman in his playing. Perhaps most notable within his playing is his ability to play complex polyrhythmic ideas with ease. The Jeff Ballard Trio is therefore a heavy hitting modern jazz trio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Time's Tales&quot; is really quite an ambitious album. It covers a lot of ground and styles from simple ballads, to heavy rock fusion, to world music and free jazz. The musicians make these transitions seamless and the whole album remains coherent and not just a big mess of tunes thrown together. Jeff's drum lines and ability to swing through even the most complicated rhythmic signatures is what really holds the whole thing together. Without having a bassist to lean back on the trio relies on the drummer to keep them grounded, but in &quot;Time's Tales&quot; case this doesn't equate to &quot;boring, safe&quot; drumming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights of the album is the track &quot;Beat Street&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). It kicks off with a twisting melody played by Zenon and Loueke in unison on top of a complicated meter. This quickly gives way to Zenon's solo which showcases his Coleman inspired free lines. This leads into Loueke's solo which takes influence from world music before Ballard gives a polyrhythmic masterclass in his solo. The magic of the piece is hearing how all three musicians stay true to their individual styles and preferences yet still serve the tune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next tune I want to highlight is &quot;Hanging Tree&quot; (above). The influence here is clearly &quot;rock&quot; music and it features Loueke playing distorted guitar in a way I've not heard him play before. This is a tune that could easily be considered &quot;fusion&quot; or even &quot;jazz-punk&quot;. On the album it is a bit of an outlier which makes it all the more memorable. It also gives Ballard a chance to play with more aggression which increases the energy and adds a nice flow to the track listing.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yOhfEkx8D4M&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another personal highlight of mine is Zenon's arrangement of Silvio Rodriguez's &quot;El Reparador de Suenos&quot; (above). Rooted firmly in the Afro-Cuban tradition the track swings with syncopated style and elegance. Here Zenon and Loueke do not opt to play in unison but play contrasting lines that seem to fit perfectly. The interplay between all members is an absolute pleasure to hear, Ballard's drumming pushes and pulls throughout creating tension only to release it at the optimal point. It is a very refreshing take on the Afro-Cuban style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I selected 3 tracks here I could have equally selected any of the others to feature. The Gershwin ballad &quot;The Man I Love&quot; is simply sublime as is the take on Bela Bartok's &quot;Dal&quot;. The improv pieces &quot;Free 1&quot; and &quot;Free 3&quot; are also worthy of note as is the Loueke penned &quot;Virgin Forest&quot;. If I were to write this blog on another day I could have easily featured a completely different set of tracks. As is the strength of this album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Time's Tales&quot; is unlikely to feature in any &quot;essential listening&quot; album list you'll ever find, but it is still worthy of your time if it is one that is unfamiliar to you. It is a great example of what a modern jazz trio can do, it takes influence from the past but is not beholden to it. I consider this album a bit of an &quot;underrated gem&quot; from the mid 2010s, so be sure to hunt down a copy if you like what you've heard/read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/072-Times-Tales/Times-Tales.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/072-Times-Tales/Times-Tales.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Humble Warrior and La Claudina</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/humble-warrior-la-claudina" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Humble Warrior and La Claudina" /><published>2021-09-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Humble-Warrior-La-Claudina</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/humble-warrior-la-claudina">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-09-04-Humble-Warrior-La-Claudina.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zkMmURjJVmE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

For the coffee this week we are heading back to Bath's finest: Round Hill Roastery. These guys have appeared on the blog many times in the past and rarely disappoint, they're one of the roasters I always find myself going back to because they're so reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this coffee arrived I had a bit of a glut of coffee to get through, so this coffee has been sitting in my freezer for a good few weeks. Typically I don't like freezing coffee and I like to keep a rolling supply going rather than keep a large freezer back log. This is largely down to superstition. When I first got into specialty coffee many moons ago all the advice said &quot;never freeze coffee&quot; and so this has kind of stuck with me. We know better now however, and plenty of people get amazing results from freezing. In the back of my mind I'm always worried about trapped humidity etc. in the bag causing issues. Fortunately with this weeks coffee I did not see any ill effects (although I didn't try a &quot;non-freezed&quot; version to compare).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is from a farm called La Claudina in Colombia. This particular lot consists of Colombia and Caturra cultivars and what makes the coffee particularly interesting is the &quot;extended fermentation&quot; processing. The coffee cherries ferment in water for 24 hours and then dry ferment for 24 hours. This farm adjusts these processing methods on different lots to achieve different results. This particular example has been &quot;extended&quot; compared to their usual approach, so I am expecting a bit of a funky vibe to this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I get notes of rich caramels and sweet dark berries. It does not give off an obvious &quot;funk&quot; note but you can tell it's got a &quot;natural&quot; thing going on. On the nose it is fairly punchy but is not a complete fruit-bomb sort of coffee. It is certainly inviting, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter brewed in the usual way: the funky note is quite apparent. This may be because I don't typically take the funky bus often. It doesn't have the real farm-yard natural funk that some have, but it is noticable. I would describe it more as a fermented fruit sort of funk instead of a boozy funk. In terms of flavour notes the dark berry notes from the nose are certainly at the forefront for me. Alongside is a little tropical fruit edge and just a hint of herbaceous florality. In terms of profile I would say the acidity and sweetness are medium and the body is fairly high. The cup is quite &quot;linear&quot; as it cools, so you don't get too many surprises. The aftertaste is quite longlasting but pleasant. For a natural this funky it is not a muddy sludgefest, there is still a decent amount of clarity (but nothing like the washed Ethiopian's of the past couple of weeks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This coffee for me is more at home as an espresso (as always I still only buy the filter roast option). The bigger body and heavier dark fruit notes are more at home in the concentrated form. The funkiness in the filter is somewhat lost as an espresso however. After a bit of playing I settled on a ratio of 1:2.25. This seemed to highlight the body and mouthfeel while being just long enough for good flavour separation. As an espresso it is one you do not really have to think about, it is extremely easy to pull and extremely easy to drink. The flavour profile is much the same as in the filter but in concentrated form you also get a sort of jammy quality too, it is a slightly &quot;sticky&quot; sort of mouthfeel which is quite nice. If you think of redcurrant jelly as you'd have on a roast dinner it's not a million miles away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected Round Hill delivered the goods again and show just how reliable they are as a roaster. I'm sure it won't be too long until they feature on the blog once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz side this week I found myself listening to a 2020 release that slipped my attention: Wayne Escoffery's &quot;The Humble Warrior&quot; on the Smoke Sessions label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/071-Humble-Warrior/Humble-Warrior.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll admit I dropped the ball on this one, I should have checked this out months ago. I love some of the music being put out on the Smoke Sessions label but I find it hard to remember individual albums because they all have near identical cover art. As a result I create fake memories of hearing a particular album because I mistake it for another. Thankfully I managed to notice my error with &quot;The Humble Warrior&quot;.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mt7tQphDzhQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Wayne is perhaps best known for his work with the Mingus Big Band (with whom he won a Grammy) but he has an equally impressive resume playing with the likes of Herbie Hancock, Ron Carter, Jimmy Cobb and Monty Alexander among others. He is also a long standing member of the Tom Harrell quintet. He also holds the prestigious position &quot;lecturer of jazz improvisation&quot; at Yale. Under his own name he has half a dozon or so albums, and his previous release &quot;Vortex&quot; from 2018 won him a lot of plaudits cementing him as one of the pre-eminent saxophonists working today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;The Humble Warrior&quot; features Wayne's usual quartet along with a couple of interesting guest spots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wayne Escoffery: Saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Kikoski: Piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ugonna Okegwo: Bass &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ralph Peterson: Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Randy Brecker: Trumpet &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Gilmore: Guitar &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can feel the sense of familiarity between the core band throughout the album. Wayne seems to place a high level of trust in his musicians and it feels more like a group collaborative effort than a band playing the leaders compositions. This shows a lot of maturity as a band leader and the music benefits from it. Kikoski and Okegwo each even get a writing credit for the tracks &quot;Undefined&quot; and &quot;Back to Square One&quot; respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album gets its title as a tribute to the many jazz greats we have lost in recent years: musicians who acted like warriors yet allowed the music to keep them humble. As quite a softly spoken character himself, it feels as though this is also a good way to describe Wayne Escoffery. But make no mistake: once the music starts he is capable of creating some of the most intense and complex fire breathing solos around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big part of &quot;The Humble Warrior&quot; is dedicated to a jazz re-interpretation of Benjamin Britten's &quot;Missa Brevis In D&quot; - and this is perhaps the major statement on the album. It is expertly crafted, it takes just enough liberties to be interesting but it does not apply so many re-harmonizations that the piece itself becomes unrecognizable. This is a difficult line to draw and one where many jazz musicians fail in interpreting classical pieces. As a young child Escoffery was a member of a boys choir, and given the popularity of &quot;Missa Brevis in D&quot; with choirs, this is likely where the inspiration came from. One of the standout moments of this re-interpretation is in &quot;Benedictus&quot; where Wayne's son Vaughn Escoffery (11 years old) adds vocals to double his father's sax lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the two Escoffery original compositions the title track gives the comtemplative and respectful quality one would expect knowing the back story. It features quite a complex twisting melody featuring some breathtaking interplay between Escoffery and Brecker. It manages to shock and amaze but at the same time remain entirely approachable, marking Escoffery as a &quot;Humble Warrior&quot; indeed. Of course the track also acts as a fantastic &quot;canvas&quot; for the soloists, with Escoffery building from tasteful almost vocal lines through to full frenetic madness but always staying in total control.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YosT9Zs_80k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another standout track for me is Gildo Mahones' ballad: &quot;Quarter Moon&quot;. On this Wayne shows he does not need to rely on his awe inspiring technique and harmonic knowledge to get the job done. He can play a sensitive and caring ballad as well as anybody, something that is becoming a bit of a lost art in modern jazz. I have to admit that &quot;Quarter Moon&quot; was not a piece I was familiar with before listening to this album, but it has become a firm favourite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall &quot;The Humble Warrior&quot; is a great example of what modern jazz can be. It is one I've had on solid rotation for the past week or so. If you're looking for something new to listen to that is complex yet approachable, respects jazz of the past but still makes a statement itself - you should really hunt down a copy of &quot;The Humble Warrior&quot; as it's a thoroughly enjoyable listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/071-Humble-Warrior/Humble-Warrior.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/071-Humble-Warrior/Humble-Warrior.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sounds From The Ancestors and Dimtu Hambella</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/sounds-from-the-ancestors-dimtu-hambella" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sounds From The Ancestors and Dimtu Hambella" /><published>2021-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Sounds-From-The-Ancestors-Dimtu-Hambella</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/sounds-from-the-ancestors-dimtu-hambella">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-08-28-Sounds-From-The-Ancestors-Dimtu-Hambella.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GN91tbUnFEg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we head back to the fine folks at Plot coffee roasting, I always seem to be raving about them on this blog but they continue to knock it out of the park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past I have talked about how much I enjoy washed Ethiopian coffees, if I see one on a cafe's bean selection it will take something special to draw me away from trying it. We are now heading into the part of the year when all the washed Ethiopian coffees are starting to land, I believe this was actually the inspiration for the Andy Williams song: &quot;It's The Most Wonderful Time Of The Year&quot; (citation needed). This brings a lot of excitement to JazzCoffeeStuffHQ but also lots of headaches in trying to decide which ones I want to buy and from which roasters. Plot is sort of a no brainer option to kick off the season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular coffee is from a washing station owned by Israel Degfa - an inpsiring man who does a lot of amazing work for the community in Ethiopia, we have talked about him at length in previous posts so we won't re-tread the same ground here. The location of the washing station is in Hambella Dhekbor within the Guji zone of the Oromia region. Each region/zone of Ethiopia has its own &quot;flavour profile&quot; so those more familiar with Ethiopian coffee might know what to expect from a washed Guji. The cultivars for this coffee have not been identified and are simply listed as &quot;landrace varieties&quot;, it would have been nice to get some more detail but this is not always possible. For those who worry about altitude of the area is at 1850-2200 MASL - so certainly on the higher end!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's not waste any more time and get straight into the coffee itself. On the dry aroma I don't get a particularly intense bouquet. As you would expect on the nose it is quite delicate and restrained but with a lot of floral complexity. It is quite hard to pick out individual notes because the aroma is so feint. As I've said before I don't believe a &quot;weak nose&quot; means &quot;weak in the cup&quot;, I think it's a false equivalency many new to coffee make. I think the reverse might actually be true, the more volatiles given off leave less to be in the bean to be extracted - but this is just my supposition, I have no evidence to back this up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going in as a filter: the first sip I had made me sit back and take note. This is a very striking coffee, it is vibrant, zingy, sparkly, clean and extremely tasty. It also has a boat load of complexity and really changes character through the lifetime of the cup. The main flavour notes I get are a really crisp dry lemonade, green apples, lime along with a ton of floral character in the back: lavendar, jasmine and violet. The peach or apricot note you often get is a little overpowered by the heavier acidic fruit flavours here and it doesn't have a strong black-tea note like some. This makes it quite a neat take on a washed Guji and keeps it very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso I've found this one is really quite forgiving on my set-up. I ultimately settle for 1:2.5 in around 25s which is a fairly typical recipe for me, I generally start there but with this one I found no reason to experiment any further. Unlike some floral coffees the floral notes are still at the forefront in the concentrated form, this makes for one of the more complex espresso shots you're likely to taste. Based on the acidity in the filter one might expect the espresso to be prone to &quot;battery acid&quot; but this is really not the case, it is certainly a crisp acidic espresso but it was not once overbearing. It is not likely to be a shot for those chasing the big bodied chewy traditional espresso styles but I think it is one that can appeal to those starting to stray into the more acidic lighter roast realms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all another knock out by Plot (not that I'd expect anything less). These sorts of coffees are really my favourites, I love tasting the &quot;unobtainium&quot; hyper-coffees with crazy processing and cultivars: but there's something special about finding really tasty coffees at reasonable enough prices. If I operated a cafe I would be very happy to make this one my &quot;house&quot; option while it is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the washed Ethiopian coffee season: another event that adds an air of excitement to the JazzCoffeeStuffHQ is a new album from Kenny Garrett. This is what we're going to take a look at today: &quot;Sounds From The Ancestors&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/070-Ancestors/Ancestors.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album was released yesterday, so this blog will very much just be my initial impressions rather than any deep takes on the pieces. I've done this with a couple of albums in the past, at one point I might go back and do a retrospective to compare my initial thoughts to how I feel after more serious listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kenny has featured on the blog previously so if you'd like more a background on him there's a good place to go. For my money Kenny is the most reliable jazz performer in the world today. His live shows are simply fantastic, he doesn't have a huge &quot;stage persona&quot;, he doesn't relay stories or jokes to the crowd, he doesn't use light shows or expansive backdrops and he doesn't ham it up with over-exaggerated mannerisms to elicit a response from the crowd. Instead he just gets to work, serves the music and has the audience eating out of the palm of his hand. If you have not had a chance to go to one of his shows I strongly suggest going.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QOH8tlpe9bY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

So let's get into &quot;Sounds From The Ancestors&quot; a bit. As the name suggests the whole album feels a bit like a nod to those that came before him. If you have heard an album from Kenny in the past decade or so you'll know he has been taking more and more of an influence from &quot;non-jazz&quot; music (but make no mistake he is still a jazz heavyweight). This is noticable on the album, you have influences from hip-hop, afro-cuban jazz, Asian classical music, soul/rnb along with a whole host of other jazz influences. My ear is quite attuned to the melodic minor scales that make up a large part of Kenny's playing (he loves the Mix flat 6 in particular over dominant chords), but I see him playing more and more with what I believe is the Hirajoshi or &quot;Japanese Pentatonic&quot; scale in his later work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album is also noticable for the inclusion of vocalists, something Kenny hasn't really used too much in the past (aside from the odd piece or the throat singing on &quot;Pushing the World Away&quot;). The vocalists don't really sing &quot;songs&quot; however, the voices are used as additional instruments in the arrangement. They are often doubling lines or providing additional harmony to extend the depth of the mix. I can imagine live this will lead to a lot of audience interaction with Kenny essentially playing the audience as a &quot;piano&quot; of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also fantastic to hear Kenny further expand rhythmically (the tracks contain tributes to legendary jazz drummers Art Blakey and Tony Allen). On the last few albums he began to dip his toe into poly-rhythms but he has taken this much further. This is perhaps most noticable on &quot;For Art's Sake&quot; where the drum and percussion players lay down a really complex but grooving meter. There is a really mind blowing section of poly-rhythm which I believe is something in 6 played over something in 7, but I'll need to listen to this more to get my ear in and really nail down what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the stand-out pieces for me is the second track &quot;Hargrove&quot; (clearly a tribute to late trumpeter Roy Hargrove). He captures the vibe of the jazz-hip-hop crossover that characterised the Hargrove sound, however he still manages to inject the Garrett sound. I believe this track could act as an incredibly powerful &quot;gateway drug&quot; for those in the neo-soul and jazz-hip-hop scene looking to start their journey into the heavier end of jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track &quot;It's Time to Come Home&quot; captures the afro-cuban side to Kenny's playing perfectly. It feels like a modern update to the sound of another great Kenny: Dorham. For the hardcore Garrett fans it also features some cool little throwback licks to older pieces in his repertoire.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rAUrNahEg7o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Overall &quot;Sounds From The Ancestors&quot; is incredibly complex, exciting and even to this day Kenny is pushing into new ground. Despite all the complexity (you can really spend an age trying to work out what's going on with some of these pieces) it is surprisingly approachable and you don't require a music degree to enjoy the music (something that can't be said for some modern jazz). I feel this is an album worthy of the hype and I'm sure it's one I'll keep coming back to, but this is hardly a surprise from a Kenny Garrett album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/070-Ancestors/Ancestors.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/070-Ancestors/Ancestors.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Music and Solberg and Hansen</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/music-solberg-hansen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Music and Solberg and Hansen" /><published>2021-08-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Music-Solberg-Hansen</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/music-solberg-hansen">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-08-21-Music-Solberg-Hansen.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/E49KcZL6Rw4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we take a look at the August edition of the KaffeBox subscription. This month the featured roaster is Solberg &amp;amp; Hansen located in Oslo, Norway. What makes Solberg &amp;amp; Hansen particularly interesting is they were established in 1879 - which in itself is quite remarkable. Most of the roasters featured on this blog were only established in the 2000s (with possibly one or two creeping into the 90s). This makes Solberg &amp;amp; Hansen the oldest coffee roaster in Norway and one of the oldest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My only previous experience with Solberg &amp;amp; Hansen has been from another coffee subscription I have for decaf coffee, and that one was probably a top 5 decaf of all time for me. So I have high hopes for the coffee this week. Unlike in previous KaffeBox offerings we only have one coffee supplied in a 250g bag this time, which means we can really dig into it as both a filter and an espresso. Which makes a change from the previous KaffeBox &quot;split&quot; blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is called Chelbesa, grown in Gedeo, Gedeb in Ethiopia. The coffee is processed at the Danche washing station. The coffee has undergone a 72 hour wet fermentation before beging washed and then soaked for a further 2 hours and dried over the course of 10 days. Unlike many Ethiopian coffees the cultivars have been identified as consisting of Wolicho and Kurume - this is a trend I am very in favour of and hope it becomes common practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Chelbesa is a coffee I have had a few times before from other roasters so I have a good idea of what to expect in the cup. Fortunately it is a coffee that I have enjoyed in the past so one I am looking forward to trying again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the dry aroma I get the usual floral and stone fruit notes you associate with a washed Ethiopian coffee like this, however I also get lots of caramel and toffee notes too. I believe this is due to the coffee being a little more developed than you'd typically expect from a Nordic roaster. You can tell this is a more &quot;traditional&quot; roaster compared to some of the &quot;new kids on the block&quot; and there is nothing wrong with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter Chelbesa is very similar to how I remember it. I would describe the coffee as very &quot;soft&quot;, I can't really think of a better word to use. While some Ethiopian coffees are vibrant, others are very perfumed, Chelbesa has a soft almost marshmallow quality to it. This is more a textural or sensory experience than it is a taste thing. In terms of flavours you have all the usual suspects coming to play: peaches, apricots, jasmine, floral, black tea - everything you want in a washed Ethiopian. It does not have much in the way of citrus like some however. It is a complex cup that really changes with temperature and it's one you can drink almost to the point of being &quot;cold&quot; and it doesn't become too harsh. It is relatively low in acidity (for an Ethiopian) and fairly sweet with a good amount of body. I wouldn't describe it as a &quot;typical washed Ethiopian&quot; but it is a nice twist on a theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso there are a few things to note. The first of which is that owing to the &quot;soft&quot; and restrained quality of the coffee you can pull really concentrated shots without things getting harsh or muddled. The slightly more developed roast helps in this regard too as it makes it incredibly easy to extract. I stuck to the tradtional 1:2 with about 7s pre-infuse then a 27s pull with this one. It's not often I use a recipe like this. I did bump the temperature up a little bit which did seem to add a touch more vibrancy to the cup. The flavour profile is much like the filter: peaches, apricots, black tea and plenty of florals. If you imagine a sweet peach iced tea that you reduced down to a syrup you wouldn't be too far off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I think I enjoyed this coffee more as an espresso than I did filter but both were enjoyable and had some interesting characteristics. Another good choice by KaffeBox and as always I'll look forward to the next month's offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week I found myself reaching for a record released in 1989 - french pianist Michel Petrucciani's &quot;Music&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/069-Music/Music.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michel is quite an inspiring character, being born with osteogenesis imperfecta (&quot;brittle bone disease&quot;) leading to him being short and often in a lot of pain - he still managed to become one of the greatest jazz pianists of his generation. Inspiring and influencing countless musicians during his relatively short career in the 80s and 90s.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dR7amlVCW6o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Michel's style was particularly interesting for the period. During the 80s and early 90s fusion ruled the roost with many players ditching the acoustic instruments and playing rock inspired pieces. In contrast Michel was a bit of a throw back, he had a much more lyrical and contemplative and was often compared to Bill Evans. He was a more multi-faceted player than being just a straight Evans clone however, he also combined this with blazing virtuosity (and given the pain he experienced while playing this is no mean feat) along with wider influences from the sounds of Paris, Brazil and elsewhere. That's not to say he couldn't hang with the fusion boys too (for example on the fantastic &quot;Manhattan Project&quot; - which may appear in a future blog post at some point).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music marked the start of Michel's experimentation with synthesizers and richer and more expansive arrangements. Unlike other records from the era the use of synth is very tasteful and often features as an instrument that doubles a piano line or is deeper in the mix to just add depth. This avoids the album feeling and sounding &quot;dated&quot; by today's standards, which cannot be said for a lot of albums released in the late 80s (as much as I love some of them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The line-up on Music is fairly fluid, with musicians subbing in and out on the various tracks of the album. This does not stop it feeling like a single cohesive piece of work however, owing to the vision of Petrucciani. The line-up is not awash with &quot;big names&quot; (although this doesn't mean much, there are all-star line-up albums that are absolute rotters) but there are two familiar names that do appear: Lenny White on the drums - best known for his fusion work. And on the last track a tasty guest soprano sax solo from Joe Lovano (Petrucciani later appears on Lovano's seminal &quot;From the Soul&quot; album which we covered a few weeks back).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is hard to do an album like Music justice by just picking a few tunes to highlight. The album covers a lot of ground. At the start of this blog I embedded one of the most memorable pieces: &quot;My Bebop Tune&quot;. This is a crazy piece with a complicated stop-start melody with lots of twists and turns. It almost comes across as Michel mocking the ardent be-bop community for their obsession with needless complexity. I have always felt the tune is a little tongue in cheek, but others may disagree with me there. Either way it is a very cool piece that really shows off Petrucciani's chops as both a composer and player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlight of the album is perhaps &quot;Lullaby&quot;. This is an absolutely beautiful piece full of the most delectable lines and a heartfelt presentation. Jazz artists often (wrongly) get accused of focussing only on the technical aspects of the music are incapable of portraying real emotion, if presented with that challenge one only needs to present &quot;Lullaby&quot; to make the argument null and void. I think you'll struggle to find a piece in any genre with more heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final track &quot;Thinking of Wayne&quot; (below) features the Lovano guest solo part way through. This track is likely one of the more &quot;modern jazz&quot; sounding pieces on the album. Given some of the licks and compositional style I imagine this is a tribute to Wayne Shorter since this could have easily been a Shorter penned track on a Weather Report album. However I do not have anything to back this up as I no longer own a physical version of this album to check the liner notes. Regardless another very cool piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is only a very small selection of what Music has to offer. You also have the Brazillian inspired &quot;Brazilian Suite No. 2&quot; and the Parisian &quot;Memories Of Paris&quot; featuring another guest Gil Goldstein on accordian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of &quot;rating&quot; I wouldn't quite place Music in the &quot;essential listening&quot; tier. It is a fantastic album that I always enjoy listening to but it is probably not quite an all-time classic. If you are already a fan of jazz and looking to expand your listening it is a good place to go to study Petrucciani's style. I think the music itself is quite approachable so it is worth listening to if this post has piqued your interest.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4hPFo32ugi0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/069-Music/Music.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/069-Music/Music.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>