<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-12T05:07:47-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Squint and Austratt</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/squint-austratt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Squint and Austratt" /><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Squint-Austratt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/squint-austratt">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-06-12-Squint-Austratt.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bFRVK_1o2cU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The blog is back after a short 1 week hiatus: over the past couple of weeks I had being trying some &quot;new&quot; (to me) roasters and the quality level was frankly quite low. I'm not in the business of writing negative reviews of coffee roasters, especially given the current economic climate for coffee companies generally, so took the week off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully this week we're back with some high quality coffee goodness - we have another installment of my Kaffebox subscription. This time featuring a pair of filter roast coffees from Norwegian roasters: Austrått Kaffebrenneri. I have to admit I had never heard of these guys before (part of the joy of the Kaffebox subscription) so was very much looking forward to giving them a go. Their website (in Norwegian) does not give much away but shows they took 3rd place in the Norwegian coffee roasting championship in 2018 and 2nd placce in 2020 - so a sign they know what they're doing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may recall with my Kaffebox subscription I dedicate one of the coffees to filter and one to espresso duties - this week the decision was made completely at random (so try not to read into any choices here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the filter side I opted for the Tanzanian &quot;JKT Itende&quot; - the cultivars appear to be N39, Bourbon and Kent (the latter being a variation on Typica that is more resistant to leaf-rust) and I believe the coffee is washed. Off the dry aroma I get berry notes mostly, it is fairly punchy but not an aroma bomb. As a filter the first thing I noticed was how clean the cup is (partly due to some particularly &quot;dirty&quot; cups in the preceeding weeks). The flavour profile consists of: blackcurrants/blackberries, apricots and good hit of honey sweetness. The cup is very sweet and juicy with just enough acidity to not be cloying. The mouthfeel is fairly thin and the aftertaste is quite intense but not particularly long-lived. It is not a super-complex cup of coffee compared to some, but it is certainly very enjoyable and it is easy to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have a Guatemalan &quot;Finca el Regalito&quot; - the cultivars are Caturra and Bourbon and again it is a washed coffee (I'm assuming &quot;vasket&quot; is &quot;washed&quot; in Norwegian). The dry aroma gives off a honey type quality, again it is punchy but there is not huge sillage. The roast level on this coffee is visibly very light which often equates to an espresso that is tough to dial in. That is not the case here however, it is suprisingly forgiving. For the past week I have been experimenting with the B-Plus screen (full review coming later) so was adjusting my grind and recipe quite often and I didn't end up with a single shot less than good. I found a 1:2.5 sort of range to be the best for this coffee with the temp at full whack. The flavour notes I pick up are dried fruits, baking spices, brown sugar and cocoa. It makes for a syrupy and sticky shot with very high levels of sweetness. The acidity is somewhat muted which makes it very easy to drink. Again not the most complex shot I've ever had but very enjoyable and easy to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall another good installment from Kaffebox - Austrått will definitely be one I'll keep an eye out for in future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we are taking a first look at the &quot;hot off the press&quot; album from Julian Lage: &quot;Squint&quot; - since this was released yesterday (11th June 2021) this will be a &quot;first listen&quot; review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/059-Squint/Squint.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Julian's second appearance on the blog, in a prior post we looked at &quot;Love Hurts&quot; which was quite a restrianed look at ballads and standards (mostly). &quot;Squint&quot;, Julian's first release on Blue Note Records, takes a different approach: it is wilder, more ambitious, more virtuosic, freer and features (mostly) original compositions.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Jx_CuxesjmU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

I have been a fan of Julian's playing for a long time, what really impresses me is his fluidity and ease over the instrument. Listening/watching Julian it never seems like he is trying particularly hard, the guitar just seems an extension to his body and there's no blocker in the &quot;brain-guitar&quot; pathway. Sure, you might be able to find those with more technical &quot;chops&quot; but few seem as comfortable playing the instrument. This means that even when playing technically or harmonically complicated pieces he is still able to have &quot;feel&quot; and tell a story through his playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Squint&quot; is also the first recording to feature Julian's new signature Collings 470JL (I believe - at least the first since the guitar has been available) - based around a Gretsch duojet style guitar it marks a depature from the telecaster (or technically nachocaster) he has been known for. The change in tonality is quite evident - there is certainly more of a nasal quality to the break-up sounds and the cleans are a bit cleaner. He has also (in places) opted for more reverb and tremolo than in the past. Personally I'm more a fan of the telecaster sound, but even so then tones on &quot;Squint&quot; are still better than 99% of jazz electric guitar sounds out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the choice cuts on the album include the opener: &quot;Etude&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). As the name would suggest this is a solo guitar piece, somewhat designed as a technical &quot;practice&quot; piece. At a relatively short 2m27 it still packs a lot in - it could take a blog post in itself to analyse everything here. The main &quot;theme&quot; takes cues from Bach and classical music more generally, but this is blended with voice-leading jazz, blues and even the odd rock accents. The walk-down just after the main melody is a mind-bending lick, the use of open strings in such a line is just crazy. Watching him play you would be forgiven for thinking he was playing something trivial, it's honestly quite disheatening for the guitar players out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a solo record however and Lage is joined by Dave King on drums and Jorge Roeder on the bass. The whole album has an intimate almost &quot;jazz club&quot; feel and comes across a bit like a live performance - owing to the interaction between the musicians. This is particularly apparent on the track &quot;Familiar Flower&quot; (above) which is one of the freer pieces on the album and takes clear nods from Ornette Coleman. A part of Julian's playing that really comes out here is how easily he can switch from the most outside free ideas to more inside groove-based playing. It never feels like he's playing outside &quot;for the sake of it&quot;.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y10ZbXSW1Go&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Two other tracks I want to make a note of: firstly the revisiting of &quot;Day and Age&quot;, a track that appeared on his 2015 album &quot;World's Fair&quot;. On the previous album it appeared as a solo acoustic piece and became a bit of a &quot;signature tune&quot; for Lage. On &quot;Squint&quot; we are treated to an electric trio version - it takes on a whole new personality, slightly more downbeat and contemplative (perhaps reflecting a change in Julian's personality in the 6 years between recordings). Undoubtedly there will be comparisons to Bill Frisell given the &quot;Americana&quot; vibe to the piece but Julian certainly has his own voice here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other track I want to highlight is the beautiful rendition of Johnny Mandel's &quot;Emily&quot;. Julian released a video playing a solo version of this tune during the start of lockdown last year (video above). This is one of my favourite ballads and Julian's version is up there with my favourite renditions. I think as a guitarist one of the hardest tasks to do is to play a &quot;simple&quot; ballad like this and keep it entertaining yet respectful to the source, many others would have layered reharmonization over reharmonization to the point of being unrecognizable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tunes selected here are some of my initial highlights but &quot;Squint&quot; is full of gems. &quot;Boo's Blues&quot; for example being a swinging blues with a hint of Monk to it. Although there isn't really a &quot;lead single&quot; to this album, perhaps the most accessible is &quot;Saint Rose&quot; (below) - if this doesn't become a staple of Julian's live shows from now on I'll be very surprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &quot;review&quot; just reflects my intial impressions after a few listens of &quot;Squint&quot; - I'm sure there's much more to uncover hidden away in these tracks. I'd strongly suggest tracking down a copy and giving it a go.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v21st5PcUOU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/059-Squint/Squint.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/059-Squint/Squint.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sound of Summer Running and Koppi</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/summer-running-koppi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sound of Summer Running and Koppi" /><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Summer-Running-Koppi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/summer-running-koppi">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-05-29-Summer-Running-Koppi.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/l8iNkhmoALs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This blog post marks the next installment of my KaffeBox subscription. This time it features another of my favourite roasters: Koppi - located in Helsingborg, Sweden. They are perhaps one of the best known of the Scandinavian roasters and are highly acclaimed (and for good reason). I beleive they are also the originators of &quot;coffee tonic&quot; - a shot of espresso poured into a chilled tonic water with ice. With summer &lt;em&gt;potentially&lt;/em&gt; around the corner it is a great choice for a drink on a hot day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may remember my KaffeBox subscription consists of 2 bags each of 125g of coffee. I split these one on espresso duty and one on filter duty, so that I get enough to dial in the espresso properly. This week I selected based on origin, I went for the origin I typically find easiest to dial in for the espresso and the other for the filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with the filter we have a Colombian coffee &quot;Finca El Prado&quot;. The cultivar is Caturra and the coffee has been wet fermented followed by a full wash and raised bed drying. Diving right into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma there is an unmistakable strawberry note to this coffee, but this plays supporting cast to a sugar-syrup or light caramel note. As you would expect the roast level is fairly light here. In the cup the strawberry meets many other red berries: redcurrants, raspberries, cherry, you name it. It's a very fruity cup. There is a sharpness there too, the bag lists passionfruit but I would describe it more as a tart raspberry quality personally. The cup has a medium body and is quite juicy in its quality. It is definitely more on the complex end of things and the various red fruits come to the forefront as it cools. As I would expect from Koppi: a really well executed and tasty cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have a Costa Rican &quot;La Lia&quot; - a Catuai cultivar that has been fully washed. I am a big fan of Costa Rican coffee in espresso, I find it to typically be extremely forgiving and it's very difficult to mess up too much. This is true of this coffee also, the grind setting needed major adjustment from my previous espresso so my first shot had a 60s pull time - it was still delicious, albeit very intense. After dialing in I settled for a normale shot: 1:2 in 28s. This seemed to be the best compromise between mouthfeel and clarity for me. In terms of flavour note the predominant note is nuts, in particular hazelnuts and almonds. Alongside there is a crisp apple type acidity that cuts through and a stone fruit note. Overall it is not the most complex espresso in the world but it is very easy to drink, it's a coffee for when you just want a coffee. Again the execution is top level and it is truly a top class espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside Koppi this week, since London has had its first glimpses of summer, I have been listening to the 1997 release from Marc Johnson: &quot;The Sound of Summer Running&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/058-Sound-of-Summer/Sound-of-Summer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marc Johnson is a name that might not be instantly recognisable to many, he is not a household name and hasn't really had many &quot;hit&quot; records under his own name. However his back catalogue speaks for itself, having featured on albums from: Bill Evans, John Scofield, Lyle Mays, John Abercrombie and Stan Getz (plus many more). Having such an illustrious side-man career has clearly influenced his playing where you can hear the aforementioned (along with others) heavily in his playing.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/skdwbRI2eXk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;The Sound of Summer Running&quot; (named after a Ray Bradbury story) is perhaps one of Johnson's best known recordings as a band-leader. Most likely due to the truly stellar cast of musicians on show:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marc Johnson – double bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Frisell – electric and acoustic guitars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pat Metheny – electric and acoustic guitars, 42-string Pikasso guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joey Baron – drums, tambourine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;dual guitar&quot; setup is likely to be influenced by prior work with John Abercrombie who often makes use of such line-ups. It is not often you get to hear 2 of the jazz guitar titans playing together. It is also rare to hear Pat Metheny play a supporting role, aside from a few obvious exceptions in his early career, he is typically in the &quot;limelight&quot;. On &quot;The Sound of Summer Running&quot; we see a different side to Metheny's playing that we don't often see. Then of course you have Bill Frisell, for my money one of the best guitar compers in the business. Hearing his interplay with Metheny is a joy on this album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the album is quite a restrained affair, it is not so much about huge chops or crazy harmonizations but more about creating a &quot;mood&quot;. While the Metheny and Frisell influences are on show it is really all about Johnson's voice as a composer: 7 out of 10 tunes being penned by him (with Frisell taking 2 of the remaining credits and Metheny 1). The &quot;Summer&quot; feel is quite clear throughout and it's an album that is very hard to dislike, it's a bit of a mystery why it is not more popular than it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some choice tracks include the opener &quot;Faith in You&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) which features a Metheny-ish main melody. The contrast in Metheny's and Frisell's solos is particularly interesting, Metheny being more at home but Frisell doing Frisell things. &quot;Union Pacific&quot; is another highlight (above) and perhaps the most &quot;straight-ahead&quot; with a strong swing and swagger. The main melody being played by Metheny and Frisell in unison is one of most memorable moments on the album for me and not something you get to hear very often.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/T8BESnWlzoo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

My last pick is the Frisell tune &quot;Ghost Town&quot; - one of his signature tunes. Getting to hear Metheny solo on this piece is a joy, the structure and changes are very far away from a typical Metheny tune so it is very interesting to see how he approaches it. Of course Frisell is right at home and works his magic on the tune. This version is as good as any of the versions on Frisell's own albums in my view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &quot;The Sound of Summer Running&quot; might not be considered &quot;essential&quot; listening by traditional standards, it is well worth hunting down a copy if you're after a no nonsense album that can fit into your day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/058-Sound-of-Summer/Sound-of-Summer.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/058-Sound-of-Summer/Sound-of-Summer.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Friday Afternoon in the Universe and Jairo Arcila</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/friday-afternoon-jairo-arcila" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Friday Afternoon in the Universe and Jairo Arcila" /><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Friday-Afternoon-Jairo-Arcila</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/friday-afternoon-jairo-arcila">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-05-22-Friday-Afternoon-Jairo-Arcila.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9zz-WKAlTvQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

On the blog this week we're heading back to Exeter and the folks at Crankhouse Coffee. A couple of weeks ago we looked at a rather elegant Ecuadorian cup from them, this week we are going much wilder with a coffee from Colombia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee is called Jairo Arcila Villarazo Natural (EF2) - the farm is located in Quindio and the cultivar is Castillo. The suffix EF2 refers to &quot;extended fermentation 2 extra days&quot;. As you may have guessed by now we're looking at a highly fermeneted natural coffee here. The process is described as: an initial 24 hours dry anaerobic fermentation. Following this the cherries are placed into bags and stored at 22 celcius (through use of a water tank) for an additional 60 hours. The cherries then dry on raised beds until an 18% moisture content before going back in the bags for 50 hours and dried on raised beds until the moisture is 10.5%. The sheer extent of the fermentation suggests this is going to be a very funky cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving right into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma you get that unmistakable &quot;natural funk&quot; - it always reminds me of black forest gateaux, bruised fruits and sherry. To me this is not a &quot;tropical fruit&quot; type natural/anaerobic - more of a deeper boozy sort of natural. I do not typically go for these sorts of coffees but it is always nice to mix things up every now and again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Served as a filter using my usual method: the first thing to note is that although this coffee is fairly high on the funk-o-meter it still has a good deal of clarity in the cup. The finish is long lasting but is fairly &quot;clean&quot; in nature. For me the major flavour notes are: bruised blueberries and cherry brandy. There is also an acidity that almost cuts through I would describe it as perhaps like a pink grapefruit, it is fairly subtle but it's just present enough to stop the cup being too cloying. As you'd expect the sweetness is very high and there is quite a lot of body - although it's not one you'll have to chew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso this coffee really shines. The sheer amount of sweetness means you can really cut back on the ratio to make the most of the mouthfeel. I found good results down to around 1:1.5 - knocking on the door of being a ristretto. In such a concentrated shot you get huge intensity and a luscious body, it almost feels like a dessert. Most coffees I tend to go for don't perform well as ristretto (in my opinion at least) so it is nice to come across one every now and again. The flavour notes are much the same as in the filter although the acidity disappears and the boozy notes are amplified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although outside of my typical coffee preferences I highly enjoyed drinking this one. It also goes to show the variety on offer at Crankhouse that you can have a super polite and refined washed Ecuadorian and this all-aboard-the-funky-bus natural Colombian from one roaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week it feels only right to go down the funky route. I have chosen an old favourite of mine: the 1995 release &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot; by Medeski, Martin and Wood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/057-Friday-Afternoon/Friday-Afternoon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've mentioned this a few times on the blog but Medeski, Martin and Wood (MMW) were one of the first jazz acts I got into heavily. Before them I had mostly been listening to the &quot;classics&quot; by (mostly) musicians who had passed long before I started listening to them. With MMW there was a band writing and performing new music who I could see live and I was all for it. They were also one of the first bands I can remember forming a new &quot;scene&quot;. They were pretty much the first of the 90s/00s wave of bands lugging wurlitzers and hammonds around gigs and managed to capture a &quot;cool&quot; younger crowd with live shows focussed on dancing and partying as opposed to the typical quieter and more respectful jazz audiences. This of course spun up many copy-cat acts trying to capture the same vibe but none felt as authentic as MMw.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b1-5jmuUkvM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Many years ago MMW were in fact one of the first acts I ever saw at Ronnie Scott's - but unfortunately it was not the best gig I've ever been to. Their setlist was pitfully short (max 30 minutes) and they didn't seem to be enjoying their time playing. It was quite a devastating gig given how much I was looking forward to seeing them live. Thankfully this was a one off and I saw them many times since and have not been disappointed (a gig with John Scofield was a particular highlight).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's interesting to see where &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot; sits within the MMW discography. Their first album &quot;Notes from the Underground&quot; does not feature the trademark organ sounds, it is a good album but does not &quot;feel&quot; like the MMW we know now. The second album &quot;It's a Jungle in Here&quot; begins to feature more organ sounds but is still heavily rooted in funk (of the Sly and the Family Stone type). Then came &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot; - here the organ sounds are expanded and the band started to play with the avant-garde. The avant-garde became a key component of the MMW sound, they would often switch from hard hitting funk to some of the most out there music in the blink of an eye. It's for that reason I consider &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot; the album were MMW hit their stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest &quot;hit&quot; off the album is &quot;Chubb Sub&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) - it showcases the MMW funk grooves in full swing. John Medeski providing the hip organ sounds, Billy Martin playing with the laid-back rock grooves and Chris Wood holding the whole thing together with some really restrained upright bass lines. Some of the MMW avant-garde craziness is shown on the short track &quot;House Mop&quot; (above) - despite being fairly free form there is still a sense of groove. The avant-garde is something they lent into heavily with their later work with John Zorn. You also have pieces such as &quot;Last Chance to Dance Trance (Perhaps)&quot; (below) - here the focus is more on dancing/partying with a heavy latin influence to the meter. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qxSFlooNldQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

With such a variety of tracks on &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot;, the album becomes a microcosm of both &quot;old&quot; and &quot;new&quot; MMW. It in some sense bridges the gap between much of their other work. It is an album I often find myself coming back to and one well worth hunting down if you have not yet heard it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/057-Friday-Afternoon/Friday-Afternoon.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/057-Friday-Afternoon/Friday-Afternoon.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Blues and Abstract Truth and Icon 5</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/blues-abstract-truth-icon-5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Blues and Abstract Truth and Icon 5" /><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Blues-Abstract-Truth-Icon-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/blues-abstract-truth-icon-5">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-05-15-Blues-Abstract-Truth-Icon-5.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/44DfWE0gatQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week marks the return of the Plot Roasting Icon series. As you may recall this a coffee subscription consisting of &quot;unobtainium&quot; type coffees - some of the rarest and most sought after on the market. This installment is no different; it features another Gesha coffee this time from Diego Bermudez in Colombia. You may recall this name from the Assembly limited edition coffee from a few weeks back - this time we have a Gesha cultivar however. As with the forementioned coffee this weeks Icon coffee undergoes a complex multistage process. First the cherries are washed with sterilised water to reduce contamination. The whole cherries are then held in sealed tanks for 60 hours at 18 celcius, they are then depulped before entering a second anaerobic fermentation phase for 36 hours at 18 celcius. The coffee then undergoes a &quot;thermal shock&quot; wash procedure; first washing at 35 celcius then 12 celcius. This is followed by a controlled drying procedure for 29 hours at 35 celcius with relative humidity 25% until the grain humidity reaches 10-11%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving right in to the coffee itself: on the nose I am getting honey and caramel notes off the dry aroma. Like many of the Gesha cultivar coffees I've had it is a relatively restrained affair and there is not a huge sillage. Moving onto the filter: the first thing to strike me is just how complex this cup is. There is so much going on in the cup. It actually benefits from being consumed at a relatively cool temperature, at the higher temperatures the flavours can overwhelm. In terms of flavour notes there are big perfumed florals: lavendar, violet, jasmine - you name it. Alongside are the typical earl-grey tea type notes one would expect also. I've also picked out stone fruit notes along with citrus (most notably grapefruit). The finish is very very sweet, reminding me of sherbet. This is a coffee to savour and ponder over each individual note, there is a lot to discover in this cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to a bit of a mix up I actually ended up with twice as much of this coffee as usual (300g) - which means for the first time I am able to try one of the Icons as an espresso. With a coffee this expensive it can be a little nerve-wracking to pull shots from, any sink-job dialing in shots are literally money down the drain! Fortunately however, this coffee required only minimal tweaks from the previous espresso I had been serving. I enjoyed this one at a 1:2.5 ratio in 28s with the machine temperature at full whack. As you'd expect this makes a great espresso too. There is one overriding flavour note I wrote down: Haribo Fangtastic sweets! There is a definite sourness to the espresso, but in a good way - not an indication of underextraction way. Especially paired with the syrupy sugar sweetness, it has a real &quot;sweet and sour&quot; thing going on which is really cool. I can't remember having an espresso with this sort of profile before so it was very enjoyable. That being said the complexity does get kind of lost so I do think filter is the best way to enjoy this coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet again Plot are killing it with the Icon series - very much looking forward to what the future brings with this subscription!

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SlkkQiZ-gV4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As is customary on Icon series posts: on the jazz side we are looking at an iconic album. This time around we are going back to 1961 on Impulse records: Oliver Nelson and &quot;The Blues and Abstract Truth&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/056-Blues-Abstract/Blues-Abstract.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oliver Nelson is one of the many jazz artists who died far too young at just 43 years old. It's perhaps for this reason his name is not as recognisable as others from his era. As a result &quot;The Blues and Abstract Truth&quot; is often an album overlooked by the jazz newbie who will not discover it until much later in their jazz journey (and kick themselves for not finding it earlier). To those in the know it is one of the most respected albums from the post-bop era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nelson is a saxophonist and clarinetist, on &quot;Blues&quot; he appears playing tenor and alto sax, however he is perhaps best known as a composer or arranger. &quot;The Blues and Abstract Truth&quot; offers a peek into his compositional sensibilities, with just a 7 piece band the tunes are not quite as expansive and experimental as some of his later works. He was also an acomplished composer outside of the jazz idiom having composed for classical and chamber groups along with TV and film scores. It would have been very interesting to see where he headed artistically had he had more time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lineup on &quot;The Blues and Abstract Truth&quot; is quite impressive in itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freddie Hubbard – trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eric Dolphy – alto saxophone, flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oliver Nelson – tenor saxophone, alto saxophone &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Barrow – baritone saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Evans – piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul Chambers – bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roy Haynes – drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A true superstar lineup, each more than worthy of a blog post in their own right. For me part of the charm of this album is the contrast in the soloing: Hubbard offering up his usual powerful exuberance, Nelson being more introverted and contemplative and Dolphy being Dolphy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;standout&quot; track on the album is the opener &quot;Stolen Moments&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) which has subsequently become a standard in its own right. With so many horns they are able to produce some very rich and wide reaching chord voicings that add to the overall feel of the piece. Perhaps the standout however is the flute solo by Dolphy - an integral part of the recording and highly memorable. Another Dolphy highlight is in the 4th track &quot;Yearnin&quot; (below) where he presents the most &quot;outside&quot; playing on the album with his solo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another standout piece (and one of my favourites) is the second track: &quot;Hoe Down&quot; (above), based on the theme from Aaron Copland's &quot;Rodeo&quot;. The genius of this track is that it sets you up thinking you're in for a corny American folk piece before descending into some of the finest post-bop soloing you'll ever hear. Hubbard's solo is the one that really stands out for me on this one.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0tNZ6AG0xWc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As with all the albums featured in the Icon series: this one is a &quot;must listen&quot; if you are a jazz fan. Be sure to pick up a copy through whatever medium you listen to your music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/056-Blues-Abstract/Blues-Abstract.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/056-Blues-Abstract/Blues-Abstract.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">XXXX and Galo Semlantes Finca Santa Rosa</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/xxxx-galo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="XXXX and Galo Semlantes Finca Santa Rosa" /><published>2021-05-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/XXXX-Galo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/xxxx-galo">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-05-08-XXXX-Galo.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_D_bUSS64W4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we feature a new roaster: Crankhouse Coffee - not a new roaster in general terms but a new roaster in terms of this blog. Crankhouse are based in Exeter and have been known for cranking out good quality and interesting coffees for many years. Unfortunately for them they are a roaster I often &quot;forget&quot; about and should really buy from more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee we're looking at today is &quot;Galo Semlantes Finca Santa Rosa&quot; it is an Ecuadorian, Typica Mejorado cultivar. We talked about this cultivar fairly recently in another post so we won't retread that ground again here. In addition to the origin/cultivar, which usually indicates a high quality cup, the processing of this coffee is intriguing. It is described as a &quot;washed double fermentation&quot;. After being picked/selected cherries are placed in sealed fermentation tanks for 48 hours until an exact pH of 4.1 is achieved. They are then pulped and placed in open tanks for another 48 hours until the pH reaches 3.7. The coffee is then fully washed and dried on African beds to reach a humidity of 11%. Finally coffee is left in bags for a month to stabilise. This is clearly a complicated and exacting process. It is definitely nice to see processing develop through the years, when I first got into specialty the processing was described as: &quot;left to dry in the sun, turning occassionally&quot; - quite a far cry from the scientific approaches adopted today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No amount of complex processing and exotic cultivars matter unless the quality in the cup is also good. So let's dive straight in. On the dry aroma I do not get a huge bouquet or sillage. There are pleasant caramel notes and a delicate florality to the nose but it is not a heavy hitter. This comes across as a very polite, refined and complex coffee - the exact style that I tend to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter I am reminded of a very specific product that likely nobody but me will remember: when I was very young there was a very sweet &quot;peach water&quot; that came in a frosted glass bottle. The intial flavour hit of this coffee is remarkebly similar to this. It has a sugary sweet syrupy taste and really delicate peach notes to it. There are also notes of sweet nectarine and a stick rosehip floral note also. This is kind of like an Ethiopian coffee with the volume turned up. The flavours are quite intense but still have a high level of clarity. It is a fairly &quot;linear&quot; coffee and the flavour profile doesn't really change much as the cup cools, this makes it very easy to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso: this coffee was one of the easier coffees to dial in. Fairly traditional recipes tend to work well with it and you can get some good syrupy mouthfeel out of it. The flavour profile is similar to the filter, but obviously much more concentrated. It's almost like a highly reduced necatarine syrup, extremely drinkable and in terms of pure flavour one of the most tasty. As an espresso some of the more interesting rosehip like florals get lost however, so it's not the most complex shot around, but there is a place for super tasty easy to drink espresso that does not require much brain power to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a good showing from Crankhouse and a good reminder that I should order from them more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we're going to take a first look at the new album &quot;XXXX&quot; from Wollny, Parisien, Lefebvre and Lillinger on the ACT record label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/055-XXXX/XXXX.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should probably start with fair warning: this is not an &quot;easy&quot; album to listen to. This one is comfortably within the avant-garde, free end of the spectrum. The music on show is almost entirely improvised (with the exception of one piece arranged by Wollny). It is very exploratory and pushes the boundaries, not something you would want to just &quot;put on in the background&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album is listed under the names of all 4 players on the record, with pianist Michael Wollny taking &quot;headline&quot; spot. Wollny is more known for his &quot;straight ahead&quot; sensibilities typically in piano trio and duo formats. I have not heard everything he has ever recorded but I believe this is his first foray into fully free froms. I have seen Wollny live a few times in the past and my reaction has always been: &quot;that was good, but it didn't move me&quot;. &quot;XXXX&quot; has certainly made me stop and take note. On the album he plays both acoustic, electric and synth instruments and there is extensive use of layering throughout. He definitely takes at least some inspiration from electronic and dance music and comparisons to Jean Michel Jarre instantly come to mind.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lRze7bfpFg0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Alongside Wollny are regular stable mates: Soprano saxophonist Emile Parisien and bassist Tim Lefebvre. You can tell that these guys are completely comfortable playing with each other. In a free structureless setting you have to be completely comfortable that your bandmates will get you out of trouble otherwise the whole project can become a disaster. There is often a misconception that playing free is &quot;easy&quot; and you just &quot;make stuff up&quot; - this is definitely not the case, as evidenced by the countless dreadful free projects that have spun up over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real driving force behind this album, however, is drummer Christian Lillinger. He brings such sheer energy to the music, it is almost impossible not to be swept up in it. He plays with such reckless abandon, but still manages to capture the right moment to bring the tempo down and when to sit out entirely. It is a truly incredible performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music takes many twists and turns it is almost impossible to cover everything. There are truly out there free jazz moments, followed by 70s rock-fusion, electronic dance music, heavy funk grooves and down tempo ballad like passages too. I find the album has almost a meditative or hallucinogenic quality even amidst the craziness. I'm clearly not alone in this since the cover-art features the chemical structure of psilocybin - the active component of magic mushrooms. It is an album best listened to start to finish as an entire piece so I have not mentioned individual tracks here (although you can find a few embedded in this post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this album is not one for everybody it is a truly fantastic achievement and a release I'm thoroughly enjoying. If you want to hear some original modern jazz there are far worse places to start than &quot;XXXX&quot;.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zcO77Q2bfVM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/055-XXXX/XXXX.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/055-XXXX/XXXX.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Genealogy and April Coffee</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/genealogy-april" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Genealogy and April Coffee" /><published>2021-05-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Genealogy-April</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/genealogy-april">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-05-01-Genealogy-April.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WKUlpo4qaLk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week  marks the next installment in the KaffeBox subscription series. The April installment features April Coffee Roasters (I see what they did there, very punny). April are a roaster based in Copenhagen, Denmark. They are a roaster I've wanted to try for a while but the shipping costs/times mean I rarely stray outside of UK based roasters and when I do I like to stick to roasters I know and love. I was therefore very happy to see April coffees arrive this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may recall my Kaffebox subscription consists of 2 different 125g bags of coffee each month (both roasted for filter). This is not enough to dial in both filter and espresso comfortably so I dedicate one to filter duty and one to espresso duty. This month I selected based on origin and what I tend to prefer for each coffee style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting off with the filter side of things we have a washed coffee from Ethiopia. It is from the Arsosala washing station in Guji, and what is interesting about this coffee is it is a Bourbon cultivar. Typically with Ethiopia you get &quot;heirloom&quot; or &quot;mixed landrace&quot; cultivars (although the specific cultivars are increasingly being identified). On the dry aroma I get caramel and candy notes along with the typical florals you would expect from a washed Ethiopian. In the cup we are treated to a very clean profile, it is refined and delicate. We have a very perfumed and floral cup with a lot of complexity that evolves as the temperature cools. Alongside we have lemon-y citrus notes and a sweet sugar-syrup vibe. The aftertaste and finish are extremely clean and fairly short lived, body is low and the acidity level is medium. It is a very good example of what a washed Guji Ethiopian should be, and the sort of coffee I can drink by the pint and still enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have a Costa Rican coffee from the Volcan Azul farm. The cultivar in question is H17 which is a hybrid cultivar. It is not one I am familiar with (I have had H3 a few times) and I can't find out many details about the exact genetic make-up. The coffee has undergone a yellow honey processing. This coffee has really blown me away as an espresso. I find honey processed Costa Ricans the most forgiving bean for espresso typically but this was a whole different level of forgiving - every single thing I tried was fantastic. It made choosing an &quot;ideal&quot; recipe next to impossible. In the end I just went to a regular 1:2 ratio so I could appreciate the thicker rich mouthfeel. The flavours on show were hazelnut, almond, honey, sugar-syrup and plum. It is not the most complicated coffee I've ever had but it is incredibly drinkable and enjoyable - it is just a great example of what espresso can be. Again like with the filter the coffee is very clean and the aftertaste is fairly shortlived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall 2 very strong showings from April, I'll certainly be on the lookout for coffees from them in the past. When I'm feeling flush I might splash out on some of their more exclusive Gesha offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side we are taking a first look at a 2021 release from Code Quartet - &quot;Genealogy&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/054-Genealogy/Genealogy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code Quartet are a relatively new project and &quot;Genealogy&quot; represents their debut which was released on April 23rd 2021. The band formed 4 years ago in Montreal, Canada. The idea behind the project was to explore &quot;chord-less&quot; music and they cite the Ornette Coleman groups from the 1950s as a primary influence. They also list the work of Fletcher Henderson, Charlie Haden and Paul Bley as influencing their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quartet is made up of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christine Jensen - saxophones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lex French - trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adrian Vedady - acoustic bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jim Doxas - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By forgoing instruments with the ability to play chords they open up many possibilities within the music. The roles of &quot;lead&quot; and &quot;rhythm&quot; players become a little harder to define and it becomes more about the interplay between instruments. On this particular project there seems to be around a 50:50 split between the compositional and improvisational aspects and it is evident that the musicians are very comfortable playing with each other, this allows them to take plenty of risks and push the boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the influences listed above the opening track &quot;Tipsy&quot; (embedded at the start of the post) sounds more like a tune you'd hear on a Hank Mobley record than an Ornette Coleman one, but this is no bad thing. The focus of the tune is the funky-soul jazz swing. Jensen taking a tasty Rollins inspired solo part way through. It is not the most complex or original piece you'll ever hear but it is a style that you don't hear explored much anymore so it is a nice surprise to open the album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yELcAAU_p40&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Perhaps the most complex piece on the album is &quot;Wind Up&quot; (above), here the band strays more into the Coleman inspired &quot;free&quot; style. The tune is based around quite a complicated rhythmic figure but Doxas manages to keep things grooving and it doesn't sound like a &quot;music degree show piece&quot; like many modern jazz pieces do. Over the top we have a twisting harmonic idea which shows the Jensen-French interplay off to full effect. Each player manages to serve the music and each other but there is still a sense of individual expression: Jensen going for a wilder outside staccato playing style while French sticks to more inside flowing legato ideas. The contrast works well together and it never feels like a &quot;jam session&quot; comprised of a random set of musicians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really makes this album interesting however is the sheer variety of music on show. The two tracks listed above are very different but share the same &quot;DNA&quot;. This is echoed throughout the entire album - we have the (very clearly) Coleman influenced title track which would have fit right in on a 50s album from Ornette. Alongside we have the more angular modern jazz influenced &quot;Watching It All Slip Away&quot;. The track &quot;Day Moon&quot; feels like it was inspired by &quot;Tijuana Moods&quot; era Charles Mingus and the album closes with &quot;Beach Community&quot; which has a Carribean-lilt which shows more than a passing resemblence to the Rollins classic &quot;St Thomas&quot;. The quartet covers quite a wide variety of jazz history in just the 51 minute play time of the album, however do not think of this as a &quot;covers band&quot; - there is a very definitely &quot;Code Quartet&quot; sound on show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this is a strong debut album. It is definitely a little &quot;rough around the edges&quot; in places but this kind of adds to its charm. Unlike many modern jazz offerings they do not let perfection be the enemy of the good. &quot;Code Quartet&quot; will definitely be a group I'll keep an ear-out for in the future as this debut shows a lot of promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/054-Genealogy/Genealogy.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/054-Genealogy/Genealogy.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">All Kooked Out and Diego Bermudez</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/all-kooked-out-diego-bermudez" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All Kooked Out and Diego Bermudez" /><published>2021-04-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/All-Kooked-Out-Diego-Bermudez</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/all-kooked-out-diego-bermudez">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-04-24-All-Kooked-Out-Diego-Bermudez.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/67U65RIWlog&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are looking at another &quot;limited edition&quot; coffee - this time from the Brixton based Assembly Coffee Roasters (one of this blogs favourite roasters). Assembly do not release &quot;limited&quot; coffees very often (I believe this is only the 5th or so they've ever offered), so expectations are high for this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is from famed Colombian producer: Diego Bermudez. Widely regarded as one of the best producers for &quot;experimental processing&quot; in the world. They are really pushing the boundaries of coffee processing with meticulous attention to detail and a careful approach. They are based in El Tambo, Cauca - located in the south-west corner of Colombia slightly towrards the border with Ecuador.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is of Castillo cultivar, in its lineage there are some robusta-arabica hybrids which made Castillo a bit of a &quot;controversial&quot; cultivar in the past with the specialty movement. This seems to have largely died down now however and people are appreciating the quality in the cup - typically considered on par with Typica, Bourbon, etc. The really cool part of the Castillo cultivar however is its resistance to leaf rust, a growing concern for global coffee production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing that makes this coffee special however is its processing. Whole cherries are fermented anaerobically for 48 hours at a strict 18 degrees celcius. Following this cherries are de-pulped and they go back in to anaerobically ferment for another 48 hours, this time at 20 celcius. The coffee then undergoes a &quot;thermal shock&quot; washing process whereby an initial washing at 40 celcius occurs, followed by a much cooler 12 celcius wash. The resulting beans then undergo a temperature controlled drying at 35 celcius until the moisture level reaches 10-11%. This is a really complicated multi-stage process so it is understandable that this is a higher priced &quot;limited&quot; coffee, the question is: does it make a difference in the cup?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start by looking at the dry aroma: this coffee is a bit of a &quot;fruit bomb&quot;. The aroma is incredibly sweet and there are tropical fruits aplenty - pineapples, papaya, passionfruits, honeydew melon and a fair few more. Certainly an enticing start to this coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving over to the filter: again the sweetness is evident. It has an almost sugar-syrup quality both in terms of sweetness but also body which is quite big for a coffee roasted so lightly. Again the main flavours of note are the punchy tropical fruits: passionfruit is listed as a taste note on the label and it's hard to disagree with that really. I would add that there are floral background notes to this one too, it's not a perfumed Ethiopian but in the aftertaste there are certainly hints of lavendar. The cup is extremely complex and takes on a number of different characters as it cools, there's a stage where the tropical fruits give way to more &quot;traditional&quot; plum and raspberry type notes which is a nice surprise. In terms of acidity I would say this is at the mid-high end of things, and despite such a &quot;heavy&quot; processing the cup remains clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the espresso I found this coffee a little finnicky to dial in. It is prone to being a little too sharp and acidic unless you nail the grind size. Once dialed in however it is a delight. I settled on a med-high heat level on my machine, a 5s pre-infuse followed by a 24s pull aiming for a ratio of 1:2.2 was what I settled on. By going a little shorter than one might expect with a filter roast left the syrupy mouthfeel in tact and the coffee has enough sweetness that there's no need to go any longer. Again the tropical fruit salad was the major flavour profile and the sweetness was very very high. Once dialed in a very enjoyable and drinkable espresso and one I'm sad to see the back of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all another knockout coffee from Assembly, hopefully they can bring us many more interesting limited editions to wrap our tastebuds around!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week the magic of &quot;shuffle&quot; reminded me of a fun album from 1998 - Stanton Moore's debut album &quot;All Kooked Out&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/053-All-Kooked-Out/All-Kooked-Out.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stanton Moore may not be a name you have heard often before - at least if you're on this side of the atlantic. He is a drummer from New Orleans who is very much a part of the scene over there. He has a few recordings under his own name and as part of groups &quot;Galactic&quot; and &quot;Garage A Trois&quot; - each featuring a &quot;jazz funk meets jam band&quot; sort of vibe. In the late 90s through mid 00s the &quot;jazz-funk-jam&quot; thing was a fairly big scene thanks to the likes of Medeski Martin and Wood. In recent times Stanton has also become a drum educator.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZEcZy2gRsK0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

On &quot;All Kooked Out&quot; Stanton is joined by two musicians who he worked with previously through the &quot;Galactic&quot; group: 8 string guitarist Charlie Hunter and saxophonist Skerik. There are others rounding out the lineup but the real highlight of the album is hearing these 3 work together. The album was recorded in a week long session in a &quot;live&quot; style: there were no overdubs, they just play through the tunes. I really enjoy recordings done this way as you can hear the players excitement and energy come through, with too many edits the soul can be sucked from the music - especially for &quot;funk&quot; styles which are more about attitude than perfection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlie Hunter is likely the &quot;biggest name&quot; on this album. During the 2000s he became somewhat of a &quot;poster boy&quot; of jazz guitar, he is known for playing 8 and 7 string guitars that are in some sense &quot;hybrid&quot; guitar and bass. This allows him to play basslines, chords and melodies simultaneously giving him plenty of freedom in composing and improvising. I have to admit I never got as &quot;into&quot; Hunter as many people are, I can appreciate his talent and ability but I don't often dig out his records to listen to. On &quot;All Kooked Out&quot; however he is a perfect fit, he has some great funk chops and the interplay with Stanton is great throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skerik really adds another dimension to this album. He is listed as playing: &quot;saxophonics and kookification&quot; on the album - the latter being a good descriptor. By combining his saxophone with various electronics and effects he is able to provide some &quot;other worldly&quot; sounds to the album. This elevates the album from being just another &quot;jazz-funk&quot; album to something a bit special. A lot of what sticks in your mind from this album is Skerik's contributions - at least for me. It is not just a bunch of &quot;tricks&quot; though, he provides some really musical solos throughout too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with the track &quot;Tchfunkta&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) - which sets the tone for the rest of the album. As the name suggests it is based around a funk groove driven forward via Stanton's drums, Charlie's heavily chorused guitar (which admittedly sounds a bit dated now) dances over the top and the flourishes are added by Skerik. This is largely the formula throughout the album. One of the more interesting pieces is &quot;Stanton Hits the Bottle&quot; (above) - where Stanton literally hits the bottle rather than his drum kit for the percussion track. A cute idea, a fun play on words and a rather good track in its own right.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OvyqNwzj3XM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;All Kooked Out&quot; is unlikely to be an &quot;earth shattering&quot; album that will completely change your views on jazz. However it is an easy album to listen to and is certainly enjoyable. It is worth hunting down if you have not heard it before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/053-All-Kooked-Out/All-Kooked-Out.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/053-All-Kooked-Out/All-Kooked-Out.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rubber Soulive and Andrea Cortes</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/rubber-soulive-adreas-cortes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rubber Soulive and Andrea Cortes" /><published>2021-04-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Rubber-Soulive-Adreas-Cortes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/rubber-soulive-adreas-cortes">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-04-17-Rubber-Soulive-Adreas-Cortes.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rbE8A4U-OAI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are looking at another coffee from Plot Coffee Roasting. I initially did not intend to write about this coffee on the blog, I was keeping it as my &quot;espresso option&quot; while enjoying the Icon Series 4 from last week's blog. However 2 things forced it up the agenda: 1) it is a cool and interesting coffee and 2) I need a bit more time to dial in the next coffee I am going to write about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee this week is called: Andreas Cortes - Pink Bourbon by Plot themselves. Andreas being owner of Finca Eucaliptos in Pitaltio, Huila, Colombia - where this coffee originates. By this point you'll also realise we're looking at a pink bourbon cultivar. Pink bourbon is a hybrid of the more common red and yellow bourbons (named after the colour of their fruit). This hybrid is hard to grow and hard to isolate so it is relatively rare. It is noted, however, that it generally offers high cup scores and has shown good (or at least better) resistance to leaf rust - which is of course a big bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself undergoes a 24 hour resting period before being de-pulped and fermented for 60 hours in sealed bags before being fully washed and dried on patios for 18 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving straight into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I don't get a huge amount of anything coming off. I would describe it mostly as a &quot;neutral sweet&quot; quality, like opening a bag of caster sugar. With a bit more focus you can just about pick off some citrus and floral notes but they are very feint. As we've stated many times before: this doesn't necessarily mean much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the filter option: forewarning here - I only had 1 cup of filter from this coffee, so these are genuine initial responses. The first thing I jotted down with this coffee was &quot;clean&quot; - not just due to flavour clarity but profile too. There is a big citrus-y hit in the front, pink grapefruits and lemons mostly. These give a very clean quality to the cup. Following that I get a bit of a resin-y pine-needle sort of quality, again giving a fresh and airy vibe to the cup. In the aftertaste there are delicate floral notes that, while not particularly strong, do have staying power. In terms of sweetness vs acidity - for me it lies a little more to the acidic side but there is a plenty of sweetness in this cup too. The mouthfeel is quite big, adding to the resin-y pine-needle note I mentioned previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my time with this coffee has been via espresso - to me this is where this coffee is right at home. Dialling it in is a little finnicky, it is a light roast designed for filter primarily, and you need to whack the machine temp right up (one day I forgot to do this and left the machine cool from a dark decaf roast I was drinking the previous night - it did not work well with this coffee at all). In terms of ratio I got to about 1:2.25 as a sweetspot, 7s pre-infuse then a 27s pull. The results are outstanding. The shot is extremely vibrant and zingy, sort of like a very crisp lemonade with a big slice of pink-grapefruit in it. I could see some people despising this as an espresso for being too acidic and bright but I enjoyed it a lot. While it's bright and crisp it doesn't stray into &quot;battery acid&quot; territory at all for me. Even when I didn't nail it when dialing in the results were just a bit flat as opposed to being a sink job. The margin between fantastic and average with this one are quite fine though I found, it took me a few shots to really get things where they needed to be - but then I was handsomely rewarded for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I dug out a record from 2010 from the band Soulive, in the form of their tribute to The Beatles: &quot;Rubber Soulive&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/052-Rubber-Soulive/Rubber-Soulive.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit I was late to the Soulive party. The band started by releasing their debut EP in 1999 with their debut LP coming a year later. I knew of them around the mid-2000s but didn't really give them much attention at that time, Medeski Martin and Wood were more my thing so I was pretty big on them. It wasn't until the late 2000s when I really became aware of them. I was working on a new musical project at the time and the bassist of the band lent me a pile of CDs of his biggest influences - a couple of these were Soulive records, and I became to realise what I had been missing out on.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wXGwagOpjQs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As you could likely guess from the name: &quot;Soulive&quot; are largely in the &quot;Soul Jazz&quot; mold. They tend to have catchy, uptempo tunes that span jazz-soul-funk-rock. They have experimented (a lot) with additional musicians and vocalists over the years but the core of the band is an organ trio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alan Evans - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neil Evans - Organ/Piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eric Kranso - Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is the lineup featuring on &quot;Rubber Soulive&quot;. They rip through 11 tunes from The Beatles back catalogue, sticking solely to the &quot;big hits&quot; rather than finding the more obscure tracks. As you would expect from a jazz-funk band the focus is well and truly on the groove, if you're looking for a complex re-harmonization of Lennon pieces this is not the one for you. But if you want a groovy jam-band party atmosphere and some familiar melodies you could do a lot worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my choice cuts on the album is &quot;Revolution&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). Likely everybody will be fairly familiar with this track already so it is not easy to take it in a new direction. The Soulive boys decided instead of leaning into the strong rock-beat of the original they would take it into an RnB direction with a Booker T and the MGs style groove. If you can get through this tune without tapping your feet you are a better man than I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fun track on the album is &quot;Help&quot; (above). Here Soulive go for a tongue-in-cheek swing feeling, almost with a lounge-jazz vibe. As the track goes onthe energy increases and by the end Alan is using a really strong and driving drum beat. The whole track is a lot of fun but also features some rather tasty organ playing from Neil. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jZsKLJIyeU8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Of course the greatest of all The Beatles is George Harrison and there are 3 of his tunes covered on this album. Perhaps the most adventurous of these being the album closer: &quot;While My Guitar Gently Weeps&quot; (above). A tune that has been covered to death at this point, with basically every guitar player having played it at some point. It is therefore quite difficult to come up with a &quot;fresh&quot; take on it, but I feel Soulive achieve that here. They stick pretty closely to the original melody and harmony throughout. Instead adding colour through groove and timbre. Some of Eric's phrasing in particular is very tasty, as are the tasteful use of effects which add rather than detract from the piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a fun little album to check out. It's not one that will require a great deal of effort to listen to, just an easy &quot;feel good&quot; sort of album. Not all jazz need be complicated and require a great deal of effort to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/052-Rubber-Soulive/Rubber-Soulive.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/052-Rubber-Soulive/Rubber-Soulive.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">In N Out and Icon 4</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/in-n-out-icon-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In N Out and Icon 4" /><published>2021-04-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/In-N-Out-Icon-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/in-n-out-icon-4">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-04-10-In-N-Out-Icon-4.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/k8ntRkcOG-4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This coming friday (16th April) marks the first anniversary of the JazzCoffeeStuff blog! Unintentionally this coincides with another special coffee from Plot Coffee Roasting through their Icon series. As you may remember the Icon series is a &quot;150g a month&quot; subscription offered by Plot featuring some of the most sought after and rare coffees availavle. This is the 4th edition of this series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question is from Ecuador, an origin that may not be familiar to some. Most think of cacao rather than coffee from Ecuador, but those familiar with the specialty coffee scene know that there are some fantastic coffees to be had. Perhaps what is most interesting about this coffee is the cultivar: Typica Mejorado. I admit that I don't think I've ever tried this particular cultivar before, apparently a cross between Bourbon and an unknown Ethiopian landrace. Certainly an intriguing proposition given the cup quality of both of these cultivars. Interestingly, doing some research a few sources claim that it is a cross between Bourbon and Gesha - but this seems to be speculative at best (although would likely help achieve a higher price for the coffee).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processing here is a natural. Ecuador has a fairly humid climate which makes natural processing problematic. This coffee undergoes a dry fermentation for 48 hours before spending 15 days in a solar powered drying chamber that exactly controls the coffees environment. Following this the coffee spends the rest of the time on raised African beds within a polytunnel. This sort of attention to detail at the processing stage is really what sets some of these super high scoring coffees a part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's just dive right in: on the dry aroma I get a strong punch of honey straight off the bat. In addition I get the sort of floral notes one would ordinarily associate with Ethiopian coffees. This coffee is off to a good start, as usual we move on to my usual pour-over - I'm currently still on Hario v60 papers instead of my usual chemex due to supply chain issues but have been appreciating the change. Taking the first sip immediately I'm struck by how sweet this coffee is, it is syrup-y sugar-y and honey-y. This is up there as one of the sweetest coffees I've had in a while, if you like sweetness it is one for you. In terms of flavour profile the honey-floral combo is certainly there - a hit of honey at the front which mellows to perfumed florals in the aftertaste. In the middle however it is a bit of a fruit bomb: strawberry is certainly present, apricots too, mangos and papaya make a bit of a showing. There is a lot going on in the cup, it is one that you should really sit down and savour but it is surprisingly easy to drink too. In terms of acidity I would describe it as low or at a push medium, there's so much sweetness it's kind of hard to notice the acidity in my opinion. The body is quite high but not one of those coffees that you can chew on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with previous Icon coffees I didn't make any espresso, next week's blog post should feature some espresso goodness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet again Plot knock it out of the park with their Icon series. 4 out of 4 bangers so far, and I am looking forward to next month's offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this friday marks the one year anniversary of JazzCoffeeStuff, on the jazz side I thought we should head back to the first artist featured: Joe Henderson with another of his Blue Note recordings &quot;In 'N Out&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/051-InNOut/InNOut.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before even getting into the music itself it is worth taking a moment to appreciate the album artwork. One of my favourite covers in the history of Blue Note, a near perfect example of the Reid Miles aesthetic. It still looks as fresh today as it did when the album was released in January 1965.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I make no apologies: I am a huge Joe Henderson fan. My love for his playing can be summed up in the title of this album: &quot;In 'N Out&quot; - for me nobody before or since has had the ability to walk the line between inside and outside playing. He has the ability to play the craziest free-jazz lines fit with the most pedestrian chord changes, and meanwhile play an absolutely pure and simple melody in the midst of a free-jazz frenzy. Sometimes he even can start a lick playing a blues and by the end be in the realms of avant-garde - and you don't even notice it. This is especially true for his playing on Blue Note around this period, you can pick up any record he appears on during this time and you'll be blown away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &quot;In 'N Out&quot; the supporting cast isn't too shabby either: on trumpet you have regular stable-mate Kenny Dorham, with whom Joe recorded many times - all of which magical. On piano we have McCoy Tyner - one of the true stars of the hard-bop era and again appears regularly with Joe. On the bass we have Richard Davis who has played on records spanning all of the sub-genres of jazz from bop to free. On the drums is Elvin Jones - possibly my favourite drummer of all time, he always finds a unique way of swinging and can only be described as a jazz legend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with the title track (embedded at the start of this post). It kicks off with a time-twisting hard-bop type melody with Joe and Kenny in unison (showing off their near telepathic communication). This is on top of a typical Elvin swing - his way of emphasing the beat gives the melody a hurried chaotic feeling. It doesn't take too long to get into Joe's first solo on the album. It features all the hallmarks of his playing: short stabby phrases, the unpredictable use of space, large intervals, ghost notes and trills. With so many &quot;tricks&quot; like these it's amazing at how well Joe can construct a solo, it's completely logical and flows from one idea to the next. McCoy then takes his turn, again sticking to his tried and tested use of fourths (mostly). Kenny then takes his turn with perhaps one of the most daring solos in his back catalogue. Typically you associate Kenny with the latin-influenced music and sticking fairly close to the melody but here he gets a little more experimental.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/78N6qHZdxYY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The album itself consists of 2 parts: the first 3 tracks being tunes penned by Henderson himself and the last 2 by Dorham. As one would expect the Dorham tunes feature a latin and bossa feel, in contrast to the hard-bop/free sound of the Henderson pieces. One of the Dorham pieces is &quot;Short Story&quot; (above).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Short Story&quot; is typical Dorham through and through but the personnel on this album takes it in a different direction. You have Elvin's drum beats adding a unique flavour to the latin piece. It would have been easy to just stick to the &quot;typical&quot; drum beats featured in latin jazz but Elvin's genius gives the piece a sort of rhythmic tension which can be released at any moment. You also have McCoy's &quot;modal chord&quot; style of comping which gives the piece an almost &quot;dream like&quot; feel. Then you have Davis' bass hook which is a real ear-worm. This sets the stage for the main soloists to show off their personality: Dorham sticks largely to the chord tones and stays inside, playing pretty phrases. In contrast Joe starts off well behaved but before long starts breaking out the wolf-notes and wild rollercoaster bop lines. The Henderson/Dorham partnership is something that will never get old, they just seemed to raise each other up every time they played together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one downside of &quot;In 'N Out&quot; is its brevity at just 5 tracks and around 38 minutes (reissues featuring an additional 9 minutes with an alternate take of the title track). In spite of this &quot;In 'N Out&quot; is an all time classic for me and one well worth your time to hunt down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/051-InNOut/InNOut.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/051-InNOut/InNOut.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Basra and Laura Nilva Paye</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/basra-laura-nilva-paye" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basra and Laura Nilva Paye" /><published>2021-04-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Basra-Laura-Nilva-Paye</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/basra-laura-nilva-paye">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-04-03-Basra-Laura-Nilva-Paye.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/390UPSAD0OI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are yet again visiting Plot Coffee Roasters - a near constant feature in the blog as of late. This time we have a rather neat competition winning lot from Peru. The lot is from Laura Nilva Paye located in the Puno department of the country. In terms of location this is the south easterly corner of Peru, close to the border with Bolivia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cultivar of this coffee is Bourbon. I have been reminded that my sloppy use of the word &quot;varietal&quot; is technically incorrect when referring to coffee. In layman's terms the difference between &quot;varietal&quot; and &quot;cultivar&quot; is the presence of human intervention - in coffee (essentially) all coffee plants have been selectively bred, hence they should be referred to as &quot;cultivar&quot; as opposed to &quot;varietal&quot;. This is something I often forget and end up referring to varietal but I'll try and be more precise in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plot label this coffee as a &quot;washed&quot; process, however looking into the details the coffee has been depulped and fermented for 20-24 hours before being washed. In that sense it is a little more &quot;honey&quot; than many washed coffees available. Following the washing stage the coffee is dried under shade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's not hang around but get straight down to business: on the dry aroma I get sweet caramel and peaches, but they are very feint. Overall the coffee doesn't have a huge bouquet when compared to others, but it is very appealling I have a sense this will be a coffee I'll like. As I've said before the dry aroma (or lack thereof) doesn't necessarily align with what ends up in the cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the filter; it is clear to see how much quality is in this cup. It is very clean and clear, every flavour is well defined. The first thing that hits me is the sweetness, it has a very sticky-sweet vibe like a really ripe peach or even a peach syrup. After the intial stone fruit hit subsides you're left with a stunning floral finish which is clean and long lasting. The notes from Plot say: &quot;a flavour profile more akin to Ethiopia than Peru&quot; and it is very hard to argue with that. In terms of acidity I would describe it as a medium, or it may be that all the sweetness just offsets it. Eitherway it is a very easy cup to drink but also has layers of complexity to keep you entertained. I find it's best enjoyed at a slightly cooler temperature, straight out of the brewer the flavours get a bit too muddled for my tastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto espresso: I found it basically impossible to get a bad shot out of this. You can basically pull it however you like, with any grind setting and it'll be great. I was without electricity for a day and even pulled a shot on my cafelat robot and it was perhaps the best shot I had. I love the robot as a manual espresso maker, but I struggle with the lighter filter roasts I favour for espresso because it is hard to keep the temperature high enough. No problem with this coffee though, it still extracted perfectly. I found most enjoyment pulling the shots a little shorter that 1:2 to get a more luxurious caramel mouthfeel. The flavour profile in the cup is pure condensed peach and apricot. It is like a shot of peach syrup, incredibly high sweetness, just enough balancing acidity and no harshness at all. As much as I enjoyed this coffee in a filter, for me it really shone as an espresso - up there with the best of the year so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we're heading back to a classic Blue Note recording from 1965 - &quot;Basra&quot; by Pete La Roca.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/050-Basra/Basra.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pete &quot;La Roca&quot; Sims is a drummer/percussionist - he is best known as a sideman having appeared alongside some of the all time greats: Sonny Rollins (Roca appeared albeit briefly on &quot;Live at the Vanguard&quot;), Joe Henderson (on &quot;Page One&quot;), Jackie McLean, Bill Evans, Sonny Clark and so on. He started his career however playing in latin bands, an influence that came through in his playing throughout his career. There are a few things interesting about Pete: firstly he despised the name &quot;La Roca&quot; - he came up with the moniker early in his career and it is how most people knew him, but he regretted it in later life. Secondly he was in some sense a &quot;part timer&quot; - throughout the 60s he made money as an NY taxi driver and later became a lawyer in the 70s returning to jazz just once after this.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3M1O7InNT14&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;La Roca&quot; only has 3 albums under his own name, and one of those was erroniously labelled as a &quot;Chick Corea&quot; album by the record label initially. It's for that reason I consider &quot;Basra&quot; to be a bit of an &quot;under the radar classic&quot;. I'm not a fan of labels like &quot;under the radar&quot; or &quot;underrated&quot; since they always bring out arguments of &quot;XXXX is less well known, so this isn't underrated&quot; eventually devolving into an excuse for showing how obscure ones musical tastes are. I consider &quot;Basra&quot; an &quot;under the radar classic&quot; however, because almost every &quot;experienced&quot; jazz fan I know loves the album but it will rarely (if ever) feature on a &quot;top 100 albums&quot; list and &quot;La Roca&quot; will never feature in a list of artists you &quot;have to hear&quot; - as a result this is an album that many do not discover until much later in their jazz journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what makes the album so special? Firstly the line up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pete &quot;La Roca&quot; - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Henderson - Tenor Sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steve Swallow - Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steve Kuhn - Piano
As with many Blue Note recordings from around this time: a true heavyweight line-up. But more than that: &quot;Basra&quot; features some truly explorative playing. It is not your typical &quot;hard bop&quot; album, the is a darker brooding attitude and vibe throughout. The players also lean into the avant-garde/free styles more than many other albums of the period. But more than that there are influences outside of the typical &quot;jazz&quot; paradigm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps most evident in the title track &quot;Basra&quot; (embedded at the start of the blog). A take on Middle Eastern classical music it is based around one chord and captures the &quot;meditative&quot; essence of the style. The &quot;blank canvas&quot; allows Joe to carve out any line he wants and it is some of the best lead playing you'll hear from Henderson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the firey &quot;Malaguena&quot; (above) which is a piece originally penned by Cuban composer Ernesto Lecuona (again &quot;La Roca&quot; tipping his hat towards the latin music he played in his early career.) Again Joe plays out of his skin and there are plenty of &quot;Henderson-isms&quot; throughout which is no bad thing. The piece manages to be energetic without being high tempo, the quartet masterfully keeps racheting up the tension as it goes on but somehow manages to swing. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/briljflpx2s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Basra&quot; also features the original recording of the Swallow tune: &quot;Eiderdown&quot; which later went on to be a Swallow signature tune and a standard in its own right. It is interesting to hear it in its &quot;original&quot; form here. It is perhaps the most &quot;straight ahead&quot; of all the tunes on the album and Swallow's bass keeps the tune driving forward in his own inimitable way. This is also one of the recordings shortly before Steve switched to electric bass entirely, so it is nice to hear him play with an acoustic instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all &quot;Basra&quot; is, in my opinion, one of the greatest recordings on Blue Note. Definitely hunt out a copy through whatever medium you use to consume your music. It is a shame we have so few records of &quot;La Roca&quot; under his own name, it would have been great to see where he would have taken his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/050-Basra/Basra.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/050-Basra/Basra.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>