<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-14T06:21:52-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Happening and Alasitas</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/happening-alasitas" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happening and Alasitas" /><published>2020-11-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-11-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Happening-Alasitas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/happening-alasitas">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-11-07-Happening-Alasitas.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y8psxWBFAEw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we feature another coffee from Drop coffee roasters in Stockholm. In order to make the shipping economical I had to order a few different coffees so they will appear for a few more blog posts yet! As I said previously they are one of my favourite roasters so this is no bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee this week is another &quot;premium&quot; one - we have another washed Gesha varietal, this time from Bolivia. Bolivian Gesha is a relatively new phenomena for me, if you recall earlier in the year I had my first experience of this from Gold Box coffee. Bolivian coffee is an interesting one for me, it is one of the first origins I got into when I was first starting out with specialty coffees. Back then HasBean had a number of great Bolivian offerings. Unfortunately the political landscape in Bolivia has made it a little difficult to get quality coffee from the region, but this appears to be slowly changing and this year I've noticed more and more Bolivians on offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular coffee comes from producers Pedro-Pablo, Daniela and Pedro Rodriguez with their Alasitas farm. Gesha is not a &quot;natural&quot; varital in Bolivia and so the Rodriguez family used seeds from the famed La Hacienda farm in Panama (the farm famed for popularising the Gesha varietal). The farm is located in famed coffee growing region Caranavi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the coffee itself. On the dry aroma I am getting mostly floral notes underlined with a caramel. It is not the most boisterous I've ever come across but neither is it a shrinking violet (ignore the pun). An inviting and intriguing coffee for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start by making a filter coffee, in much the usual way - you'll likely be bored of hearing about the technique/equipment by now. Taking the first sip my first thought was &quot;wow&quot; - this is truly an exquisite coffee. As you would expect from a Gesha it is subtle yet fragrant with a lot of complexity. The overarching flavour for me is peach iced tea, it has the juicy peachy quality, the sweetness but also the floral tea-like quality. As the cup cools there are waves after waves of floral notes: honeysuckle, lavendar, jasmine... basically think of any floral note and it will be there. It is really sensitive to temperature of the cup and it is constantly evolving. If you enjoy cup complexity and trying to work out flavour notes this is certainly one for you. The acidity is reasonable but not overbearing, the cup is definitely on the sweeter end. The mouthfeel and body are what I'd describe as &quot;juicy&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the espresso. To dial this one in I found that a med-high sort of temperature works best, for a ratio around 1:2.25 was the sweetspot - perhaps a little shorter than you would expect for a light roast filter coffee. For reference I was pulling this shot with a 5s pre-infuse followed by a 24s pull - a fairly &quot;standard&quot; espresso recipe despite being a filter roast. As an espresso everything great about the filter is just amplified. The mouthfeel gets juicier, the peaches get peachier and the florals really linger on the finish. As much as I loved it as a filter it is even better as an espresso!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This coffee is one I just couldn't get enough of, I was sad to see the bag come to an end. On the price scale it is certainly not cheap, but not quite at the price of the previous Gesha featured (and to be honest I prefer this one to that one - but both were fantastic). For my bank balance's sake I'll probably take a break from the Geshas for a while!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week I have picked another 2020 release. This one was released a few months ago (July) but I totally missed but it has been the soundtrack of my week since discovering it. The artist is Gerald Clayton and the album is called: &quot;Happening: Live at The Village Vanguard&quot;. His debut on the legendary Blue Note label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/029-Happening/Happening.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess the question is: why did this album pass me by for so long? I have to be honest here; Clayton is not somebody I follow religiously. He is (clearly) a great player but I just tend not to connect with his music as much as I do with other players. I have never seen him live under his own name however, perhaps if I saw him live that would have changed (hopefully I will get a chance soon). This album has changed my opinion somewhat and I'll be certain to follow a bit more closely in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you release an album called &quot;Live at The Village Vanguard&quot; you very quickly put a target on your back. Rightly or wrongly peopl will always compare your release to previous albums recorded there (for example Sonny Rollins, John Coltrane and so on). The Village Vanguard is the oldest continuously operated jazz club in the world (next on the list being London's own Ronnie Scott's). I have never had the opportunity to visit the Vanguard yet but it is somewhere I certainly plan to go to. Visually it is a fairly unassuming place, the room itself being essentially &quot;pizza slice&quot; shaped. But as with many of these old jazz clubs it has near perfect acoustics which makes it such a great venue and consequently why so many live albums have been recorded there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clayton can still be considered somewhat of a jazz &quot;up and comer&quot; at 36 years old, but given his &quot;child prodigy&quot; type background it does feel as though he has been around for a long time. In that time he has released 5 albums under his own name (including &quot;Happening&quot;.) And has also recorded and toured with artists such as Charles Lloyd, John Scofield, Roy Hargrove, Ambrose Akinmusire and Peter Bernstein among others. Certainly a well qualified CV for any modern jazz player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The band takes the form of a quintet with the personnel on this album being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gerald Clayton - piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logan Richardson - alto saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walter Smith III - tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Sanders - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marcus Gilmore - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a &quot;star studded&quot; line up full of veterans with loads of acolades - instead a band of relative youngsters trying to make an impact. This gives the album itself a lot of vibrancy and energy, it feels fresh without falling into the trap of being &quot;too modern&quot;. This album has a unique sound but at the same time it feels as though it could have been released any time from the 1950s through to today. This is something that is not easy to achieve.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lzQM_SVM7dM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The music itself is definitely in the &quot;post-bop&quot; universe with lots of twisting and turning rhythmic and harmonic devices used throughout. However in places it also borrows from the modal school and uses some &quot;fusion&quot; ideas (although there are no electric instruments on show here). When not flying at full speed there are also times when things are slowed down and you have time to catch your breath - here the influence of Bill Evans (another artist with a legendary Vanguard album) comes to the fore front. There are also nods towards latin and even hip-hop at times - like much modern jazz it is all about taking a wide variety of influences and trying to mash them together into something coherent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album spans 75 minutes while featuring just 7 tunes - so the band has a chance to really explore each one. 4 of the tunes are Clayton originals and 3 are standards including Ellington's &quot;Take the Coltrane&quot;, &quot;Body and Soul&quot; and Bud Powell's &quot;Celia&quot; - the latter 2 being presented in trio format (offering the sax players a well needed break!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &quot;highlight&quot; picks from the album are &quot;Rejuvenation Agenda&quot; (embedded at the start of this post), one of the Clayton originals. The main theme features some inter-twined sax lines and some really grooving drum work from Marcus Gilmore. The majority of the tune is made up of an extended piano solo from Clayton however. Here he shows off some great virtuosity but always respecting the tune, many of the new breed of jazz musician often forget this and just throw their chops at it. Another highlight is Ellington's &quot;Take the Coltrane&quot; (embedded above) which closes the album. It starts off with some Monk-like solo piano work before breaking into the tune proper. On this tune everybody gets a chance to take an extended solo and really stretch their legs. Each player seems to egg on the next to reach even higher heights. It essentially becomes a clinic on modern jazz improvisation. Again Gilmore's drumming is on point (and includes an awe inspiring solo) - some of the sax work really takes things to the next level. I guess this is fitting for a tune with &quot;Coltrane&quot; in the title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were looking for a representation of the current state of live jazz you could do much worse than pick up a copy of &quot;Happening&quot;. It is one that I have been enjoying throughout the week - I'll certainly keep more of an eye out for Gerald Clayton releases in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/029-Happening/Happening.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/029-Happening/Happening.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Valentine and Adola</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/valentine-adola" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Valentine and Adola" /><published>2020-10-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Valentine-Adola</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/valentine-adola">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-31-Valentine-Adola.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TJxURT1NGro&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with Drop coffee from Stockholm, who were featured last week on the blog. This time we are looking at a more &quot;reasonably priced&quot; coffee instead of a super expensive rare coffee. As is a trend on this blog it is a naturally processed coffee from Ethiopia. Again we are looking at the Guji zone within the Oromoia region - and yet again it is from a washing station owned by Israel Degfa's company. This blog might be becoming a bit predictable! The coffee takes its name from the washing station &quot;Adola&quot;. In addition to running the washing station Israel has also built a school in the local area so that the children can get an education, Drop offer an &quot;extra&quot; version of this coffee which includes a donation directly to the school. To be honest the &quot;extra&quot; cost to a bag of coffee is negligible (about £2.50 at time of writing) in the scheme of things so it is worth opting for this version in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike last week this coffee is one I could use as an espresso! In fact it was (mostly) what I was drinking as an espresso last week while using the Gesha as a filter. Usually I like to keep the same coffee on both filter and espresso as I like to see how the different characteristics come into play with each preparation method. For me it's rare I'll find a coffee that I love prepared one way but hate prepared another. I might prefer one to the other for a specific coffee but there's rarely a coffee that is only suited to one style. And as I have said multiple times on this blog I only ever opt for filter roasts or occassionally omni-roasts as I find these show off the coffees character most clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto the coffee itself. The first thing to notice is this is very light roast, one of the lightest I've had in a while. Grinding for filter on my handgrinder I could physically feel the difference in density compared to previous coffees. The dry aroma coming off the coffee is fairly subdued, there is a little natural processing funkiness and a bit of a floral note but that is about it. This is not a blow your socks off coffee on the nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the filter prepared in the usual way. the first thing that jumped out to me is the funk. If you're unsure of what I mean by &quot;funk&quot; - some natural coffees that have been left in their cherries for a long time essentially start to ferment and develop a flavour profile sometimes referred to as funk. Funk is almost like a &quot;gone off&quot; taste (but in a good way). For me I always associate the funky notes with 2 things: firstly bruised fruits (typically blueberry) and alcohol (particularly fortified alcohol). Adola is not super funky, but it is noticable - espescially if you're like me and don't tend to drink the funky stuff very often. With the funk I also get huge sweetness in the cup combined with the mouthfeel it gives a sticky syrupy kind of quality. In terms of flavour notes blueberry is the first thing that comes to mind. As the cup cools it totally transforms however and the tropical fruits come out to play - it actually reminds me of those old fashioned pineapple cube sweets. All the way through there is a background floral note that adds a lot of elegance to the cup. With this coffee you're also given a really long aftertaste which is great when the coffee tastes so good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you would naturally expect this coffee to be an absolute pig to dial in for espresso given how light the roast is but I actually found it surprisingly forgiving. As you would expect you want to whack up the temperature on your espresso machine to as high as it can reliably go and you want to pull longer shots. For a ratio something like 1:2.75 is a good place to start, I was pulling this one with a quick 3s or so pre-infuse then a 25s pull - so not super quick compared to some. As an espresso this coffee is truly fantastic. The sweet sticky syrupy quality from the filter just gets amplified and it's one of the sweetest cups you'll find. The funkiness is there but is not overbearing, combined with the florals it gives the cup elegance and keeps it interesting. The pineapple cube note is unfortunately nowhere to be found in the espresso but the long aftertaste is thankfully still there. This is a coffee I'd give to somebody unsure about lighter roast coffees for espresso, it is a slightly different experience to a more developed roast but I'd struggle to see how anybody could not find this delicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this is another fantastic coffee from Drop. I said it in my last post but I'll repeat it here: for my money Drop is in the truly &quot;elite&quot; level of coffee roasters. I don't think I've ever had a bad coffee from them, I just wish they were a bit easier to get hold of in the UK!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we're going to look at another relatively recent release (from August 2020). From the Blue Note record label it is Bill Frisell's latest: &quot;Valentine&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/028-Valentine/Valentine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill has appeared a couple of times on this blog but never with an album under his own name. I heard this album the day it was released and have been listening to it since. I am unapologetically a huge Frisell fan-boy so I have been a bit reluctant to feature this album on the blog - I wanted to make sure my fan-boy-ism wasn't causing me to overhype it. But after a few more listens I have come to the conclusion that it is actually that good and is up there with Bill's best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Valentine Bill is joined by regular collaborators: Rudy Royston on the drums and Thomas Morgan on the bass. Although Bill has recorded with countless musicians in the past for his own projects he seems to have a small &quot;inner-circle&quot; with whom he collaborates regularly. I think this is an important part of the magic of some of his recordings/performances since it is very much focussed on interaction and intimacy between band members. In his post-ECM recordings he tends to take relatively simple tunes and elevate them to new levels. Often re-recording the same few tunes in different ways on his various projects. This is in some sense similar to Thelonious Monk who also had a relatively small repertoire but continually re-invented them (unlike say a Duke Ellington who wrote many pieces). Bill is in some sense similar to Monk in other ways too; he often focusses on rhythmic ideas and creating space when playing, and of course he has a history of playing Monk tunes with the Paul Motian band(s) earlier in his career. On this album the title track &quot;Valentine&quot; is quite clearly “an affectionate wink to Thelonious Monk&quot; (to use Bill's own terms) with its twisting time signatures, angular melody and humorous motifs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track list will be familiar to the more seasoned Frisell fan. It features &quot;Winter Always Turns to Spring&quot; featured on &quot;Ghost Town&quot; and &quot;Levees&quot; from the Great Flood documentary. Along with familiar pieces such as &quot;What the World Needs Now&quot; and &quot;Baba Drame&quot; (off &quot;The Intercontinentals&quot;) which he has done renditions of in the past. This habit of re-visiting pieces is very interesting as it allows us to see how Bill has matured and evolved over the years and it invites comparison. Often he will entirely re-work the piece for a new format so it never just feels like re-treading old ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album closes with the civil rights anthem &quot;We Shall Overcome&quot; (another tune that Bill has played many times in the past). This is embedded at the start of this blog, along with a great piece of animation in the music video (I would suggest watching it in its entirety at some point). In this version he sticks very closely to the melody and remaining faithful to the tune itself. Given the civil rights issues in the recent past it feels as though this was intentional. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zU0HS4aMqBg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The latter part of the album features many tracks that seem aimed at the current world landscape: &quot;Winter Always Turns to Spring&quot;, &quot;We Shall Overcome&quot;, &quot;Where Do We Go?&quot; and a beautiful rendition of Bacharach's &quot;What The World Needs Now&quot; (embedded above is a live version from a recent socially distanced outdoor gig). The track titles combined with the dream like quality to the arrangement appears to be Bill's attempt at fostering hope going forward. He is not an artist you'd associate with making political statements typically but I guess that is what he is trying to do with &quot;Valentine&quot;. Perhaps his recent work with Charles Lloyd, who is relatively outspoken, has rubbed off on him?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any writing I do about the music on this album will not do it justice, if you have heard any recording of Bill's from the past 20 years or so you'll know what to expect. This is not a particularly &quot;groundbreaking&quot; album but more of a solidification of the style built up over the past years. It is one of the most complete and polished offerings in the Frisell cannon so is well worthy of your time. The interplay between Frisell/Thomas/Royston is something to behold, it can easily go over your head the first few times you hear them but once you really start to pay attention you can see how well they work as a unit. There is no &quot;flashiness&quot; here just good solid performances all round. As it's incredibly rainy in London right now, I'd definitely recommend the album for some rainy afternoon listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll end with a funny story I have about Bill: a few years ago I saw him live when he was touring the &quot;Guitar in the Space Age&quot; album where he was revisiting tunes from his childhood. It is probably the most &quot;pop&quot; or radio friendly album he has released. I was in the front row and sat next to a party of Americans visiting London. Those who know Frisell know that in addition to the &quot;pop&quot; style recordings on this album he also has his &quot;weird Bill&quot; mode where he uses effect pedals to create crazy sounds and feedback. At the end of one of the pieces you could see Bill get a grin across his face and he bent down to adjust some effect pedals and treated the audience to 60s or so of crazy oscillating feedback and noise (I guess he got a bit bored playing simple melodies every night). At the interval I heard the American party talking to each other saying: &quot;It was a shame about the technical issues with his guitar at the end of that tune&quot;... I'm sure Bill would have found that amusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/028-Valentine/Valentine.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/028-Valentine/Valentine.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Live at Town Hall and Doña Daisy</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/live-at-town-hall-dona-daisy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Live at Town Hall and Doña Daisy" /><published>2020-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Live-At-Town-Hall-Dona-Daisy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/live-at-town-hall-dona-daisy">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-24-Live-At-Town-Hall-Dona-Daisy.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cd5rGoDqTyE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week we take a bit of a different turn with our coffee. We are for the first time stepping away from roasters located in the UK and moving our sights to Sweden. In particular we are looking at Drop Coffee Roasters located in Stockholm. This has been one of my favourite roasters for many years but getting their coffee to the UK is often expensive (as is true with most of the Scandi roasters). I noticed they had a &quot;free shipping&quot; offer however so wanted to make the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the coffee itself is a bit different for this blog too. In browsing the online shop for which coffees to purchase this one jumped out at me. It was a bit expensive so I had my doubts but thought it had been a while since I bought a higher end coffee so went for it. Unfortunately it wasn't until I had ordered that I noticed it was a half-bag size instead of a full-bag size. So what was initially &quot;a bit expensive&quot; turned out to be &quot;very expensive&quot;! So this will be by far the most expensive coffee featured on this blog so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is from San Jose in Central Valley, Costa Rica. The farm is called Finca Don Pepe and the coffee is called Doña Daisy. The farm is a result of a partnership between Daisy and Pepe Fallas who decided to grow coffee in their garden relatively recently - this is not a coffee from a big farming conglomerate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you'd guess from being an expensive coffee (at this level) we are looking at a Gesha varietal - something we have talked about previously in the blog. Gesha is finnicky to grow and finnicky to work with, it requires absolute attention at every stage to get the most out of it. I can't recall seeing a Costa Rican Gesha before this so it is interesting to see how it behaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processing on this coffee is listed as a natural process by Drop but is described more as a &quot;white honey&quot; process in their literature. We have talked about Honey/Pulped-Natural processing before, the &quot;colour&quot; preceeding the &quot;honey&quot; is used as a descriptor for how much of the cherry is left on the seed. White representing the least amount of cherry left (i.e. the closest to a &quot;washed&quot;) - so I am expecting quite a clean elegant cup profile. Following the honey stage the coffee has been left for 25-32 days to dry, which is fairly long for this processing style. This may help to increase the cup complexity - but only the producer will know for sure why they opt for a longer drying style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I only have a half bag of this coffee I did not try to pull an espresso with it - at the price I did not want to risk a &quot;sink job&quot; with a poorly pulled shot when dialing in. Don't worry however! There was still plenty of espresso being consumed at JazzCoffeeStuff towers, the coffees in question may appear in next weeks post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that build up let's get on to the coffee itself. First thing to note about this (and other Drop coffees) is how light the roast is. It is certainly lighter than most other coffees around, if you are more of a medium-light or medium fan this might be a bit much for you. But if like me you enjoy the lighter roasts Drop are always worth a shout. On the dry aroma I get lots of notes, the first thing that came to mind was tangerine. Along with this there are floral notes of jasmine and bergamot and hints of that honey sweetness you get from a pulped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual the filter comes from my Hamasi brewer with (bleached) chemex papers. What is striking about this coffee is its complexity. There is so much going on in the cup. As with a lot of these complex coffees they come alive as they cool. Unfortunately since the roast is so light you need to brew with very hot water. This leaves you like a kid on christmas eve staring at their presents unable to open them, quite a torturous affair. If you don't let the cup cool enough everything gets a bit muddled and it is difficult to get any flavour separation. If you can hold off long enough you are treated with a truly amazing cup of coffee. In a blind cupping you would likely guess this is an Ethiopian coffee given the major flavour notes are peach and florals. However there is more to it than that, the sweetness is very high - syrupy even. This syrupy character carries through to the mouthfeel too. The tangerine note we had on the nose also comes into play too and gives a big juicy and fruity character to the coffee. As you'd expect with Gesha the florals are ever present too, they come more to the forefront the longer you leave the coffee to cool. The coffee also has a strikingly long aftertaste too described on the tasting notes as &quot;strawberry lemonade&quot; - which is an absolutely perfect description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this is a great coffee. Whether it is worth the price of admission is up to you - at around 5 times the price of the other coffees featured on this blog, is it really 5 times the coffee? Probably not, but this is true with most &quot;premium&quot; items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to pick some jazz to pair with such a special coffee is no easy task. In the end I decided to pick Thelonious Monk with his 1959 album &quot;The Thelonious Monk Orchestra at Town Hall&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/027-Live-At-Town-Hall/Live-At-Town-Hall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Monk's first appearance on this blog, I wanted to save him for a special occassion. For me no other artist sums up what jazz is all about more than Thelonious Monk. More than that he transcends the genre to become, in my opinion, one of the greatest artists on any medium. It takes a matter of seconds to know you're listening to Thelonious, even if people try their best to replicate him they never quite nail it - they always sound like a karaoke impersonation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As some readers to this blog may be relatively new to jazz it is worth giving a brief re-cap on Monk's history. He first came to prominence in the 1940s as one of the leading fore-fathers of the be-bop movement. Along with Dizzy Gillespie and Charlie Parker he helped work out how be-bop could be played - most notably in after hours gigs at Minton's jazz club in Harlem (if you gave me a time machine this is one of the places/times I would visit just to hear some of those gigs). A little while later during his career he and fellow pianist Bud Powell were caught in a car with drugs in it. Thelonious refused to rat on his friend and so the police took away his cabaret card. Monk apparently heeded the aphorism &quot;snitches get stitches&quot;. By losing his card he was unable to play in the main jazz clubs in NY (any club serving alcohol). This allowed Monk to be effectively shielded from the jazz scene and develop his own sound. Another consequence was it allowed him the opportunity to collaborate with John Coltrane and create some truly great music. In the latter stages of his career he was plagued by mental illness/neurological issues and his behaviour became more and more erratic before his death in 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monk's compositions (and playing style) are characterised by their twisting rhythmic constructions and angular sounding melodies. I have to admit the first time I heard Monk I didn't &quot;get&quot; it, I heard him too early on in my jazz journey and it was just too much of a stretch at the time. I revisted Monk a few years later and he blew my mind, from then on he became (probably) my favourite jazz artist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another big part of the Monk vibe is the humour, there are very few other artists who use humour in the same way. Not only in the sometimes cartoon-ish playful melodies but also when performing. He would often get up and dance while others were soloing, sometimes interrupting his dancing to add a chord stab at an opportune moment without missing a beat. He was also renowned for his fashion/style being particularly associated with hats - this is also picked up on the tribute to Monk by Eric Dolphy in the tune &quot;Hat and Beard&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Town Hall&quot; album was recorded in Feb 1959, it is one of the rare opportunities to hear Monk in a &quot;big band&quot; context. Most of his other works are in quartet and small-band formats. Here he revisits some of his previous tunes but uses the wider soundscape available to him. You can also hear, perhaps most clearly, his love of Duke Ellington being in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of &quot;behind the scenes&quot; recordings from the concert which give a real insight into Monk's approach, the particularly interested can hunt these down and you can hear Monk describe the tunes to the band and it is very illuminating. I also remember hearing a story that in the rehearsals for this album one of the musicians was unable to lock into the rhythm and so Thelonious pulled him to one side and preceeded to dance in front of him as a way of portraying the rhythm. This gives a great insight into how to think about these tunes, and with that in mind it gives you a whole fresh perspective on the pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 10 musicians appearing on this album so we will not mention all of them. However it is worth noting that this album features a relatively young Donald Byrd on the trumpet, Art Taylor on the drums and is the first collaboration between Monk and Charlie Rouse who played tenor with various Thelonious bands for 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to pick out choice tracks on this recording as all 6 tunes are fantastic. Perhaps the most revered on this album is &quot;Little Rootie Tootie&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). This is quintessetially Monk featuring a twisting rhythmic melody that is both silly yet also completely logical. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/G9Nf2qOqhoE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Up to now we have mostly talked about the fun playful side of Monk, but lest we forget he was also a master at writing hauntingly beautiful sombre tunes. On this album &quot;Monk's Mood&quot; is probably the best example of this. It manages to conjure up great sadness but at the same time just the right amount of happiness and hope. It is a melody that can rattle around your head for weeks after listening to it and the extended band arrangment adds to the weight behind the melody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this album belongs in the &quot;essential&quot; category of jazz albums for me. If you have not heard it before do yourself a favour and hunt down a copy (I'd recommend the original 6 track listing above the extended reissues which don't really add much in my view).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/027-Live-At-Town-Hall/Live-At-Town-Hall.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/027-Live-At-Town-Hall/Live-At-Town-Hall.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rainbow Sign and Debeka</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/rainbow-sign-debeka" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rainbow Sign and Debeka" /><published>2020-10-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Rainbow-Sign-Debeka</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/rainbow-sign-debeka">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-17-Rainbow-Sign-Debeka.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iRRwSAoRX28&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the blog this week we are staying in sunny Margate and sticking with the Curve Coffee Roasters. Yet again we're featuring another Ethiopian coffee, this time a natural process from the Debeka farm - another owned by Israel Degfa (this blog is becoming a bit predictable at this rate). Again we're in the Oromia region but this time the Borena zone (I believe a blog first).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this coffee particularly interesting however is the varietal: Mundo Novo. This is not a varietal one would usually associate with Ethiopia. Typically Mundo Novo is found in South American regions - most notably Brazil. It has also been introduced to Central America but you don't see it often there either, reportedly due to the farmers not liking how tall the plants become. In this case Israel received some plants from a friend on a trip to Brazil and decided to plant then at Debeka. Mundo Novo comes from the typica-bourbon lineage and is a natural mutation of a bourbon, as such it inherits a lot of bourbon characteristics: good cup quality but not particularly resistant to pests nor disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly on to what matters: the coffee itself. The dry aroma consists of two main components for me: a syrupy rich sweet note like a honey and a soft delicate floral note - I would describe it as a white floral instead of a lavender/violet type floral. Overall it is fairly delicate and is not one that will blow you away on the nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start with the filter. Here the &quot;soft&quot; and &quot;delicate&quot; descriptors certainly come to play. Although this is a natural process it is a very clean cup and you couldn't describe this one as a &quot;fruit bomb&quot; like some naturals. There are fruit notes however, the typcial apricot/peach notes you expect with Ethiopian coffees but also a hint of a tropical fruit from the processing. The taste notes on the bag call this pineapple, which I feel is fair. The whitefloral notes certainly come out to play in the aftertaste, it reminds me of the jasmine flowers that come out to bloom in early summer. This is a coffee I find very interesting and have enjoyed coming back to, it is so soft that it doesn't command your attention if you have other things to do but there's enough intrigue to keep you entertained. Another great filter cup from Curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll move onto the espresso here, but before we talk taste notes I'm going to take a brief de-tour into the topic of &quot;puck-prep&quot;. This something that seems to boggle the mind of a novice barista and internet message boards/youtube comments are filled with questions about it. You'll often find people coming up with increasingly complicated preparations to get a &quot;better&quot; shot. In my experience a lot of it amounts to chasing ghosts and simplicity is the best approach, you want to have something you can repeat day in day out without thinking about it. Your approach should match the equipment you have and the type of coffee you drink. For me WDT (Weiss distribution trick) is worth doing but the other prep types (e.g. the OCD spinner style) are a waste of time. To do WDT you essentially &quot;stir&quot; your grounds within the portafilter, this aims to break up any lumps and ensure that the grounds are well &quot;mixed&quot;. Depending on your grinder you might find that the grind quality changes as you grind coffee (due to different weights of beans being above the burrs, popcorning etc.) You want the puck to be as homogeneous as possible so you give it a little stir. That's it, very simple... Yet many get this part wrong: first part to consider is the stirrer itself. You can pick these up from various places such as etsy if you search &quot;WDT tool&quot; - but not all tools are created equally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/026-Rainbow-Sign/WDT.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a WDT tool you want to find one with &quot;thin&quot; lugs, if they are made from thick pieces of metal you risk compressing the grinds more and leaving a &quot;hole&quot; when you remove the tool itself. The next thing to consider is the positioning of the lugs themselves, typically you'll see the lugs being parallel to each other pointing straight down. This gives the tool a very &quot;thin&quot; profile (like the picture above), this is not ideal for mixing the grounds. Instead it's best if you point the lugs outwards to give a &quot;wider&quot; profile, this will allow for much more efficient mixing. You can do this by gently bending the legs at the body of the tool. Ideally you want the lugs to touch the edges of your basket. With your good &quot;wide&quot; WDT tool it's time to start mixing, to do this you want to gently make a circular motion so that you bring grinds from the basket walls towards the centre and vice versa. You do not have to spend long doing this; I like to do 10 rotations in a clockwise direction then 10 in an anti-clockwise direction. After this remove the tool, tamp and go. It's that simple, it should only take a matter of seconds after you get the technique down. I see lots of people say WDT doesn't make a difference, but also lots of videos of people doing it badly - I do wonder if the two are linked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the coffee itself. Again this is the &quot;filter&quot; roasted version of this coffee as is my preference. The roast is fairly light and for filter I use a hand grinder so I can tell these beans are particularly hard. This usually means that a coffee can be a pain to dial in, but actually this one was a pleasure. It is very forgiving and with my setup almost impossible to get it too &quot;wrong&quot;. Unsuprisingly I find it works best with a high temperature and a long pull (1:2.75) which I get through in about 25s. In the cup the same &quot;soft&quot; descriptors come through, it seems to pickup a &quot;melon&quot; type quality in the espresso which I did not notice in the filter. The mouthfeel is big and somewhat creamy in texture. Both acidity and sweetness are medium. In the aftertaste those familiar white florals come through, this seems to be this coffees &quot;signature&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I'm very happy with this coffee and another solid showing from Curve. This is the last of my current batch from Curve but given the two I've had here I'm sure they will appear back on the blog at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this weeks jazz we're looking at another 2020 recent release. This time we're going to Blue Note records and taking on the new Ron Miles album: &quot;Rainbow Sign&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/026-Rainbow-Sign/Rainbow-Sign.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who have not come across Ron before he is a trumpet player and composer from Denver, Colorado. He first started making records in the late 1980s/early 1990s. He is perhaps best known for his collaborations with guitarist Bill Frisell with whom he has released many albums under both his own name and Bill's. The line up on &quot;Rainbow Sign&quot; is the same quintet as on the 2017 &quot;I Am A Man&quot; release, namely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ron Miles: Trumpet and Cornet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jason Moran: Piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Frisell: Electric Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas Morgan: Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brian Blade: Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of modern jazz this is pretty much an &quot;all star&quot; line-up. Each player being regarded as a premier artist in their own right.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/p4-cnRUsIlQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Ron wrote started writing this album in 2018 while looking after his father at the end of his life. Rather than being a maudlin and sombre affair &quot;Rainbow Sign&quot; instead offers up a loving dedication. The album seems to reflect a spiritual awakening for the trumpeter as he comes to terms with his loss. It seems to offer up hope of eternal peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many albums in the Miles and Frisell back catalogue it is hard to classify the music. The music seems to start off in one place and then gently transform into something completely different without the listener noticing. Really it is about letting the music take you to a different place rather than diving in to explore the technicalities in this author's opinion. Ron and Bill are completely on the same page and create new sonic landscapes for us to explore. I often describe the ultimate goal for any artist as creating their own universe and allowing their fans to explore this. I feel this is what separates the merely &quot;very good&quot; musicians to true artists. The Miles/Frisell partnership is capable of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface &quot;Rainbow Sign&quot; seems like an easy-going, simple record - one that can simply blend into your day without demanding much attention. However the more you concentrate the more the album gives, dancing between jazz, folk, blues, world-music and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title track (embedded at the top of this post) is one of the more &quot;jazz&quot; focussed pieces. It is characterised by Ron's beautifully clear and articulate tone giving the melody some weight. Brian Blade is given the chance to swing on this track, perhaps more so than any other track. Elsewhere Blade offers up subtle textures to his playing which is perhaps what he is known best for. Bill and Jason take on the comping duties, each relying on sparsity to give the piece space. It feels like more than a little nod towards Thelonious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is followed by &quot;The Rumor&quot; which feels very much like a tune that could have featured in any number of Frisell recordings. The main melody is driven via Bill's guitar. It has the feel of an old Americana tune (albeit revisited through the lens of modern jazz). The second half of the tune features some of Miles most subtle playing, there's no hint of ego here - letting Bill take a bit of the limelight. This lifts the piece into a well rounded composition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album ends with the piece &quot;A Kind Word&quot; which almost has a &quot;rock&quot; vibe. Knowing that this album is dedicated to his late father this piece feels a bit like a eulogy.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lJxzoS11z8c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This is another great album released in 2020. It is well worth hunting down a copy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/026-Rainbow-Sign/Rainbow-Sign.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/026-Rainbow-Sign/Rainbow-Sign.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hero Trio and Chelbesa</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/hero-trio-chelbesa" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hero Trio and Chelbesa" /><published>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Hero-Trio-Chelbesa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/hero-trio-chelbesa">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-10-Hero-Trio-Chelbesa.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CrUm4CsKW8c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we have a new roaster appearing on the blog: Curve Coffee Roasters - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.curveroasters.co.uk/&quot;&gt;https://www.curveroasters.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt; - based in Margate. They have been on my &quot;to try&quot; list for a while but I never got round to it until now. They come with a reputation for roasting some truly great coffees and their pricing is very reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you would expect with this blog I stuck with their &quot;filter roast&quot; offerings (they also offer an &quot;espresso roast&quot; option). For me personally I tend to find these speak to me more than the espresso roasts - admittedly you need to work a bit harder to get a good espresso out of one though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is from the Chelbesa village within the Gedeb Zone of the Oromia Region. of Ethiopia. This coffee is made up from contributions from a number of small holders within the village and the coffee is a washed process. This is generally a recipe for a coffee I will enjoy, washed coffees from this area are generally my &quot;go to&quot;. After a bit of digging it appears this coffee has a cupping score of 89.5 - which is very high!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado lets get right in to the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I get a sweet honey note paired with the typical floral notes one would expect from this sort of coffee. The aromas are not too strong coming off the grinds, everything is soft and subtle. As we've said before on this blog: the dry aroma can give you some indication of a coffees character but does not tell you everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual starting with our usual filter technique: one word to get us started is &quot;wow&quot;. This coffee is a near perfect example of why washed coffees from this area are so prized. The first thing I notice is an apricot or peach note, a sweet but not too sweet character. These flavours slowly morph into a melon type flavour the more the cup cools. Then of course the florals: bergamot is clearly present along with violets and lavendar in the background. The mouthfeel is soft, creamy but slightly syrupy - it is not one of the very thin washed Ethiopians completely devoid of mouthfeel. As one  would expect the aftertaste is a lingering black tea affair. Overall very enjoyable!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso. This one I found a little finnicky to dial in, all my shots tasted good but there was a certain astringency in the aftertaste that took a while to sort out. In the end I found a ratio of 1:2.5 was about right - I didn't want to go superlong with this one since I knew it had a good mouthfeel I didn't want to go to waste. I went for a pull of around 25s which is reasonably quick but not excessively. The story was the same with the temperature: hot but not super-hot. As a shot many of the notes from the filter came through, however the florals took more of a backseat. With the mouthfeel and the very subtle florals the &quot;honey&quot; descriptor from the dry aroma became more apt. If you're willing to put the work in you will be rewarded for it with this coffee but I see why they would label this a &quot;filter&quot; roast - certainly not a coffee I'd recommend to the novice barista for espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is certianly a very good coffee and one I very much enjoyed, hopefully this is representative of what Curve can do - I'm sure I'll be trying them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jazz this week is a 2020 release from Rudresh Mahanthappa called &quot;Hero Trio&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rudresh is an alto-saxophonist based in New York. He is perhaps best known for his work with pianist Vijay Iyer with whom he has collaborated often. As well as regularly featuring in Downbeat polls he is also musical director at Princeton - so quite a pedigree for a modern jazz musician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with his work I would describe Rudresh's playing as being fairly &quot;outside&quot;, it is technical and wild but at the same time he still respects the music and song structure. I like free jazz but I sometimes struggle with the really avant garde artists who completely throw out all semblance of musical structure. Mahanthappa also spent many years studying Indian classical music - and this often comes out in his playing, however this never comes across as forced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the album &quot;Hero Trio&quot; Rudresh pays tribute to some of his favourite artists including: John Coltrane, Keith Jarrett, Ornette Coleman and of course no alto saxophonist would not list Charlie Parker as an influence (Rudresh even released &quot;Bird Calls&quot; in 2015 - an entire album dedicated to Parker). Alongside these jazz stalwarts there are even pieces from Stevie Wonder and Johnny Cash. We should not think of this as simply rehashing a number of standards however, each tune has been majorly reworked and given its own style. The music feels modern while still paying respect to the past - this is certainly not easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the album name suggests the band is a trio format consisting of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rudresh Mahanthappa - Alto Saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;François Moutin - Acoustic Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rudy Royston - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rudresh the band as &quot;superheros&quot; even dressing up the band in suitable costumes for some of the promotional material. Listening to the album it is easy to understand why. The band is totally locked in, this allows them to take real risks in the arrangments. The album feels like being on a rollercoaster, you know you're in safe hands despite travelling a mile a minute. In a piano-less trio format the band is allowed to really stretch their legs, without chords tying down what is &quot;acceptable&quot; to play Mahathappa (and Moutin) is free to play without inhibition - something he really takes advantage of. The extra space in the mix allows Royston to really flex his chops too, Rudy is one of my favourite current jazz drummers but he is probably more well known for playing sparsely - so it is nice to hear him let loose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with &quot;Red Cross&quot; a Charlie Parker tune. Whereas Parker's classic bounces along with a jovial be-bop type rhythm, the Hero Trio goes for a much more direct hard hitting approach. This is somewhat characteristic of the album as a whole - this is music that demands your attention, it's difficult to imagine this being &quot;background music&quot;. Mahathappa relies on a lot of chromaticism throughout his solo, this along with his phrasing certainly point towards his Indian classical background. It is a sound that is uniquely his, I don't think you would mistake him for anybody else out there today.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NSmY80pmavE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

One of the &quot;non-jazz&quot; tributes on the album is to the Johnny Cash classic &quot;Ring of Fire&quot;. I sometimes find it worrisome when jazz artists take on these really well known tunes. It is very easy for them to become either: instantly forgettable as they don't take any risks (and it's just a ploy to sell records) or they use so much reharmonization that the original tune is completely unrecognisable. Thankfully Mahanthappa and crew take on &quot;Ring of Fire&quot; seriously and pay it the respect it deserves. They do not take too many liberties with the melody, instead they play rhythmically instead. This gives the tune some energy and freshness without straying too far away from the spirit of the piece. Of course the solos are free and wild as one would expect, however they are some of the most restrained on the entire album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlight of the album for me however is &quot;The Windup&quot; a Keith Jarrett piece (and one of my all time favourite tunes from the Jarrett songbook). Covering a Jarrett piece without having a single instrument capable of playng chords is certainly a challenge. This really goes to show just how talented Moutin is as a bass player, much of the main melody falls on him and he needs to drive the music forward. At the same time he needs to imply the chords of the piece so that it doesn't feel &quot;hollow&quot;. About mid-way through the tune when comping Mahanthappa's solos there is some of the best bass playing you are likely to hear. A truly fantastic acheivement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This album is another 2020 banger, if you are into jazz you definitely should hunt this album down. For a rank newbie to the world of jazz this might be a bit much as a first step and it'd perhaps be worth familiarising yourself with the source material first - but certainly put this one of the list of albums to catchup on later. I feel this is an album I'll come back to time and time again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/025-Hero-Trio/Hero-Trio.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stein Urheim and La Lima</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/stein-urheim-la-lima" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stein Urheim and La Lima" /><published>2020-10-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Stein-Urheim-La-Lima</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/stein-urheim-la-lima">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-10-03-Stein-Urheim-La-Lima.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KUAaMLeE4OE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with Whitstable based roaster Eigthy Seven Plus. This time we have a Peruvian coffee from the La Coipa district, in the north west corner of the country not too far from the border with Ecuador. This is a washed Caturra/Bourbon coffee from a farm called La Lima owned by Eduardo Campos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we noted before the roaster takes its name from dealing with coffees with an SCA rating in excess of 87 exclusively. This particular coffee has a score of 88 - the highest currently offered by the roaster. It is also the most expensive they currently have at £15 per 250g - which is still very reasonable for a coffee of this quality - this comes out to around 90p per (large) cup of coffee so compared to what you pay in a cafe a veritable bargain!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've mentioned in the past Peru is not an origin I naturally gravitate towards, I don't dislike Peru and don't avoid at all costs but usually other origins speak to me more so I rarely order Peruvians. This year however I have found some fantastic Peruvian coffees. I tend to find that each year there is one origin where the stars have aligned and they produce fantastic coffee. This feels like Peru's year to me and maybe I'll start buying more Peruvians from now on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado lets get onto what is important: the cup. First things first the dry aroma: I get faint hints of tropical fruits (that I am unable to put my finger on) but really the big notes are: raspberry, apricot and florals. It is quite a delicate aroma, if you want a big bold fruit bomb it might not be for you. This is sophsticated and refined, these are charactersitics I find myself looking for more and more these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we will start by looking at the filter, again my usual set up of using my Hasami brewer with chemex papers and relying on a &quot;pulse pour&quot; style technique to avoid excess agitation and so I end up with a super clean cup. The first thing to note is this coffee &quot;grinds coarse&quot; by which I mean for a given grind setting you'll likely find drawdown is quicker than you expect. If you are a relative coffee novice one of the first things you might try to do is &quot;chase&quot; a specific time for a brew and fine up the grind (I used to do this when I started). I personally think this is a bad idea, I don't believe there's a &quot;magic&quot; drawdown time that will fix all woes. Instead any adjustment should be by taste alone - and it was clear this coffee liked the shorter drawdown! In all the brewtime I acheieved was around 2:20s on average - many brewguides will tell you to hit 3:00-4:00 for an &quot;optimal&quot; cup. My cup did not suffer from this, in fact I tried to hit a 3:30 drawdown out of curiousity one day and it made the coffee 100 times worse, it became more bitter and harsh and lost a lot of flavour separation in the process. As always your tastebuds are the best measuring device!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter coffee we get a cup that pretty much mimics the dry aroma. It is a delicate affair and shows real sophistication. The major underlying flavour is raspberry, the tartness and acidity along with the sweetness therein.  This is supported by the delicate juicy apricot type note (which itself brings more sweetness). Throughout the cup the florals are prominent too, while the cup is hot they take a bit of a back seat but as it cools they come to the front. They remind me mostly of a bergamot Earl-grey type floral but there are also plenty of white jasmine notes too. This coffee really evolves as it cools so try and savour it (if you can). In terms of acidity I'd say it is fairly low (but does not taste flat) and the sweetness high, but the cup is very complex and interesting. Definitely a very enjoyable cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso, again this is a filter roast so all the usual rules apply. This coffee seems to be slightly lighter in roast compared to the previous Kayon Mountain (from memory and by eye - I don't own a meter to check this). However I found that it actually benefits from a more &quot;typical&quot; recipe of about 1:2.2 and a medium heat, with a PI time of 10s then a 27s pull - a very &quot;standard&quot; recipe for an espresso and not usually what you expect from a filter roast. As an espresso I found a new note becomes more prominent: Pears. The raspberry note seems less noticable than in the filter but otherwise all the familiar notes appear. Being so subtle some of the florals are a little harder to find but they're still there, but cold espresso is disgusting so they don't really get a chance to speak as the drink cools. As such I think while it makes a good espresso this coffee really shines in the filter settings. I don't drink milky coffee but I imagine this one would struggle to punch through so look elsewhere if you're looking for a flat-white!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto this weeks jazz. This one might be a bit contentious to the jazz purists out there, I could see this causing an &quot;Is this jazz?&quot; argument. Personally I don't care where the boundaries are - as long as the music is good! And this record is certainly good. It is from 2014 and is on the Norwegian &quot;Hubro&quot; record label: Stein Urheim - Stein Urheim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stein Urheim is a Norwegian jazz guitarist/composer. His self titled album is not his debut album having released (to my knowledge) 2 albums under his own name before this and multiple collaborations. The self titled album marks a bit of a change of direction however. The album is essentially a solo project, Stein plays a number of instruments on the recording (guitars, flutes, harmonica, slide tamboura, fretless bouzouki, gu qin, mandolin, langeleik, charango, banjo, analog synths and effects),  there is a brief cameo by Jørgen Træen who adds some synth parts. In essense it is a &quot;one man band&quot; however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album was recorded entirely at the home of Ole Bull (a Norwegian violinist of the 1800s) - the space was designed with acoustics in mind with each room being tailored for small band concerts. This is distinctly noticable in the recording as it has a very &quot;warm&quot; sound and does not &quot;feel&quot; like a cold studio enviroment. In fact I would say in terms of recording quality I can't think of many albums released in the past 20 years or so that come close to having this level of &quot;organic&quot; recording. It is truly a pleasure to listen to, if you can find a vinyl copy I would strongly suggest picking it up as it's worth listening to on a quality sound system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music itself is no slouch either. Each piece is highly ambitious with many layers and interacting tracks. While it would take an eternity to unpick all the key and time signature changes that happen, all this doesn't really matter. Each piece is essentially a little look into a distinct universe, Urheim takes us on a journey - they are essentially films in musical form. Exact details matter less than the overall &quot;feeling&quot; of each piece. There are many influences throughout the album from the obvious jazz and blues, through traditional folk, surf, western classical and baroque through the middle east, hasidic and eastern musical traditions. The music slowly meanders through these styles but it never sounds forced, it is all done in a respectful and natural way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the standout pieces on the album for me is the 11 minute long &quot;After the Festival&quot; (embedded above). This piece is probably the most playful and joyous on the album, it features folk, flamenco and Carribean elements prominently along with atmospheric drones. Towards the end of the track a simple beautiful melody appears out of the chaos - what is so clever is that this melody has been there (in various forms) throughout the track it's just been obscured. This is a &quot;trick&quot; that Stein relies on for a few of the tracks on the album and it gives the project a real cohesion which I think makes it such a memorable album.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/an9C8kvNjYw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another stand-out piece is &quot;Beijing Blues&quot; - which as the name suggests is a juxtaposition of eastern-classical and blues traditions, there is even a bit of an Indian raga thrown in for good measure. The subtle use of harmonica towards the end of the track just lifts the whole piece as it slowly morphs into a blues swagger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an album that is very hard to do justice through words, I find listening to it a very visceral experience. You are transported to different worlds when you listen to it. It is an album that rewards those willing to dedicate the 40 minutes or so to listen to it without distraction - I would recommend nothing more than a comfy chair and a big pot of coffee as an accompaniment. However it can also blend into the background of your day, providing a soundtrack to whatever else you are doing. Although it relies on complex arrangement and harmony in places, it is not at all distracting. It is not often you find music that can take on both of these functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a superb album that is well worth hunting down. For my money one of the best albums released in the past 10 years and a modern classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/024-Stein-Urheim/Stein-Urheim.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tributes and Kayon Mountain</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/tributes-kayon-mountain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tributes and Kayon Mountain" /><published>2020-09-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Tributes-Kayon-Mountain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/tributes-kayon-mountain">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-09-26-Tributes-Kayon-Mountain.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/re_O4_u9VMY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we feature a new roaster called &quot;Eighty Seven Plus&quot;, not only are they new to the blog htey are relatively new in general - being set up around 1 year ago. They take their name from their coffee ethos of only using coffees that score in excess of 87 points on the SCA scale. We have talked about the pros/cons of the SCA scale in the past so we won't start that conversation again - suffice as to say 87 is usually the threshold I look for personally when deciding on a coffee. I think 87 is a good compromise between cup quality and cost, if you limit yourself to only purchasing 90 plus coffees you will have a relatively small number to choose from and you will end up paying a lot! With 87 coffees you can generally purchase them for fairly reasoanble prices but still get some really great flavours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's worth mentioning the company also has an app (via Apple app store/Google play) - I have not used this as despite working in tech I am a bit of a luddite when it comes to using tech. It appears the app allows you to take notes about the coffees and share your tasting notes with the wider community which is quite a nice idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is (another) Ethiopian - the 4th in a row for this blog. This time however it is washed whereas the previous were all natural. Given the choice I am typically more of a fan of washed coffees compared to other processing methods since I value cup clarity most of all. Like the preceeding coffees this too is from the Guji zone in the Oromia region. the farm itself is called &quot;Kayon Mountain&quot; - this is a farm I am particularly familiar with and have had coffee from them via many different roasters over the years. As such I have a number of preconceptions about how I expect this one to taste and behave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving right in to the dry aroma: the first thing that hits me is a caramel sort of smell, this is a little unexpected for a coffee like this so it stuck out. However the major notes you would expect from a coffee like this are there: peaches and stone fruits along with florals and a hint of citrus. All coffees from Eighty Seven Plus are labelled as a &quot;filter&quot; roast which I think is fair, this coffee is not quite as light roast as some others I have seen however. As usual we start with a filter in a v60 type funnel with a chemex paper. As I remembered from drinking this coffee in the past the first thing that comes to mind for me is &quot;soft&quot; - the mouthfeel is soft and delicate and the flavours are gentle and do not punch you in the face. As with most washed coffees from this region we are treated to delicate floral notes of lavender and jasmine along with lemon-y citrus and peach notes. As it cools it becomes increasingly &quot;tea like&quot;. However there is a couple of &quot;strange&quot; notes that come back time and time again with Kayon Mountain coffees to me: the first is &quot;strawberry milkshake&quot; - a combination of flavour notes and the softer mouthfeel. And &quot;bubblegum&quot; - in this example it's rather faint so if I wasn't expecting it I might not have picked up on it. But for me it is unmistakable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso: this is an Ethiopian washed coffee roasted for filter so there are no prizes for guessing the advice I give for pulling shots on this one! Hot, fast and long are the orders of the day! Owing to the density of Ethiopian beans you'll likely find that you need to set your grinder &quot;coarser&quot; to achieve the same flow-rate as you would from a central American coffee. In the end I settled on a ratio of 1:2.75 being optimal here. This seemed to be the turning point where the shot didn't get any sweeter, pulling longer than this just ended up giving thinner mouthfeel. I was pulling these shots in around 22s with a slight pre-infusion of a couple of seconds. With a &quot;shrinking violet&quot; coffee like this without any powerful flavour notes we can often find the espresso gets a bit &quot;bland&quot; - but this one does not suffer that fate. The similar flavour profile from the filter is still there but the &quot;bubblegum&quot; is able to push through a bit more and becomes more noticable. It is a real treat to find washed Ethiopian espressos like this, given a choice this is the style I go for every time. It will come as no surprise that I'll say I recommend trying this one as an espresso (even though it is considered a filter coffee).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both the filter and the espresso this coffee is super clean and has a limited clean aftertaste. Overall a strong showing from a new roaster and hopefully indicative of what else they will offer in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto this weeks jazz. We're taking a bit of a different approach this time, I am recommending an album that was released yesterday (25th September 2020) - as such I've only listened to this a few times so far so I won't dive too deeply into what is going on since I haven't had chance to study it yet, perhaps I'll revisit this one in a later blog once I've had chance to fully digest it all and can see if my perceptions change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album is called &quot;Tributes&quot; and it is by Nordic saxophonist Marius Neset, released on the German ACT record label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/023-Tributes/Tributes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marius Neset is one of the &quot;next generation&quot; of jazz musicians, being 35 years old which is young for a jazz artist these days. He released his first album in 2008 and has 11 albums to his name currently (plus a few more as a co-leader or guest slots). I first came across him via his &quot;Golden Xplosion&quot; album in 2011 - a truly fantastic album, a little rough around the edges but it was pretty clear to me he was destined to be a leading name in jazz as he matured. After a few more great albums (including the terrific &quot;Sun Blowing&quot; with Lars Danielsson) I had very high hopes for him. But his last few albums disappointed me a little. They were not terrible but he seemed to get a little lost, the high octane energy he was known for initially disappeared and the compositions - while nice - did not set the world on fire. With &quot;Tributes&quot; however he appears to have worked out how to balance the energy with solid composition and he has created the album I have been waiting for from him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Neset sax style is clearly very influenced by Michael Brecker, as most modern sax players are, however he combines this with a strong influence of chamber music (and various other European classical movements). On &quot;Tributes&quot; as the name suggests it appears he is trying to pay homage to his idols. Brecker clearly makes an appearance, but there are also strong Rollins influneces, Coltrane, and countless others. However it is done via the Neset lens - it always sounds like him and never as a cheap impersonation. While on some of his earlier records he let the fire-breathing solos take over - here Neset is always serving the music and deploys wildness only when it is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this album he is supported by the Danish Radio Big Band (conducted by Miho Hazama) - this allows him to use the big band to create an expansive soundscape to support the composition. It is extremely accomplished and done masterfully throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this album is only a day old finding clips via Youtube to embed is a challenge. The album itself is composed of 2 longer multi-part compositions (which are the true highlights for me) along with 3 shorter pieces. At the start of this blog post we embedded the title track. This one is probably the most similar to previous Neset offerings, you can really hear the chamber music influences and the big band is shown off to the full extent. Marius takes a sublime soprano solo, which is adventurous but fits into the backdrop created by the big-band seamlessly. He manages to resist the urge to throw all his chops at the piece, something that a lot of younger players (and older players too) often struggle with.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XcKHp_LgWrg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The real stars of the album are the two extended pieces: &quot;Bicycle Town&quot; which is a hark back to the sound he crafted on the &quot;Pinball&quot; album of 2015. Michael Brecker being a clear influence with the choppy sound and use of ghost notes along with the use of symmetric and diminished scales throughout. The two parts of this composition is where he can really stretch his legs and play the most soaring and technically advanced solos on the entire album. Showing he still has the chops to be considered one of the best on the scene. &quot;Children's Day&quot; is the other multi-part composition which (after a slow build) descends into a calypso and cuban feel, very reminiscent of &quot;St Thomas&quot; by Sonny Rollins. However this is combined with a complicated harmonic and rhythmic landscape and more &quot;Neset-isms&quot;. It is perhaps the most adventurous on the album and probably my favourite piece as a result. The longer the piece goes on the more the main melody gets distorted and the composition takes on a life of its own before coming back round at the end for a final big crescendo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I am very impressed with this album and I'm sure this is going to be one I listen to regularly in the next few weeks/months. After a couple of listens I don't like to make grandiose statements but I feel this has potential to be up there with the best albums released in the last few years. Hopefully this marks a new era for Neset and he can live up to his potential. If you get a chance I strongly suggest you pick up a copy of this album through whatever means you use to purchase your music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/023-Tributes/Tributes.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/023-Tributes/Tributes.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Way Out West and Bale Mountain</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/way-out-west-bale-mountain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Way Out West and Bale Mountain" /><published>2020-09-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Way-Out-West-Bale-Mountain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/way-out-west-bale-mountain">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-09-19-Way-Out-West-Bale-Mountain.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C6Oma0WOALU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

After a brief hiatus JazzCoffeeStuff is back! We are once again looking at a coffee from the fine folks at PLOT roasting - who are fast becoming a regular fixture on this blog. Like the preceeding two posts we have yet another coffee from the Israel Degfa company, again from Ethiopia - this time West Arsi Zone, Oromia - and another natural process. This one is called &quot;Bale Mountain&quot;. This is a single farm coffee - that is every coffee bean here is from the Bale Mountain farm. This is fairly rare for Eithiopian coffees where it is common for a single washing station to process coffees from multiple individual farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have mentioned Israel and his company a few times in the past weeks, it is about time we talk about this a little more. From what we have seen so far Israel owns many farms and washing stations in the area. You may have come to the conclusion that this is somehow &quot;big business&quot; and somehow exploitative. This is not the case, specialty coffee allows farmers to get more for their crops than they would via other avenues (I'm not saying specialty is the perfect system by any means, but compared to the alternatives it is better!) Israel and company also works directly with the local communities, offers finance to farmers to help them get started and also provides education and even builds schools in the local areas. While not a &quot;pure&quot; charity it does appear Israel does good for the people of Ethiopia and should be commended for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the coffee itself - this is a bit of a memory test for me since I no longer have this coffee in front of me. Usually I write these pieces while drinking the coffee itself but recently life has got in the way of the blog and so this comes a bit late - but this coffee was so special I had to give it some kudos. The dry aroma on the nose I get a lot of floral notes but also a good whack of really sweet fruitiness. The aroma is quite powerful so suggests we could be in for a flavour-bomb of a coffee. As usual diving into the filter, the first thing I notice is that it is not nearly as punchy as the dry aroma suggested. It is a refined and elegant cup, it's not a super funky boozy natural like you sometimes find with Ethiopians. The major flavour note for me is strawberry - PLOT decided to use a &quot;red&quot; colour scheme for the label of this one and it is clear to see why. There are other fruity notes too but strawberry is by far the most prominent. It is very very sweet, if you like sugary sweet coffees this one is for you! The label says &quot;honey&quot; as a flavour note but for me it is more of a cotton candy sweetness - I associate honey with the texture as much as the flavour and there is little in the way of syrupy mouthfeel on show here. In addition to this there is a perfumed floral note, particularly in the aftertaste, it is really quite noticable and makes the cup super interesting. The balance between fruit and floral changes significantly with temperature and you can spend ages trying to unpick the flavours if that is your thing. Equally it is not so complex that it is distracting either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the espresso. It was fairly obvious where this one would like to be dialed in to, if you've read my advice on filter roasts used as espresso before you can guess what I'll suggest: pull long, pull fast, pull hot! This one didn't need to go super long into lungo territory but it was on the long side. The flavour profile was similar to the filter; strawberry at the front, floral at the back. Again it's super sweet and it is not too acidic. It has a sort of mellowness in the espresso, it's elegant and refined. This is what I really enjoy in (good) Ethiopian espressos. Overall  was very sad to see the back of this coffee. I guess you would expect a comparison to the previous Israel Degfa from PLOT (the Gelana gesha) - it's very hard to pick a favourite. They were both fantastic and really quite different prospects - if I had to choose I'd give the gesha the edge but you cannot go wrong with either and they're both worth buying if they're available as you read this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the jazz this week. When JazzCoffeeStuff was on hiatus the jazz world was celebrating one of its greatest contributors: Sonny Rollins who turned 90 years old on September 7th. To celebrate this milestone this week we are looking at one of my favourite albums of all time: &quot;Way Out West&quot; released in 1957 on Contempary Records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/022-Way-Out-West/Way-Out-West.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage nothing needs to be said about Rollins and his legacy, I don't believe anybody would consider him anything other than an &quot;all time great&quot;. His reputation far exceeds that of jazz, he's known as a commentator (very recently penning an interesting article in the NY Times about current global events and whether that leads to personal change) as well as a cultural icon - you have to have a certain level of recognition to be a major character in an episode of The Simpsons (and lets be honest: Bleeding Gums Murphy is himself a not so subtle homage to Rollins). With a recording and touring career spanning 65+ years he has played with just about every major artist in the post-bop era (and many from the be-bop era too) as well as having a string of albums under his own name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album we're looking at here is &quot;Way Out West&quot; - one I always find myself coming back to.  It is a bit of an oddball in the Rollins back catalogue, he explores americana, country and western swing through the lens of be-bop. This gives the album its own personality which I like! It's a shame Sonny didn't revisit these ideas often but I guess any attempts to do this might feel a little forced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album cover is one of my favourite album covers of all time. Sonny fully leans into the &quot;cowboy&quot; theme with gun holsters and a cowboy hat. The humour is something that is found throughout the album, the music is of course serious in terms of composition and harmony but it does not mean you can't have fun with it. Jazz has the impression of being &quot;serious&quot; so it is nice to listen to these &quot;lighter&quot; records on occassion. &quot;Way Out West&quot; does have provenance too however, it is the first album to feature a trio of the form: sax-bass-drums. This is now ubiquitous, it's hard to picture a time when this would have been considered ground-breaking. By forgoing an &quot;accompanying&quot; harmonic instrument such as piano or drums a lot of space is opened up in mix which allows Sonny to improvise much more freely - which for an improviser as prolific as Rollins is certainly a good thing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album opens up with the track &quot;I'm An Old Cowhand&quot; (embedded at the start of this blog) which was originally penned by Johnny Mercer in 1936. While the woodblock &quot;horse&quot; sounds are a little cheesy the track itself is masterfully done. Rollins takes the main melody of the tune and looks at it through the lens of be-bop - the accents and timing are essentially textbook Charlie Parker. However he resists the temptation to up the tempo (as many would have) - this combined with the sparse arrangement of having only bass and drums in the rhythm section means Sonny can have complete freedom over the tune: he can lean into the groove at points but then breathe fire on a solo for effect. By all accounts this should just be a silly, gimmicky sort of tune to fill up space on an album - but the magic of Sonny is he can elevate this into something magical. For contrast you can see the original performance of &quot;I'm An Old Cowhand&quot; from 1936 in the film &quot;Rhythm on the Range&quot; (with Bing Crosby singing). It's a long way away from Sonny's interpretation!

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jo-pApe1Kd0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

While the western vibe is prominent on 3 of the 5 album tracks (the track above, another western standard &quot;Wagon Wheels&quot; and the Rollins penned &quot;Way Out West&quot;) - this is balanced with some simply sublime ballad playing. I've said it in this blog before: I consider being able to play ballads a real test of an improvisers skill. The second track on this album is a beautiful interpretation of Duke Ellington's 1934 &quot;(In My) Solitude&quot;. This has been recorded multiple times over the years by a range of artists - but the version on &quot;Way Out West&quot; is the definitive version for me, the version I think of whenever anybody mentions the tune. Sonny manages to perfectly capture the haunting beauty in the piece while somehow providing just a glimmer of hope. It is an absolute masterclass in improvising over a ballad, and for me personally some of Sonny's best playing.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_D3zqnokaVI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

So far we have (rightly) been focussed on the man himself, but it is time to recognise the bass playing and &quot;give the drummer some&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bass we have Ray Brown - who is a legend in his own right. Having recorded with artists through the late big-band era, through be-bop then post-bop and beyond. He is perhaps best known for his work with Oscar Peterson and Ella Fitzgerald who he recorded with on multiple albums. He also has countless recordings as a leader/co-leader. Without a harmony instrument in the line-up the role of the bass player becomes crucial, often in larger ensembles the bass player has the function of keeping things grounded. In a small trio format like this that changes to driving the tune forward (which may otherwise fall to a piano player) - this was the first time anybody played in this way on record. Ray does it masterfully, I find his playing on Solitude in particular superb but he is consistently brilliant on every track. It would be very easy for this trio format to fall down by a bass player being too sparse, fortunately this is not the case here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drummer on this album is Shelly Manne - again somebody who can be considered a legend in their own right. Manne is most associated with the west coast jazz scene. In the US during the 40s-60s (roughly) there was east and west coast schools of jazz (perhaps a pre-cursor to east and west coast rap?) The west coast typically focussed on the &quot;cool jazz&quot; sound, relaxed and laid back. But also the west gave rise to some of the more avant-garde artists too - Shelly played with both the cool and avant extensively. Aside from his own work he is probably remembered most for his work with Chet Baker. On &quot;Way Out West&quot; in addition to the &quot;horse sounds&quot; with the wood block he also unleashes pure swing. In this small trio format the bass player has to &quot;cover&quot; for the harmony instruments and so the swing is largely driven by the drummer - there are few as well equipped for this role than Shelly.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9XvpsxQAZjo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The fearlessness of Sonny Rollins as a leader cannot be overstated here. Not only did he invent this new trio format (which has since been copied by pretty much every major sax player since at some point in their career) - he did so with 2 musicians in Brown and Manne who he hadn't worked with before. I think this adds to the spontaneous and playful atmosphere throughout the album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish I'll leave you with another country tune: &quot;Wagon Wheels&quot; - another examination of a piece of americana through the lens of be-bop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Way Out West&quot; is one of my favourite albums of all time, so I strongly suggest you pick up a copy via whichever medium you use to purchase your music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/022-Way-Out-West/Way-Out-West.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/022-Way-Out-West/Way-Out-West.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Riverside and Saint Semeon Abay</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/riverside-semeon-abay" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Riverside and Saint Semeon Abay" /><published>2020-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Riverside-Semeon-Abay</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/riverside-semeon-abay">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-09-05-Riverside-Semeon-Abay.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BDpJyUznSSY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are featuring a new (for the blog) roaster: Saint Coffee Roasters. Their roastery is located in Hackney, London and they have a number of cafes across the capital including Baker Street, Angel and Camden. I decided to give them a try based on this coffee in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question is an Ethiopian coffee from the Israel Degfa company (as our previous one was also). From the Adola washing station from the Aferara region of the Guji zone. It has been designated an &quot;experimental natural&quot; process - also known as a &quot;bag process&quot; whereby the coffee cherries are left to ferment in a polypropylene bag (rotating every 12 hours). This (reportedly) leads to increased development of intense fruity flavours. This particular example has an SCA score of 90.25 - regular readers at this point will know an SCA score is not the be all and end all but a score above 90 places the coffee in the top 1% of coffee globally. High praise indeed! Given this the price of the bag was fairly reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ordering this coffee there was a bit of a royal mail mishap and my original package got so wet that the address label rubbed off and sent back to Saint (it begs the question what on earth royal mail were doing with it!) Saint were quick to correct this and sent an additional bag of coffee by way of an apology - this is certainly a good way to resolve the issue from my side so I'm giving them a shout out here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly onto the coffee itself: the dry aroma gives a very big hit of chocolate/cocoa, that is the overiding note with some lighter fruitynotes hidden in the background. This coffee is roasted marginally darker than some of the roasters commonly featured in this blog, it is by no means &quot;medium&quot; but it is certianly &quot;omni&quot; as opposed to the &quot;filter&quot; styles usually featured, this will likely bring out these cocoa notes a bit more. As usual we start with a filter; as the dry aroma suggested the cocoa is a big part of this coffee and there is a big body and mouthfeel to go with it. There are the usual &quot;natural&quot; tropical fruit or bubblegum notes present but they're not as funky and as in your face as you might expect. Actually I find myself using &quot;black forest gateau&quot; as the most predominent descriptor here. As the cup cools the fruity notes come more to the front and the cocoa subsides. Overall it is fairly complex and there's a lot to pick apart here, for a natural it is also very clean tasting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the espresso, here I toyed around with shorter shots trying to make the most of the cocoa notes and body but it fell a bit flat for me, the complexity was lost. In the end I settled on pulling a little longer around 1:2.75 - at a medium heat with a decent preinfusion. This sacrificed a little in mouthfeel and body but more than made up for it in sweetness. As a coffee I found it very easy to dial in and was very forgiving. It seemed to be quite insensitive to grind size change, I had to move my settings quite a lot to notice a difference with this coffee. In the cup the tropical fruits came out a little bit more, however it is not a &quot;loud&quot; coffee and don't go expecting real deep funky notes. The &quot;black forest&quot; vibe is certainly still there and still the first thing I notice when tasting. Again it is a clean coffee and the aftertaste does not linger too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a complex and interesting coffee and one I'm glad I picked up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we are heading back to 2014 through the &quot;Riverside&quot; album from Dave Douglas and Chet Doxas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/021-Riverside/Riverside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project Douglas and Doxas pay tribute to Jimmy Giuffre. However unlike many other &quot;tribute&quot; albums this album is not just a rehash of Giuffre's tunes: instead all but 2 tracks are originals. There is only one Giuffre composition (&quot;The Train and the River&quot;) and one Johnny Mercer standard (&quot;Travelin' Light&quot;) which was a favourite of Giuffre. While the back catalogue of Jimmy Giuffre is fairly broad (from big band, through cool and even free-jazz) - on &quot;Riverside&quot; they pay homage to the blues-folk influenced stylings, but in a more &quot;modern&quot; style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The line up on the album is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dave Douglas - trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chet Doxas - clarinet, saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steve Swallow - electric bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jim Doxas - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dave Douglas is a fairly &quot;big&quot; name in modern jazz. His back catalogue is extensive covering just about every jazz sub-genre you can think of and has worked with many other artists both old and new: from John Zorn, Bill Frisell, Lee Konitz, Joe Lovano, Horace Silver and many others. He also has a background as an educator working with various universities and music institutions and also has his own record label &quot;Greenleaf Music&quot; (on which &quot;Riverside&quot; is released) which is one of my favourite current jazz labels. It is hard to summarize the Douglas &quot;sound&quot; or &quot;style&quot; in a way that does him justice given the breadth of his experience - however he typically focuses on a powerful big sound and often plays with a great deal of swagger. If you ever get a chance to see him perform live (regardless of the project) you should jump at it, he always puts on a show and is one of the most consistent out there. I try and catch him when he comes to town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Riverside&quot; appears under both Douglas and Doxas names - I have to be honest I know very little about Chet Doxas (and his brother Jim on drums). He has a relatively small back catalogue - but I've enjoyed everything I've heard to date. It may be a case that &quot;less is more&quot;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Swallow is the &quot;veteran&quot; of this line up; having worked from 1960 onwards. In fact he previously worked with Jimmy Giuffre fairly extensively which gives this album an air of authenticity. He is also known for working with Paul Bley, John Scofield, Steve Kuhn, Carla Bley and Gary Burton (among others) and has a sizeable career as a leader. He was one of the first jazz bassists to move to electric bass exclusively - and one of only a select few who plays a 5 string bass. He has a style that I would describe as intricate but relaxed, often opting to play chords when comping and playing in the very high register when soloing. He genuinely plays softly with contemplation rather than opting for big powerful bass lines. It is a sound all to himself and is instantly recognisable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &quot;Riverside&quot; the writing duties are split roughly 50:50 between Douglas and Doxas and the album has essentially 2 speeds: an upbeat chaotic swing of Douglas and the slower more meditative approach of Doxas. &quot;Handwritten Letter&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) is a prime example of the Douglas approach. The main melody is an uptempo high energy affair but there are many twists and turns as the tune progresses. The rhythmic interplay is a key feature of the album and brings a playful feel to proceedings.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3Mjkn0OX8N4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The tune &quot;Old Church, New Paint&quot; shows off the groups softer side with a down-tempo comtemplative ballad with a nod towards gospel. Doxas plays with a beautiful breath-y tone, meanwhile Douglas playing some great counter-point. The use of counter-point melody is something that appears frequently throughout the record. The rhythm section of Doxas and Swallow keeps the whole tune swinging with a blues tilt. There is a lead-in track to this piece that features a beautiful solo from Steve Swallow and gives him a chance to flex some of his chops, something that does not appear too often on this album with Douglas and Doxas taking most of the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall it is a fantastic album, slightly overlooked at the time so well deserving of a second listen. This is the sort of album that can satisfy in a number of ways: it is quite &quot;easy&quot; to listen to as it is focussed on blues-folk yet behind this there are some really interesting rhythmic and counter-point ideas should you want to investigate further. There has since been a second album for the Riverside project called &quot;The New National Anthem&quot; where they look at the work of Carla Bley - also worthy of your time.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BUolZzqECyQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/021-Riverside/Riverside.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/021-Riverside/Riverside.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Real McCoy and PLOT Gelana Gesha</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/the-real-mccoy-gelana" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Real McCoy and PLOT Gelana Gesha" /><published>2020-08-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/The-Real-McCoy-Gelana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/the-real-mccoy-gelana">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-08-29-The-Real-McCoy-Gelana.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/73VczRfu9Kg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Welcome to the 20th JazzCoffeeStuff post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week we are back to PLOT coffee roasting again. If you have read the previous blog posts you'll notice that (at the moment) there is little variation in roasters appearing on this page: this is intentional given the global situation. I recommend everybody support the businesses they like as it is a tough time for coffee roasters. As such I'm doing less &quot;exploring&quot; and am spending more of my coffee money on the usual suspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto more positive notes: this week the coffee we're looking at is kind of interesting. It is a coffee from Ethiopia and from the Israel Degfa empire. I (partly) joke about calling it an empire, Israel owns a company Kerchanshe Trading who own a number of washing stations and mills throughout Ethiopia. If you are looking at high quality coffee from this region it won't take you long to come across the Israel Degfa name. Over the past few years he has been working tirelessly to improve the quality of coffee being produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this instance the coffee we're looking at today is a natural process from the Gelana woreda in the (west) Guji zone of the Oromia Region. Guji is highly synonymous with high quality coffee and has featured on this blog in the past. Gelana is a small area that benefits from decent rainfall and fertile soil which is a good starting point for growing high quality coffee plants. Israel decided that this particular farm was a prime location to experiment and decided to plant a large number of Gesha plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have talked about varietals in the past, but I believe this is the first Gesha we have featured on the blog. Gesha first came onto the scene around 2004 through the prized Panama farm Hacienda La Esmeralda. On the cupping table it produced such vibrant floral notes that many thought somebody had &quot;smuggled&quot; some Ethiopian coffee onto the table and it couldn't possibly be produced in Panama. This sparked an obssession with the varietal and quickly Gesha lots became the hottest lots in auctions reaching crazy price levels. Through the end of the 2000s and 2010s barista competitions essentially became &quot;Gesha  shows&quot; - if you wanted to place you needed to have a special Gesha coffee to show off! But what is so special about Gesha itself? It originally hails from Ethiopia, first identified in the 1930s, samples got sent to Costa Rica in the 1950s and Panama planted samples as early as 1960s. The Gesha varietal is synonymous with &quot;floral&quot; notes particularly jasmine and bergamot and is almost always fruit focussed. They tend to be very perfumed with a big bouquet, as a result they regularly score in the 90s for SCA cup scores (remember 80 is the cutoff for specialty, getting into the 90s is incredibly rare &amp;lt;1% of coffee produced each year globally gets into this bracket - essentially the best of the best).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is particularly interesting about this coffee from PLOT is the price; for a Gesha it is simply outstanding value - it is the same price as their &quot;regular&quot; coffees. I'm not sure I've ever found a Gesha at this price point before so I was very eager to try it. Although I admit I was a little skeptical, like if you find a Ferarri in the autotrader for £1000. But given the last few coffees from PLOT I considered this a &quot;risk&quot; worth taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a dry aroma from the ground beans the fragrance is a little subdued, this is something I regularly notice about Gesha coffees - they tend to be quite &quot;polite&quot; and never punch you in the face. There is certainly a peach note and also, as expected, the jasmine floral note. Another thing I instantly notice: this coffee is a very light roast, this is certainly one you could consider the mythical &quot;nordic roast&quot; style. Onto the filter, as usual a chemex filter type, the resulting coffee is clean as they come, there isn't a hint of &quot;funk&quot; from the natural processing. I would describe the flavour profile as relatively subtle but certainly complex. The main overiding flavour note for me is peach, it is like biting into a ripe juicy peach. As the cup cools the florals come out to play and it takes on an elderflower cordial sort of vibe - the sweetness of this coffee taking on that sticky almost jammy quality. What I found most astounding however was the aftertaste: out of nowhere a ripe banana note comes out. It is only evident in the aftertaste and there is no hint of it before, it is really suprising but unmistakable for me. This is a note that PLOT did not list on the bag but for me it's one of the major characters of the coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso, a coffee roast this light can be a nightmare to dial in and you're left with a &quot;sweetspot&quot; living on a knife-edge with even the slightest change in puck-prep throwing the whole shot off. Fortunately this one was surprisingly easy to dial in on my setup, I didn't have any issues at all. In the end I settled for a 1:2.75 ratio out in 24s with my machine on maximum temperature. As with the filter the major flavour note for me was peach, the shot was super sweet with just enough acidity not to be cloying. Again it was a super clean flavour profile and there was little in the way of body or mouthfeel. Again the ripe banana note came out during the aftertaste but was slightly less pronounced in the espresso, the aftertaste of the filter lingered whereas the aftertaste of the espresso was fairly shortlived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this was a very interesting and delicious coffee. On the face of it a very simple delicate flavour profile but there was enough complexity there to keep you entertained too. It is certainly worth trying if it is still available as you read this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we are heading back to 1960s Blue Note with a hard-bop classic from McCoy Tyner: &quot;The Real McCoy&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/020-The-Real-McCoy/The-Real-McCoy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McCoy Tyner is probably best known for being the pianist in the John Coltrane band - where he featured on many seminal albums such as &quot;My Favourite Things&quot;, &quot;Africa/Brass&quot; and &quot;Love Supreme&quot;, all of which are worthy of a blog post to themselves. He also had many other dates as a sideman for the likes of Wayne Shorter, Lee Morgan, Hank Mobley, Freddie Hubbard and Joe Henderson along with many others. Today however we are focussed on his solo career which was equally prolific. &quot;The Real McCoy&quot; was released in 1967, some 2 years after he left the John Coltrane band. It was during this time he began to find his own voice as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is safe to say McCoy is certainly in the &quot;modal&quot; school of post-bop jazz - for those who do not know music theory: a mode is essentially a degree of a scale, for example taking the major scale (&quot;do, ri, me, ...&quot;) there are seven associated &quot;modes&quot; of this scale depending on which note is the root (&quot;home&quot; note). Each mode has its own flavour/mood, in a modal composition we take a specific mode and build the entire tune around that, this gives pieces a specific &quot;mood&quot; or &quot;feeling&quot;. This is in contrast to, say, be-bop where the focus is on chord changes and the melody follows the structure of the chord and so a composition may feature many different scales in passing. Modal jazz became very popular with post-bop artists and even many modern records still use a modal concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another factor of McCoy's playing is his powerful left hand playing, he often relies on big choppy chords to drive the pieces forward. This often brings an authoritative punch to the compositions and drives the music forward. There is a certain &quot;stride&quot; influence to this but it is certainly his own sound and it is unmistakable, you can often hear other players doing a &quot;McCoy impression&quot; but never quite getting it right. Of course another big part of his playing is his reliance on fourth intervals that appear throughout his work, many of his chord voicings are based around the idea of stacking fourths - he even has an album named &quot;Reaching Fourth&quot; so they clearly meant a lot to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at the rest of the line up on this album now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McCoy Tyner - piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Henderson - tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ron Carter - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elvin Jones - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the majority of albums featured on this blog: this line up is stellar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have read any of the previous blog posts you'll know about Joe Henderson at this point, one of my favourite artists of all time. As you'd expect Joe's improvisation is top notch playing some really intricate and interesting lines, he doesn't get quite as &quot;free&quot; as he does on his own albums (understandably) but he matches perfectly the energy of Tyner throughout. Joe is one of those players who is equally talented as a sideman (by not taking the spotlight away from the named artist) and leading a band himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then on the bass there is Ron Carter, again a legend who has appeared on this blog on numerous posts (although not yet as a solo artist). The magic in Carter's playing for me is his ability to accompany other players, it is an often underappreciated skill. The best accompanists have a quality that I like to describe as &quot;holding up a mirror&quot; where they manage to allow the soloing musician to sound &quot;even more like themselves&quot; - Ron has this ability in abundance. This is certainly on display in this album where you have McCoy's compositions being fairly harmonically dense and frantic solos from McCoy and Joe - if Ron came to the session with ego and not willing to allow the others to speak it could quickly turn into a car crash. The other aspect of Carter's playing that is so impressive to me is his command of rhythm, he can really find the pocket when things get complicated. He is certianly deserving of his reputation as one of the finest bass players in jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly we have drummer Elvin Jones. Without doubt one of my absolute favourite drummers of all time. Like McCoy, Elvin spent much of his early career playing as a sideman with some of the great artists: in the 1950s with Miles Davis and Sonny Rollins (appearing on the &quot;A Night at the Village Vanguard&quot; - an all time classic) and the 1960s appearing in the John Coltrane band alongside McCoy. Again the list of artists and albums he has worked with and on is basically a &quot;who's who&quot; of jazz. His playing style is very fluid, playing legato like phrases on the drums. This gives him a rubbery slippery sound that influenced jazz (and other genres) for decades afterwards and still to this day. He manages to maintain this quality while playing sophisticated polyrhymic ideas, which is not easy to do. With complex ideas like this it is very easy for the drumming to begin to sound &quot;robotic&quot; but Elvin keeps things swinging. However Elvin also had the ability to play thunderous and powerful lines when required, he was far from a &quot;one trick pony&quot;. Without a doubt one of the best drummers of all time, not just in the jazz world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album starts with &quot;Passion Dance&quot; (embedded at the start of this blog) which is the opening track and one of the album's highlights. It is a fairly dense piece with a complicated melody, however it is essentially a blueprint on band interaction and connection. Each player is solely concerned with lifting the music and not themselves. This is perhaps most evident with the rhythmic interplay between McCoy and Elvin. Joe takes a blistering solo too, tap-dancing through the chaos to play something beautiful. This focus on connection is evident throughout the album, while some of the other compositions may be less manic there is always a sense of cohesion and togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another tune that sticks out for me on this album is the closing track: &quot;Blues on The Corner&quot;

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/64lWx44RjdU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As the name suggests this is a take on the blues, however as you'd expect it is a little more sophisticated than that. While Elvin showed off his power in &quot;Passion Dance&quot; here he shows just how hard he can swing on a blues. Ron is playing with complete attitude too which gives McCoy the freedom to explore harmonically while keeping things grounded. Joe also takes the opportunity to play with his characteristic wolf notes and &quot;outside&quot; playing, it is perhaps one of the best solos he's taken and with his repertoire that is really saying something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the 2 tunes outlined here are fairly up-tempo and wild, this album also features 2 beautiful ballads. I find the modal paradigm really lends itself to ballads - it is very easy to create a &quot;mood&quot; and give the piece some character. On this album we have &quot;Contemplation&quot; and &quot;Search for Peace&quot; both of which are fantastic example of hard-bop ballads. Overall you cannot go wrong with any track on this album each one is a classic. This makes, in my opinion, &quot;The Real McCoy&quot; absolutely essential listening for anybody interested in jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2020)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/020-The-Real-McCoy/The-Real-McCoy.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/020-The-Real-McCoy/The-Real-McCoy.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>