<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-17T05:52:20-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Rubber Soulive and Andrea Cortes</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/rubber-soulive-adreas-cortes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rubber Soulive and Andrea Cortes" /><published>2021-04-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Rubber-Soulive-Adreas-Cortes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/rubber-soulive-adreas-cortes">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-04-17-Rubber-Soulive-Adreas-Cortes.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rbE8A4U-OAI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are looking at another coffee from Plot Coffee Roasting. I initially did not intend to write about this coffee on the blog, I was keeping it as my &quot;espresso option&quot; while enjoying the Icon Series 4 from last week's blog. However 2 things forced it up the agenda: 1) it is a cool and interesting coffee and 2) I need a bit more time to dial in the next coffee I am going to write about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee this week is called: Andreas Cortes - Pink Bourbon by Plot themselves. Andreas being owner of Finca Eucaliptos in Pitaltio, Huila, Colombia - where this coffee originates. By this point you'll also realise we're looking at a pink bourbon cultivar. Pink bourbon is a hybrid of the more common red and yellow bourbons (named after the colour of their fruit). This hybrid is hard to grow and hard to isolate so it is relatively rare. It is noted, however, that it generally offers high cup scores and has shown good (or at least better) resistance to leaf rust - which is of course a big bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself undergoes a 24 hour resting period before being de-pulped and fermented for 60 hours in sealed bags before being fully washed and dried on patios for 18 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving straight into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I don't get a huge amount of anything coming off. I would describe it mostly as a &quot;neutral sweet&quot; quality, like opening a bag of caster sugar. With a bit more focus you can just about pick off some citrus and floral notes but they are very feint. As we've stated many times before: this doesn't necessarily mean much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the filter option: forewarning here - I only had 1 cup of filter from this coffee, so these are genuine initial responses. The first thing I jotted down with this coffee was &quot;clean&quot; - not just due to flavour clarity but profile too. There is a big citrus-y hit in the front, pink grapefruits and lemons mostly. These give a very clean quality to the cup. Following that I get a bit of a resin-y pine-needle sort of quality, again giving a fresh and airy vibe to the cup. In the aftertaste there are delicate floral notes that, while not particularly strong, do have staying power. In terms of sweetness vs acidity - for me it lies a little more to the acidic side but there is a plenty of sweetness in this cup too. The mouthfeel is quite big, adding to the resin-y pine-needle note I mentioned previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my time with this coffee has been via espresso - to me this is where this coffee is right at home. Dialling it in is a little finnicky, it is a light roast designed for filter primarily, and you need to whack the machine temp right up (one day I forgot to do this and left the machine cool from a dark decaf roast I was drinking the previous night - it did not work well with this coffee at all). In terms of ratio I got to about 1:2.25 as a sweetspot, 7s pre-infuse then a 27s pull. The results are outstanding. The shot is extremely vibrant and zingy, sort of like a very crisp lemonade with a big slice of pink-grapefruit in it. I could see some people despising this as an espresso for being too acidic and bright but I enjoyed it a lot. While it's bright and crisp it doesn't stray into &quot;battery acid&quot; territory at all for me. Even when I didn't nail it when dialing in the results were just a bit flat as opposed to being a sink job. The margin between fantastic and average with this one are quite fine though I found, it took me a few shots to really get things where they needed to be - but then I was handsomely rewarded for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I dug out a record from 2010 from the band Soulive, in the form of their tribute to The Beatles: &quot;Rubber Soulive&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/052-Rubber-Soulive/Rubber-Soulive.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit I was late to the Soulive party. The band started by releasing their debut EP in 1999 with their debut LP coming a year later. I knew of them around the mid-2000s but didn't really give them much attention at that time, Medeski Martin and Wood were more my thing so I was pretty big on them. It wasn't until the late 2000s when I really became aware of them. I was working on a new musical project at the time and the bassist of the band lent me a pile of CDs of his biggest influences - a couple of these were Soulive records, and I became to realise what I had been missing out on.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wXGwagOpjQs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As you could likely guess from the name: &quot;Soulive&quot; are largely in the &quot;Soul Jazz&quot; mold. They tend to have catchy, uptempo tunes that span jazz-soul-funk-rock. They have experimented (a lot) with additional musicians and vocalists over the years but the core of the band is an organ trio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alan Evans - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neil Evans - Organ/Piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eric Kranso - Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is the lineup featuring on &quot;Rubber Soulive&quot;. They rip through 11 tunes from The Beatles back catalogue, sticking solely to the &quot;big hits&quot; rather than finding the more obscure tracks. As you would expect from a jazz-funk band the focus is well and truly on the groove, if you're looking for a complex re-harmonization of Lennon pieces this is not the one for you. But if you want a groovy jam-band party atmosphere and some familiar melodies you could do a lot worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my choice cuts on the album is &quot;Revolution&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). Likely everybody will be fairly familiar with this track already so it is not easy to take it in a new direction. The Soulive boys decided instead of leaning into the strong rock-beat of the original they would take it into an RnB direction with a Booker T and the MGs style groove. If you can get through this tune without tapping your feet you are a better man than I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fun track on the album is &quot;Help&quot; (above). Here Soulive go for a tongue-in-cheek swing feeling, almost with a lounge-jazz vibe. As the track goes onthe energy increases and by the end Alan is using a really strong and driving drum beat. The whole track is a lot of fun but also features some rather tasty organ playing from Neil. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jZsKLJIyeU8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Of course the greatest of all The Beatles is George Harrison and there are 3 of his tunes covered on this album. Perhaps the most adventurous of these being the album closer: &quot;While My Guitar Gently Weeps&quot; (above). A tune that has been covered to death at this point, with basically every guitar player having played it at some point. It is therefore quite difficult to come up with a &quot;fresh&quot; take on it, but I feel Soulive achieve that here. They stick pretty closely to the original melody and harmony throughout. Instead adding colour through groove and timbre. Some of Eric's phrasing in particular is very tasty, as are the tasteful use of effects which add rather than detract from the piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a fun little album to check out. It's not one that will require a great deal of effort to listen to, just an easy &quot;feel good&quot; sort of album. Not all jazz need be complicated and require a great deal of effort to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/052-Rubber-Soulive/Rubber-Soulive.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/052-Rubber-Soulive/Rubber-Soulive.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">In N Out and Icon 4</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/in-n-out-icon-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In N Out and Icon 4" /><published>2021-04-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/In-N-Out-Icon-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/in-n-out-icon-4">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-04-10-In-N-Out-Icon-4.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/k8ntRkcOG-4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This coming friday (16th April) marks the first anniversary of the JazzCoffeeStuff blog! Unintentionally this coincides with another special coffee from Plot Coffee Roasting through their Icon series. As you may remember the Icon series is a &quot;150g a month&quot; subscription offered by Plot featuring some of the most sought after and rare coffees availavle. This is the 4th edition of this series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee in question is from Ecuador, an origin that may not be familiar to some. Most think of cacao rather than coffee from Ecuador, but those familiar with the specialty coffee scene know that there are some fantastic coffees to be had. Perhaps what is most interesting about this coffee is the cultivar: Typica Mejorado. I admit that I don't think I've ever tried this particular cultivar before, apparently a cross between Bourbon and an unknown Ethiopian landrace. Certainly an intriguing proposition given the cup quality of both of these cultivars. Interestingly, doing some research a few sources claim that it is a cross between Bourbon and Gesha - but this seems to be speculative at best (although would likely help achieve a higher price for the coffee).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processing here is a natural. Ecuador has a fairly humid climate which makes natural processing problematic. This coffee undergoes a dry fermentation for 48 hours before spending 15 days in a solar powered drying chamber that exactly controls the coffees environment. Following this the coffee spends the rest of the time on raised African beds within a polytunnel. This sort of attention to detail at the processing stage is really what sets some of these super high scoring coffees a part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's just dive right in: on the dry aroma I get a strong punch of honey straight off the bat. In addition I get the sort of floral notes one would ordinarily associate with Ethiopian coffees. This coffee is off to a good start, as usual we move on to my usual pour-over - I'm currently still on Hario v60 papers instead of my usual chemex due to supply chain issues but have been appreciating the change. Taking the first sip immediately I'm struck by how sweet this coffee is, it is syrup-y sugar-y and honey-y. This is up there as one of the sweetest coffees I've had in a while, if you like sweetness it is one for you. In terms of flavour profile the honey-floral combo is certainly there - a hit of honey at the front which mellows to perfumed florals in the aftertaste. In the middle however it is a bit of a fruit bomb: strawberry is certainly present, apricots too, mangos and papaya make a bit of a showing. There is a lot going on in the cup, it is one that you should really sit down and savour but it is surprisingly easy to drink too. In terms of acidity I would describe it as low or at a push medium, there's so much sweetness it's kind of hard to notice the acidity in my opinion. The body is quite high but not one of those coffees that you can chew on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with previous Icon coffees I didn't make any espresso, next week's blog post should feature some espresso goodness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet again Plot knock it out of the park with their Icon series. 4 out of 4 bangers so far, and I am looking forward to next month's offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this friday marks the one year anniversary of JazzCoffeeStuff, on the jazz side I thought we should head back to the first artist featured: Joe Henderson with another of his Blue Note recordings &quot;In 'N Out&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/051-InNOut/InNOut.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before even getting into the music itself it is worth taking a moment to appreciate the album artwork. One of my favourite covers in the history of Blue Note, a near perfect example of the Reid Miles aesthetic. It still looks as fresh today as it did when the album was released in January 1965.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I make no apologies: I am a huge Joe Henderson fan. My love for his playing can be summed up in the title of this album: &quot;In 'N Out&quot; - for me nobody before or since has had the ability to walk the line between inside and outside playing. He has the ability to play the craziest free-jazz lines fit with the most pedestrian chord changes, and meanwhile play an absolutely pure and simple melody in the midst of a free-jazz frenzy. Sometimes he even can start a lick playing a blues and by the end be in the realms of avant-garde - and you don't even notice it. This is especially true for his playing on Blue Note around this period, you can pick up any record he appears on during this time and you'll be blown away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &quot;In 'N Out&quot; the supporting cast isn't too shabby either: on trumpet you have regular stable-mate Kenny Dorham, with whom Joe recorded many times - all of which magical. On piano we have McCoy Tyner - one of the true stars of the hard-bop era and again appears regularly with Joe. On the bass we have Richard Davis who has played on records spanning all of the sub-genres of jazz from bop to free. On the drums is Elvin Jones - possibly my favourite drummer of all time, he always finds a unique way of swinging and can only be described as a jazz legend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with the title track (embedded at the start of this post). It kicks off with a time-twisting hard-bop type melody with Joe and Kenny in unison (showing off their near telepathic communication). This is on top of a typical Elvin swing - his way of emphasing the beat gives the melody a hurried chaotic feeling. It doesn't take too long to get into Joe's first solo on the album. It features all the hallmarks of his playing: short stabby phrases, the unpredictable use of space, large intervals, ghost notes and trills. With so many &quot;tricks&quot; like these it's amazing at how well Joe can construct a solo, it's completely logical and flows from one idea to the next. McCoy then takes his turn, again sticking to his tried and tested use of fourths (mostly). Kenny then takes his turn with perhaps one of the most daring solos in his back catalogue. Typically you associate Kenny with the latin-influenced music and sticking fairly close to the melody but here he gets a little more experimental.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/78N6qHZdxYY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The album itself consists of 2 parts: the first 3 tracks being tunes penned by Henderson himself and the last 2 by Dorham. As one would expect the Dorham tunes feature a latin and bossa feel, in contrast to the hard-bop/free sound of the Henderson pieces. One of the Dorham pieces is &quot;Short Story&quot; (above).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Short Story&quot; is typical Dorham through and through but the personnel on this album takes it in a different direction. You have Elvin's drum beats adding a unique flavour to the latin piece. It would have been easy to just stick to the &quot;typical&quot; drum beats featured in latin jazz but Elvin's genius gives the piece a sort of rhythmic tension which can be released at any moment. You also have McCoy's &quot;modal chord&quot; style of comping which gives the piece an almost &quot;dream like&quot; feel. Then you have Davis' bass hook which is a real ear-worm. This sets the stage for the main soloists to show off their personality: Dorham sticks largely to the chord tones and stays inside, playing pretty phrases. In contrast Joe starts off well behaved but before long starts breaking out the wolf-notes and wild rollercoaster bop lines. The Henderson/Dorham partnership is something that will never get old, they just seemed to raise each other up every time they played together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one downside of &quot;In 'N Out&quot; is its brevity at just 5 tracks and around 38 minutes (reissues featuring an additional 9 minutes with an alternate take of the title track). In spite of this &quot;In 'N Out&quot; is an all time classic for me and one well worth your time to hunt down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/051-InNOut/InNOut.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/051-InNOut/InNOut.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Basra and Laura Nilva Paye</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/basra-laura-nilva-paye" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basra and Laura Nilva Paye" /><published>2021-04-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Basra-Laura-Nilva-Paye</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/basra-laura-nilva-paye">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-04-03-Basra-Laura-Nilva-Paye.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/390UPSAD0OI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are yet again visiting Plot Coffee Roasters - a near constant feature in the blog as of late. This time we have a rather neat competition winning lot from Peru. The lot is from Laura Nilva Paye located in the Puno department of the country. In terms of location this is the south easterly corner of Peru, close to the border with Bolivia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cultivar of this coffee is Bourbon. I have been reminded that my sloppy use of the word &quot;varietal&quot; is technically incorrect when referring to coffee. In layman's terms the difference between &quot;varietal&quot; and &quot;cultivar&quot; is the presence of human intervention - in coffee (essentially) all coffee plants have been selectively bred, hence they should be referred to as &quot;cultivar&quot; as opposed to &quot;varietal&quot;. This is something I often forget and end up referring to varietal but I'll try and be more precise in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plot label this coffee as a &quot;washed&quot; process, however looking into the details the coffee has been depulped and fermented for 20-24 hours before being washed. In that sense it is a little more &quot;honey&quot; than many washed coffees available. Following the washing stage the coffee is dried under shade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's not hang around but get straight down to business: on the dry aroma I get sweet caramel and peaches, but they are very feint. Overall the coffee doesn't have a huge bouquet when compared to others, but it is very appealling I have a sense this will be a coffee I'll like. As I've said before the dry aroma (or lack thereof) doesn't necessarily align with what ends up in the cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the filter; it is clear to see how much quality is in this cup. It is very clean and clear, every flavour is well defined. The first thing that hits me is the sweetness, it has a very sticky-sweet vibe like a really ripe peach or even a peach syrup. After the intial stone fruit hit subsides you're left with a stunning floral finish which is clean and long lasting. The notes from Plot say: &quot;a flavour profile more akin to Ethiopia than Peru&quot; and it is very hard to argue with that. In terms of acidity I would describe it as a medium, or it may be that all the sweetness just offsets it. Eitherway it is a very easy cup to drink but also has layers of complexity to keep you entertained. I find it's best enjoyed at a slightly cooler temperature, straight out of the brewer the flavours get a bit too muddled for my tastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto espresso: I found it basically impossible to get a bad shot out of this. You can basically pull it however you like, with any grind setting and it'll be great. I was without electricity for a day and even pulled a shot on my cafelat robot and it was perhaps the best shot I had. I love the robot as a manual espresso maker, but I struggle with the lighter filter roasts I favour for espresso because it is hard to keep the temperature high enough. No problem with this coffee though, it still extracted perfectly. I found most enjoyment pulling the shots a little shorter that 1:2 to get a more luxurious caramel mouthfeel. The flavour profile in the cup is pure condensed peach and apricot. It is like a shot of peach syrup, incredibly high sweetness, just enough balancing acidity and no harshness at all. As much as I enjoyed this coffee in a filter, for me it really shone as an espresso - up there with the best of the year so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we're heading back to a classic Blue Note recording from 1965 - &quot;Basra&quot; by Pete La Roca.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/050-Basra/Basra.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pete &quot;La Roca&quot; Sims is a drummer/percussionist - he is best known as a sideman having appeared alongside some of the all time greats: Sonny Rollins (Roca appeared albeit briefly on &quot;Live at the Vanguard&quot;), Joe Henderson (on &quot;Page One&quot;), Jackie McLean, Bill Evans, Sonny Clark and so on. He started his career however playing in latin bands, an influence that came through in his playing throughout his career. There are a few things interesting about Pete: firstly he despised the name &quot;La Roca&quot; - he came up with the moniker early in his career and it is how most people knew him, but he regretted it in later life. Secondly he was in some sense a &quot;part timer&quot; - throughout the 60s he made money as an NY taxi driver and later became a lawyer in the 70s returning to jazz just once after this.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3M1O7InNT14&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;La Roca&quot; only has 3 albums under his own name, and one of those was erroniously labelled as a &quot;Chick Corea&quot; album by the record label initially. It's for that reason I consider &quot;Basra&quot; to be a bit of an &quot;under the radar classic&quot;. I'm not a fan of labels like &quot;under the radar&quot; or &quot;underrated&quot; since they always bring out arguments of &quot;XXXX is less well known, so this isn't underrated&quot; eventually devolving into an excuse for showing how obscure ones musical tastes are. I consider &quot;Basra&quot; an &quot;under the radar classic&quot; however, because almost every &quot;experienced&quot; jazz fan I know loves the album but it will rarely (if ever) feature on a &quot;top 100 albums&quot; list and &quot;La Roca&quot; will never feature in a list of artists you &quot;have to hear&quot; - as a result this is an album that many do not discover until much later in their jazz journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what makes the album so special? Firstly the line up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pete &quot;La Roca&quot; - Drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Henderson - Tenor Sax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steve Swallow - Bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steve Kuhn - Piano
As with many Blue Note recordings from around this time: a true heavyweight line-up. But more than that: &quot;Basra&quot; features some truly explorative playing. It is not your typical &quot;hard bop&quot; album, the is a darker brooding attitude and vibe throughout. The players also lean into the avant-garde/free styles more than many other albums of the period. But more than that there are influences outside of the typical &quot;jazz&quot; paradigm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps most evident in the title track &quot;Basra&quot; (embedded at the start of the blog). A take on Middle Eastern classical music it is based around one chord and captures the &quot;meditative&quot; essence of the style. The &quot;blank canvas&quot; allows Joe to carve out any line he wants and it is some of the best lead playing you'll hear from Henderson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the firey &quot;Malaguena&quot; (above) which is a piece originally penned by Cuban composer Ernesto Lecuona (again &quot;La Roca&quot; tipping his hat towards the latin music he played in his early career.) Again Joe plays out of his skin and there are plenty of &quot;Henderson-isms&quot; throughout which is no bad thing. The piece manages to be energetic without being high tempo, the quartet masterfully keeps racheting up the tension as it goes on but somehow manages to swing. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/briljflpx2s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Basra&quot; also features the original recording of the Swallow tune: &quot;Eiderdown&quot; which later went on to be a Swallow signature tune and a standard in its own right. It is interesting to hear it in its &quot;original&quot; form here. It is perhaps the most &quot;straight ahead&quot; of all the tunes on the album and Swallow's bass keeps the tune driving forward in his own inimitable way. This is also one of the recordings shortly before Steve switched to electric bass entirely, so it is nice to hear him play with an acoustic instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all &quot;Basra&quot; is, in my opinion, one of the greatest recordings on Blue Note. Definitely hunt out a copy through whatever medium you use to consume your music. It is a shame we have so few records of &quot;La Roca&quot; under his own name, it would have been great to see where he would have taken his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/050-Basra/Basra.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/050-Basra/Basra.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sun Blowing and Morgon</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/sun-blowing-morgon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sun Blowing and Morgon" /><published>2021-03-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Sun-Blowing-Morgon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/sun-blowing-morgon">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-03-27-Sun-Blowing-Morgon.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iZxqTWYV7w4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are back with another installment of the KaffeBox subscription. Recall the KaffeBox subscription highlights a different Scandinavian roaster each month. This month was particularly exciting for me since it featured one of my all time favourite roasters: Morgon Coffee Roasters - who I do not buy from nearly enough due to the logistics of getting the coffee here to London. The roastery is located in Gotherburg, Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that I noticed about Morgon is their aesthetic vision. Everything from their website, to instagram account to the bags themselves are really well put together. Each bag is blue in colour and features a picture depicting the flavour profile of the coffee inside. The images are really works of art in themselves, and this gives the impression of great quality even before opening the bag. As an example, here is an image from one of the bags we are looking at today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/049-Sun-Blowing/Ferney-Cruz.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly some of the best looking packaging out there in my mind. As with previous KaffeBox subscriptions I have 2 different 125g bags to play around with. This is not enough to dial in an espresso and make filter coffees with so I split the coffees - one for espresso duties and one for filter duties. This time I did it at random, when making the first filter coffee I just reached for a bag on the shelf and that's how it was assigned. Note that both coffees are &quot;filter&quot; roast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the filter option: we have a washed Ethiopian coffee from the Uraga Raro washing station located in the Guji zone - an area that crops up frequently on this blog. Morgon don't provide much more information than that, which is not a problem - we can move swiftly on to what matters: the coffee itself. On the dry aroma you get your &quot;typical&quot; washed Ethiopian qualities: citrus fruits and florals. As you would expect it is not a really punchy hard hitting coffee on the nose. In the cup you get everything you expect from a coffee like this: elegant earl-grey tea-like flavours, citrus-y blood orange and grapefruit sharpness and a very refined balance to the cup. This is just a top drawer example of what washed Ethiopian coffees are all about, there is so much clarity it allows the complexity to come through and allows you to enjoy the cup at the cooler temperatures. This is what I like and respect about the Morgon offerings I've had in the past - they're just completely dependable. They seem to respect the origin and each one is a top quality example of what a particular region is all about. No nonsense, just really good quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have a washed Caturra from Colombia - Ferney Cruz. Again not a whole lot of information here so we'll dive right in. On the nose I get hits of sweet &quot;red&quot; fruits like strawberry, raspberry and rhubarb, again it's not a big hitter but certainly enough to draw you in. Dialing this one in for espresso was a bit of a pain, this is a coffee where you need to set your grinder very fine. I was just past the point of burrs touching and I could just about wrestle a 1:2 in 27s sort of profile out of it. Being a filter roast however, it seems to benefit from a bit of a longer pull. 1:2.5 seems to work best in around 25s with the machine at full temperature. The resulting shot is syrupy sweet. The flavour profile is full of raspberry and rhubarb - if you imagine a pineapple cube sweet but made with rhubarb I don't think you'd be far off the mark. Again the coffee is very clean, especially in the aftertaste - qualities I like in a coffee. Again it is just a very very good example of a clean washed coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was very happy to drink some more Morgon coffees this month, it reminds me that I should order from them more often. If you're after &quot;fireworks&quot;, crazy processing, loud punchy flavours - Morgon probably aren't the ones to go to (at least in my experience). But if you want complete quality and elegant clean cups Morgon are certainly up there with the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I found myself digging out an album from 2016 by the trio of Lars Danielsson, Marius Neset and Morten Lund on the ACT label - &quot;Sun Blowing&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/049-Sun-Blowing/Sun-Blowing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story behind this album is that Danielsson, Neset and Lund met by chance on a train in 2012 - they had not met each other before, let alone played together. Two years after this happy accident they decided to record &quot;Sun Blowing&quot; - representing an &quot;intial encounter&quot; in the studio. The line-up here represents a &quot;tenor-sax-trio&quot; format with Neset on tenor, Danielsson on bass and Lund on drums. We have spoken about trio formats like this in the past on this blog - many sax players try and play in this context but few succeed. With so much space and freedom it really exposes the sax so you need to be on top of your game. Neset, however, is no ordinary sax player. A bit of a &quot;prodigy&quot; and one of the most accomplished young sax players out there. In contrast to his solo work which typically contains large ensembles, it is rare to see Neset play in such an intimate setting.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EqCQnjVxXQE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Being a &quot;first encounter&quot; there is a lot of energy and vibrancy on show on the album. As you'd expect from a trio of this format there is a big influence from the tenor greats: Coltrane, Rollins, Brecker, Henderson and so on. However there is also a lot of influence from the avant-garde and free sides too particularly from the early ECM records. While it would be easy to release an album of Neset just blowing over changes and showing off his chops, the guys here have worked on creating actual tunes. I think of Neset as a very thematic player, although he has chops his primary focus seems to be on creating themes and movements in the music. This gives his playing a &quot;story-telling&quot; sort of quality, this makes the tunes very memorable and they often stick in your head for days after hearing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with &quot;Little Jump&quot; (embedded at the start of this post), here Neset's playing is somewhere between Sonny Rollins and Michael Brecker. In the rhythm section Danielsson plays some of the grooviest, funkiest bass lines on the album and drives the tune forward. Behind it all however is Lund's modulating drum beat, he pulls and drags the time throughout masterfully. The interplay between Danielsson and Lund throughout is incredible also, it almost feels like a live gig with the energy flowing between the trio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another tune of note on the album is &quot;Up North&quot; (above), the main theme of which has a folk/Americana sort of vibe. This is an influence that comes up a few times throughout the album, this is even in reflected in the title of one of the pieces &quot;Folksong&quot;. On &quot;Up North&quot; there is more than a hint of Joe Henderson to Neset's playing - if you're familiar with this blog you'll know I see this as no bad thing.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/h_FPZZx0oos&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Sun Blowing&quot; is comprised entirely of original pieces apart from the Don Grolnick penned &quot;The Cost of Living&quot; (above) which closes the album. This is one of the lower tempo pieces on the album and it features some beautiful soloing from Danielsson. We are also treated to a masterclass from Lund who builds the energy just enough to punctuate the crescendo of each solo before bringing us back down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're looking for a jazz album you may have missed in the last decade, &quot;Sun Blowing&quot; is definitely worth your time. It's a little hard to believe this album is 5 years old (7 since it was recorded) - but it still sounds fresh. Given the energy and &quot;story-telling&quot; nature of the tunes it is an easy listen that does not require too much attention. Well worth hunting down a copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/049-Sun-Blowing/Sun-Blowing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/049-Sun-Blowing/Sun-Blowing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Colour of Intention and Finca La Esmeralda Gesha</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/colour-of-intention-la-esmeralda" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Colour of Intention and Finca La Esmeralda Gesha" /><published>2021-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Colour-of-Intention-La-Esmeralda</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/colour-of-intention-la-esmeralda">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-03-20-Colour-of-Intention-La-Esmeralda.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0WhO96JY7JE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we're heading back to the Brew Coffee Plus roasters in Streatham. For the second week in a row we're looking at a Gesha varietal coffee - but this time a washed processed example. We have talked about Gesha a few times in the past so we won't retread that ground - suffice to say the past few weeks of coffee have been relatively expensive so I might have to avoid the super-rare lots for a while!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would be remiss if I did not first mention the packaging for this coffee. Since this is a special Gesha coffee, Brew Coffee Plus decided to pull out all the stops with the packaging. The coffee arrived in a thick cardboard box with a magnetic clasp, it reminds me more of a hardback book than it does a coffee box. Yes, it is superfluous and doesn't actually &quot;add&quot; anything to the coffee itself - but I'm a firm believer that subconciously you judge a coffee long before it even reaches the cup and so this certainly does no harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself is from Finca La Esmeralda in Acatenango, Chimaltenango, Guatemala. Seeing the words &quot;La Esmeralda&quot; and &quot;Gesha&quot; on the same page will likely make one think of &quot;Hacienda La Esmeralda&quot; in Panama - but this coffee is unrelated (aside from the obvious sharing of the Gesha varietal). There wasn't too much information provided with the coffee itself but it does state that the owner of the farm is one Mr Hermes and it provides an interesting tidbit that he is working with hybrid varietals. Potentially something to look out for in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive into the coffee itself: in the usual way starting with the dry aroma. The first thing I notice is the nuance in the coffee. You can tell this will be a complex cup from the moment of opening the bag. There are layers upon layers of florals and citrus notes. It's quite hard to pinpoint individual notes here as there is a lot going on, but it is very inviting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter this coffee really shines. It is an incredibly clean cup of coffee, one of the cleanest I've had in a while. The main two &quot;themes&quot; of flavour notes are citrus and florals. I would describe the citrus notes as being clemantine in terms of sweetness but with a grapefruit type acidity in their too. You could also argue various other citrus-y type notes too but those are the two that come to mind for me. Once the initial citrus hit subsides you're hit with a wave of florals - jasmines are certainly there and there's a certain honeysuckle type sticky sweetness on show too. The taste notes say &quot;bergamot&quot; which is also a good description. The cup is very complex so picking out a few taste notes is difficult. This cup is also super sensitive to temperature and it takes you on a journey when drinking it. Using any sort of temperature control mug would be a crime against coffee here. I would instead recommend getting a very thin walled drinking vessel so that it cools down quicker as it won't last long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had enough of this coffee that I could experiment with espresso too. It is a roast that is on the lighter end and has delicate floral taste notes which can sometimes lead to a difficult dialing in process. I found the coffee very forgiving however, most things seemed to work well. Ultimately though a longer shot of around 1:2.75 in about 25s worked best for me and the machine wanted to be as hot as it could go. Going too short with this one led to something too concentrated and it was hard to identify the flavours for me. The bit of extra liquid helped seperate the flavour notes - again a similar palette of flavours to the filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another super enjoyable Gesha coffee and another good showing from Brew Coffee Plus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we're looking at a 2020 release from Lewis Wright called &quot;The Colour of Intention&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/048-Colour-of-Intention/Colour-of-Intention.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lewis Wright is perhaps best known as being the vibraphone player in the UK jazz group &quot;Empirical&quot; - one of the more interesting UK jazz groups of the past few decades, playing music inspired by some of the free and avant garde artists as well as the more straight ahead. On &quot;The Colour of Intention&quot; however we get to see Wright in a more stripped down setting - he is joined by two fantastic musicians in the form of Matt Brewer on the bass (one of my favourite bassists) and Marcus Gilmore on the drums. With only a 2 piece rhythm section to support him we get to hear what Wright has to offer unencumbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this outing there is less in the way of &quot;free&quot; playing than you'd expect if you came here via &quot;Empirical&quot; - the majority on the playing is fairly &quot;inside&quot;. The one notable exception being the opening track &quot;Mettle&quot; (embedded at the start of the blog) which evokes Bobby Hutcherson on Eric Dolphy's &quot;Out to Lunch&quot; recording with it's circular repeating melody.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IpUY3zsGGXg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

What really stands out throughout the album is the sheer virtuosity of Wright. He has some really enviable chops, but does not let that get in the way of the music. You never get the impression that he is &quot;showing off&quot; or trying to impress anybody. This is particularly evident by the rather notable final track on the album: &quot;Brilliant Corners&quot;. For those unfamiliar: this is a piece by Thelonious Monk. It is known for being so complicated that the musicians on the recording (including Sonny Rollins) were unable to play it end to end without making mistakes, and to my knowledge Monk never performed this piece live in its entirety. By placing this track on an album you are certainly making a statement about your jazz chops. The arrangement is very cool too, it captures the vibe and the frequent tempo changes/rhythmic motifs but Wright manages to throw his own spin on the tune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with playing a relatively obscure instrument such as the vibraphone is you instantly get compared to those that came before. These days most will get compared to the late great Gary Burton given his reinvention of the instrument. While Wright is clearly influence by Burton  (perhaps most notably on the track &quot;Resolve&quot; (above) which has a tinge of &quot;Crystal Silence&quot; to it.) Wright has his own sound and voice that is his own.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZYb6L9KuTM8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Another track that really stands out for me is the beautiful &quot;Raise (For Z)&quot; (above) - it is not about high octane virtuosity at all and is the most stripped back on the album. I'm particularly fond of Brewer's arco playing which is simply stunning, Wright makes sure to hold back during these parts to allow Brewer the chance to shine. Overall the piece has a dream-like almost meditative feeling to it and offers a stark contrast to the more uptempo numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall &quot;The Colour of Intention&quot; is a really great modern jazz release. If you like small band interaction it is a shining example of what can be achieved. There is a near telepathic interplay between the trio and each one is trying to help the others thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/048-Colour-of-Intention/Colour-of-Intention.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/048-Colour-of-Intention/Colour-of-Intention.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The All Seeing Eye and Finca Hartmann Gesha</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/all-seeing-eye-hartmann" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The All Seeing Eye and Finca Hartmann Gesha" /><published>2021-03-13T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-03-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/All-Seeing-Eye-Hartmann</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/all-seeing-eye-hartmann">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-03-13-All-Seeing-Eye-Hartmann.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xY2rNo9dUZs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

After a brief month hiatus the Plot Roasters ICON series subscription is back! Owing to Brexit related supply chain issues this coffee was due to be released in February but unfortunately got delayed until March. Let's see if good things do indeed come to those who wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a reminder this is the 3rd installment of the ICON series by Plot Roasters. This series is a relatively expensive series of rare and exciting coffees, it's for those who love coffee and don't mind paying to get access to the rare lots. In this installment we have a Gesha varietal from Panama. In the past we've talked about the rise of the Gesha varietal in the mid 2000s - and those with a good memory will recall that a particular lot from a Panamanian farm was responsible for causing the &quot;boom&quot;. It is therefore always interesting to get hold of some Gesha from Panama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this instance the Gesha was grown by the Hartmann family - one of the leading names in coffee in Panama, and their coffees always command high prices and achieve enviable cupping scores. The Hartmann family has owned farmland in Panama since the early 1900s, it now consists of many different coffee growing plots. The coffee we're talking about today is from the &quot;Roscosa Montana&quot; plot which translates to &quot;Rocky Mountain&quot; which borders the Parque Nacional de La Amistad rain forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee itself has been naturally processed - dried on raised African beds for a full 25 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with previous ICON installments this arrives in 150g bags only. As a result I don't use it for espresso since after a couple of shots to dial in I'd be left with very little to enjoy at its best! So it's a filter only blog-post this week. I have been drinking a great espresso alongside this one but I'll feature it next time in a dedicated post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving nose first into the dry aroma: the first thing to note is it smells incredible. The main hit is from tropical fruits, notably papaya and mango. But along with that there are caramel notes and a good floral bouquet. You can tell this is a very complex coffee before even taking a sip. Although it's a natural process there is not a hint of funkiness however, it seems very clean for a natural coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving into the filter: this coffee is truly exquisite. The supply chain delays seem irrelevant on first sip - it is well worth the wait. The first wave of flavour that hits is the tropical fruit notes from the nose. Papaya and Mango are most prevalent but there is also a sharpness to it too, perhaps a passionfruit. But in the supporting cast I also noted down wild strawberries and I could even be argued into agreeing the sharpness has a raspberry quality. What is so interesting about this coffee however is that the floral notes stand up to these big tropical fruit notes - I get strong violet and lavendar vibes from this one. It is very very rare to find a coffee where the florals don't get overwhelmed by the bigger bolder flavours. This makes for a super interesting and complex cup. As the cup cools down the balance between the fruit and the floral changes, the cooler you go the more florals you pick up. This is a coffee that demands you to savour and watch the flavour profiles develop, drinking this in a temperature controlled ember mug would be an absolute travesty!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet again Plot have smashed it out of the park. Looking forward to see what is to come with future ICON releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side we're going to look at another icon: Wayne Shorter with his 1966 release &quot;The All Seeing Eye&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/047-All-Seeing-Eye/All-Seeing-Eye.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point Wayne Shorter is certainly one of the elder-statesmen of jazz. Nearing in on his 90th birthday he has a career spanning around 70 years. During that time we has released solo works, been a member of both Art Blakey's Jazz Messengers (with whom he became the primary composer for the band) and Miles Davis' band - along with being a founding member of one of the greatest fusion groups of all time in Weather Report. &quot;Star studded career&quot; isn't nearly enough to describe what Shorter has achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very start of his career Shorter was seen as &quot;just another Coltrane tribute act&quot; - a label that (rather unfairly) was attributed to many tenor players of that era. As his career developed it was clear Wayne was anything but. Instead of relying on flashy, complicated, virtuosic playing (although he certainly had chops) - Shorter is now best known for his compositional voice. You can argue that he is one the greatest composers in all of jazz, if not all of music. His compostional style is focussed heavily on harmony, and using this to create a &quot;mood&quot;. A few albums before &quot;The All Seeing Eye&quot; he released perhaps his most famous album &quot;Speak No Evil&quot; where he explores the modal jazz style. Although his later works can't really be considered &quot;modal&quot; in the same way you can tell the modal style of creating a mood for a piece stuck with Shorter.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ylc6_wPm6SA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;The All Seeing Eye&quot; marks Wayne's 9th solo outing, and to date his most ambitious. From the get-go it is clear this is not your run of the mill bop record but something new entirely. It makes some nods from the avant-garde and free movements but the compositions are much more structured than is often the case in those styles. It is a highly ambitious record that still sounds daring today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening title track (embedded at the start of this post) sets the tone for the rest of the record. In interviews Wayne has stated the entire album is an attempt to depict the meaning of life, creation and the nature of god. The solos on the title track thus represent &quot;the machinery involved in the process of creation&quot; - with other tracks on the album showing similar levels of symbolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most &quot;traditional&quot; bop-sounding track on the album is &quot;Chaos&quot; (above) - living up to its name it's a chaotic fire-breathing sort of piece which allows the stellar cast to flex their chops. The supporting cast on the album features: Freddie Hubbard on trumpet/flugelhorn, Grachan Moncur III on trombone, James Spaulding on alto, Herbie Hancock on piano, Ron Carter on bass and Joe Chambers on drums (with a cameo from Wayne's brother Alan on one piece). This is an enviable line-up of talent and the quality shows throughout, although the music is highly daring and experimental it never feels out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;The All Seeing Eye&quot; represents one of my favourite Wayne Shorter albums and it is well worth your time. It is likely music you'll have to put the effort in to appreciate however, and it commands your attention. But it is an album that will reward your effort so it's worth investigating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/047-All-Seeing-Eye/All-Seeing-Eye.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/047-All-Seeing-Eye/All-Seeing-Eye.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Body Talk and Villa Betvlia</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/body-talk-villa-betvlia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Body Talk and Villa Betvlia" /><published>2021-03-06T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-03-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Body-Talk-Villa-Betvlia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/body-talk-villa-betvlia">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-03-06-Body-Talk-Villa-Betvlia.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z76Sl2rwlUw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are welcoming a new coffee roaster to the blog: Brew Coffee Plus. Located in Streatham, South London - these guys have been on my radar for a while but I haven't got round to trying them. They tick a few boxes for things I typically look for in a roaster: a concise offering, focusing on quality over quantity. Plus their packaging is attractive but simple. You can read more about them on their website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://brewcoffeeplus.com/&quot;&gt;https://brewcoffeeplus.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I opted for one of their Colombian offerings - Villa Betvlia - a Caturra microlot that has been naturally processed. The farm is located in Huila, a &quot;hotspot&quot; for coffee within the country. The bag/website does not offer much in the way of back story behind this coffee, fitting with Brew Plus Coffee's minimalist aesthetic, so I don't really know much more about this coffee. So I guess we should just dive right in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the nose the first thing that hits you is big juicy tropical fruits. It is not a really intense &quot;fruit bomb&quot; aroma but more like a very nice tropical fruit salad. Although the tropical fruits hint towards natural processing methods you do not get the boozy/funky natural notes you often get. I also notice a caramel note in the supporting cast. Very appetising. In terms of roast level we are in a light range, but it is not super light/nordic by any means - not quite medium-light but getting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving swiftly onto the filter: again the over-arching flavour notes are tropical fruits. I get mango and pineapple most of all - the sweeter end of the tropical fruit range. There is also the passion fruit type acidity to matters but primarily I would say this is on the sweeter end rather than the acidic end. If you imagine a tropical fruit salad covered in a sugar-syrup you wouldn't be far off. The body and mouthfeel are in the medium sort of range, it is not completely absent but neither is it a coffee you need to chew. The aftertaste is fairly intense and lingering. Temperature wise I find this coffee is fairly linear - it has the same character hotter or cooler so it's one you can drink at your leisure. Overall it is not hugely complex but is certainly very drinkable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso this might be one of the easiest coffees to dial in I've experienced. It can take pretty much whatever I threw at it in terms of recipe. In the end I found that I liked a 1:2.1 ratio with a 7s pre-infuse followed with a 32-34s pull - on the temperature scale I'm medium-high. This is not normally how I like to pull shots as it can introduce some bitterness or astringency to the finish but this is a coffee that can take it. You're rewarded with a thicker more luxurious shot and more intensity compared to my more usual longer/quicker style of pull. Again the tropical fruit salad and sugary sweetness comes through in the espresso, the acidity is slightly more noticable in the espresso but it is still a sweet coffee first and foremost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a very enjoyable coffee, hopefully a sign of things to come from this roaster and one I'm sure I'll be heading back to based on this showing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our jazz record this week we are heading back to 1973 and guitarist George Benson with his release: &quot;Body Talk&quot; on CTI records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/046-Body-Talk/Body-Talk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to the world of jazz you might be surprised to see George Benson recommended on a jazz-blog. For many he will be synonymous with pop records such as &quot;Give Me The Night&quot; or his &quot;crooner&quot; image from his later works. It is easy to forget he has some serious jazz under his belt also. When he burst onto the scene in the 1960s he was considered a protege to Wes Montgomery in some respects. George's &quot;twin careers&quot; of jazz star and pop star came to a head a few years ago at a gig in London whereby he was unable to sing so played a set of instrumental jazz pieces and the (non-jazz) crowd booed him for not playing his &quot;hits&quot; - a rather embarrassing incident for the London live music scene and those involved should be ashamed.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HV1Tfj8qqtI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;Body Talk&quot; is one of my favourite Benson albums. It marks a kind of &quot;cross-over&quot; period from the more straight ahead jazz he was playing before and the RnB and pop influenced music that came after. I wish he spent a bit more time exploring this soul-jazz kind of space as he was very good at it. On this album Benson entrusted James Brown alumni - saxophonist Pee Wee Ellis to write and arrange a few of the tunes. But it is clear that the James Brown DNA heavily influenced Benson at the time since all the tracks feature the strong grooves we associate with Brown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album also features some heavyweight jazz icons in the supporting cast: Jack DeJohnette taking control of the drumming duties - one of the most prolific jazz drummers of all time. Jack manages to introduce a slight swing to proceedings while keeping the muscular grooves driving forward, something that is not easy to do by any means. Alongside is Ron Carter on the acoustic bass (the album also features Gary King on electric bass). We've spoken about Ron in the blog before, as a bass player he is completely reliable and can throw his hand at anything - another jazz legend. On the electric piano we also have Harold Mabern. He is one of the underappreciated greats, a lot of his work has been as a sideman rather than a leader. I was fortunate enough to be able to meet him before he passed away - a great musician and a great person. I'll save my Harold story for another day when we can focus on him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with &quot;Dance&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) and straight away gets into a deep groove. You can tell that Benson had an eye on making music you can move to here, it's almost impossible to not tap your foot along to the beat. However, it features an absolutely virtuousic guitar performance throughout. I consider Benson as one of the most naturally gifted guitar players of all time. There appears to be absolutely no filter between brain and guitar, it comes across as completely effortless. This is backed up by watching some of his incomprehensible guitar tuition videos - it is so natural he is completely unable to effectively explain what he does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another track that is particularly interesting on the album is the third number: &quot;Plum&quot; (above). This really exemplifies the two worlds of jazz and RnB that Benson is trying to straddle. It starts off in a swinging jazz tune but eventually the horns and percussion come in, the groove hits and we're comfortably in foot-tapping mode again. This is not a jarring experience of slamming two styles together - the transition is seamless. Again Benson throws out some mindblowing guitar lines as all this is unfolding.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/li5IDW_H_6s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Perhaps the hardest hitting groove is the title track &quot;Body Talk&quot; (above). Here we have a piece that is part James Brown groove and part Latin jazz. It's 8 minutes of pure energy and intensity. While there is incredible musicianship on display, the main theme is itself catchy and something you'll likely be humming to yourself after hearing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Body Talk&quot; is a bit of an underappreciated jazz album, from his &quot;jazz&quot; period other Benson albums such as &quot;Beyond Blue Horizon&quot; often get more publicity - but for me &quot;Body Talk&quot; is where Benson hits his stride. If you do not know anything of George Benson's jazz career I'd strongly suggest giving it a listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/046-Body-Talk/Body-Talk.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/046-Body-Talk/Body-Talk.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sonny Side Up and Arnoldo Perez Hydro Natural</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/sonny-side-up-arnoldo-perez-hydro" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sonny Side Up and Arnoldo Perez Hydro Natural" /><published>2021-02-27T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Sonny-Side-Up-Arnoldo-Perez-Hydro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/sonny-side-up-arnoldo-perez-hydro">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-02-27-Sonny-Side-Up-Arnoldo-Perez-Hydro.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Iz0CcsmAelw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we're heading back to Plot Coffee Roasting again. A few blog posts ago we featured the rather special Champagne yeast processed coffee from Finca La Senda in Guatemala - this time we feature another experimental processed coffee from the very same farm. As before the coffee is of the Pache varietal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process is described as a &quot;hydro-natrual&quot; - the cherries are picked and dried in the sun for 4 days before being soaked in water overnight. This &quot;rehydrates&quot; the cherries which are then dried in the shade for another 28-30 days. The folks at Finca La Senda are certainly experimental and they should be commended for it. I think processing variation is likely to be the key to unlocking new flavour potential in coffee. Of course genetic diversity of coffee plants can lead to variation but this is a slow process driven by evolution (aside from the rare &quot;freak discovery&quot; of an unknown varietal) - processing is something that has a shorter feedback loop and so is a more commercially viable for the farmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit however I'm not a fan of all the experimental processings I've had. In fact I have a rather low hit rate of enjoyment from them, I often find them unbalanced or just plain odd. Based on the Champagne yeast processed coffee I have high hopes for this one however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets just dive straight into the coffee itself. Like the Champagne yeast offering Plot have opted for a pretty light roast, maybe a hair darker than the Champagne yeast but I never compared them side by side. On the dry aroma it is clear this is a very different beast. The first thing that I notice is the red berry note - it also has a sort of bramble note too, it reminds me of a fruit picking farm. In the background there is just a hint of tropical fruit, but it is not your typical &quot;fruit bomb&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual we start with a filter brew: just as on the nose the primary thing I notice is the red berry flavours. The label lists blueberry and raspberry, which I don't disagree with. The tropical fruit flavours are also more prominent in the cup, mango being the predominant note. On the acidity scale this one comes in quite high but it is balanced with a lot of sweetness. It also has quite a big mouthfeel and body. Interestingly I find this coffee is better at higher cup temperatures, usually I find the flavours difficult to distinguish at the higher temperatures but this coffee keeps its clarity. At lower cup temperatures the acidity can take over a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto espresso: as you'd expect for a light roast the machine temp is set to maximum. For a ratio I found 1:2.5 works best but I prefered to pull a bit slower than usual at around 30-32s. This allowed more of the body to come through and added some intensity to the shot. I didn't find this added any bitterness at all and everything balanced nicely. The flavour profile was much the same as the filter brew: mangos and raspberries. Despite being a fairly acidic light roast it is surprisingly easy to drink as an espresso and one I have enjoyed. The only downside to the espresso compared to the filter is less of the complexity comes through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall another great offering. For me the Champagne yeast version was more up my street, but I could easily see others having the opposite preference. Drinking two coffees from the same farm with different processings is always interesting as you can see what a huge difference there is in the cup. These coffees are night and day different, in a blind tasting I don't think I'd be able to identify they were from the same farm. Plot offer a third processing from Finca La Senda (carbonic maceration) but unfortunately at the time I couldn't justify getting all three since I already had too much coffee to be getting on with. If it's still available next time I do a Plot order I'll pick up a bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week we're heading back to an all time classic from 1957. The seminal &quot;Sonny Side Up&quot; from Dizzy Gillespie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/045-Sonny-Side-Up/Sonny-Side-Up.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dizzy has featured on the blog in the past as a co-headliner but this is his first showing in his own right. Dizzy of course needs no introduction - one of the forefathers of be-bop, he is one of the few jazz artists who became known outside of the jazz community. Potentially down to his look: often sporting a beret, horn-rimmed glasses and of course the puffed out cheeks when playing. Or possibly down to his jovial and light hearted personality. But, there is no doubting his musical pedigree.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Rezdck_Roog&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

By 1957 be-bop had pretty much run its course, it had become fairly &quot;mainstream&quot; in jazz by then so just playing be-bop was not enough to gain recognition. Jazz artists were beginning to look at the new &quot;post-bop&quot; world and where they could make their mark. For somebody like Dizzy who was one of the originators this could present a problem, it is often easy for an artist to get stuck in their stylistic box and unable to adapt with the times. To combat this Dizzy apointed two tenor saxophonists to help him out: Sonny Stitt and Sonny Rollins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides just providing am easy pun for the album's title the tenor pair provided the necessary artistic direction for the album. Both Sonny's were clearly disciples of Gillespie's buddy Charlie Parker - but instead of simply copying Bird licks they each developed upon the Parker framework in different ways. Stitt was most directly compared to Parker, originally playing alto he was often labelled a &quot;Parker Clone&quot;. To combat this he made the switch to the tenor and developed a more forceful approach, however he still adopted the belly-fire of Parker and made use of the wild lines we associate with be-bop. In contrast Rollins adapted the Parker ethos in a different way, he made use of the be-bop framework but explored thematic and motif led ideas. You could argue it is more of an intellectual approach, often adopting more complex harmonic devices and crafting lines that fall further from typical be-bop. Hearing the two tenor-men back-to-back is part of the joy of this album. You could never mistake one for the other since their styles are so different (although I believe one version of the liner notes did just that, stating that a Rollins solo appears first or vice versa) Yet both players serve the music being played and neither sounds out of place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With three titans in Gillespie, Rollins and Stitt - it would be easy to overlook the rest of the band: Ray Bryant on piano, Tommy Bryant on bass and Charlie Persip on drums. While these guys may not be &quot;headline acts&quot; as the others they do add to the quality of the album - so many albums featuring &quot;heavyweights&quot; fall down with poor supporting casts. This is particularly true for an album such as &quot;Sonny Side Up&quot; where you have two tenor players battling each other for supremacy, the rhythm section needs to be tight and stay out of their way and that is certainly achieved here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Sonny Side Up&quot; is afterall however a Dizzy Gillespie album so it is worth exploring a little bit of his role. The album is itself essentially a &quot;live&quot; studio album, all tracks were recorded in one take in a &quot;cutting session&quot; style. Reportedly before the date Dizzy did his best to rile up the rivalry between the Sonny's - important work to get the best out of the band. This all came to a head in the stand out tenor-duel on the track &quot;Eternal Triangle&quot;. For me this is Dizzy Gillespie's true talent: getting the best out of people. I do not believe Charlie Parker would have been nearly as revered as he is today without Gillespie. Dizzy worked out a lot of the harmonic complexities of be-bop which allowed Parker (and to a lesser extent Monk) to flourish.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8afBciyvAeA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Dizzy is of course no slouch on the trumpet either, this is particularly clear on his killer solo on &quot;After Hours&quot;. He manages to pull of an effortlessly cool and laidback blues led solo. Not something you instantly think of when you think of a Dizzy solo. Then of course you cannot ignore the trademark Gillespie humour and wit - on this album coming through in the opening track &quot;On the Sunny Side of the Street&quot;. Here Gillespie completely reworks the standard both melodically and rhythmically to create a fresh take on a well-trodden classic. We also get to hear Dizzy stretch his vocal chords which is always intresting too. I can see many parallels between his vocal phrasing on this tune and the phrasing used in rap music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downside to this album is its brevity - clocking in at just over 30 minutes. It would have been great to have another cut or two on the album but it doesen't take away from the enjoyment. For the jazz historians and those interested in the progression of be-bop it is a very interesting recording, but it is also a great listen for those that just want to hear a great old-fashioned cutting session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/045-Sonny-Side-Up/Sonny-Side-Up.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/045-Sonny-Side-Up/Sonny-Side-Up.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Landmarks and Clever Coffee</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/landmarks-clever-coffee" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Landmarks and Clever Coffee" /><published>2021-02-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Landmarks-Clever-Coffee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/landmarks-clever-coffee">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-02-20-Landmarks-Clever-Coffee.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rMcyjco69z4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This blog post marks a return to my KaffeBox subscription. This time it features a pair of coffees from Danish coffee roaster Clever Coffee. Not to be confused with the &quot;clever dripper&quot; brewer manufactured by a totally different company. I have to admit I'd never heard of Clever Coffee prior to receiving these coffees, part of the joy of a subscription service like KaffeBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packaging wise they opt for quite a minimalist aesthetic with plain white packages and green labels. For each coffee there is a different shade of green so I assume they might have other colours for other coffees. Overall I don't mind the presentation but it is not as eye-catching as some other packaging I've seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the previous KaffeBox offerings I received 2 bags of 125g each, I decide to dedicate one to filter and one to espresso so I have a chance to dial in and get the best out of them. This time I decided which coffee to use for each preparation completely at random - it was whichever I picked up first when brewing the first filter coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the filter side this week we have La Catarata - a red catuai varietal from Costa Rica. The processing method is described as &quot;black honey&quot; - I've covered honey processing in previous posts so won't retread old ground there. But the &quot;black&quot; designation is used to refer to the amount of fruit/mucilage left on the seed as part of the honey process. Very loosely: a white honey means that a lot of the cherry is removed (&quot;closer to a washed&quot;) and black honey means more cherry is left attached (&quot;closer to a natural&quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to notice about this coffee is that it's certainly on the lighter end roast wise. On the dry aroma I get hints of caramel and honey along with a fig fruity note. It has a heft to the nose but it is not something you'll smell across a room when somebody opens the bag. In the cup the first thing to note is how balanced the cup is; acidity and sweetness are in perfect harmony. In terms of flavours I get apples and caramels most of all. You get the crisp sharpness of a green apple followed by the sweetness of the caramel. In terms of body I would describe this as a medium, given the roast level it has more body that you would expect. The aftertaste is very clean and fairly short lived. It is not the most complex coffee you'll ever drink and you don't really get anything in the way of progression as the cup cools. It is a very reliable no-nonsense sort of cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have Fazenda Samambaia - a Mundo Novo varietal from Brazil. What is interesting here is that it is an anaerobically processed coffee, I don't remember seeing many Brazilian coffees with this processing method. However, Brazil is not an origin I spend much time with typically. On opening the bag again I notice the light roast level and on the nose I get caramel notes but overall it is a pretty subtle affair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of dialing this coffee in I have to admit it was a bit of a challenge (this is a light filter roast so that is not a complaint). This coffee is prone to getting a bit acidic so to combat that I had to set the machine to maximum temperature. Pulling the shot long helped with this also but the coffee has a great body that is sacrificed so I preferred to keep it more in the 1:2.5 range. When it's right it is fantastic and super interesting. I would describe the sensation as being like those traditional pineapple cube sweets - that sort of tropical fruit note combined with huge sweetness. I find that the mouthfeel starts off kind of thin but the body &quot;blooms&quot; and you're left satisfied. If you don't have it dialed in or your puck prep is not quite right you do end up with a &quot;battery acid&quot; shot however. This is one for somebody experienced at making espresso and doesn't mind a bit of work, but you will be rewarded for it in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this weeks jazz we're jumping back to 2014 with Brian Blade and The Fellowship Band and their Landmarks recording.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/044-Landmarks/Landmarks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Landmarks is the fourth release from The Fellowship Band having released their debut album in 1998. The heart of the band features Brian Blade on drums, Jon Cowherd on piano, Myron Walden on alto sax and bass clarinet, Melvin Butler on soprano and tenor sax and Chris Thomas on bass. They also feature the occassional &quot;guest&quot; spots notably in the guitarist spot - on this album we have Marvin Sewell and Jeff Parker who replace Kurt Rosenwinkel

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aEcLf-uoqAA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Drummer Brian Blade is of course the &quot;headline act&quot; for this band and, arguably, the most famous musician on the recording. He is perhaps best known as a sideman and particularly through being &quot;Wayne Shorter's drummer&quot; for many years. He has also been a long time member of the Chick Corea trio and has appeared alongside more modern greats such as Joshua Redman and Kenny Garrett, as well as appearing on Joni Mitchell records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian's drumming style is both interesting and distinctive. A big part of his vibe is his use of dynamics when playing, it is very musical and makes everybody he plays with sound better. I have to say that live this comes at a cost however. I have seen him live a few times where he has ruined the gig by not playing the room correctly. The drastic change in dynamics can become jarring and quite distracting in my experience. But on record and on dates where the room can support his style he is incredible however and few can compare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all the Fellowship records Landmarks has long been my favourite of the lot. I feel that at this point the band is so familiar with each other that they are completely free to express themselves. The record prior to this one are great and I still enjoy listening to them, but as a complete statement Landmarks is where they nail it. While taking a nod to jazz artists that come before them the Fellowship band really thrives at bringing in elements from Gospel and American Folk like lyricism. It is more about an overall atmopshere and feeling than it is technicality, each member adds texture upon texture to create a landscape. This is an album where it's best to just let it wash over you, and it may take a few listens to truly appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selecting tracks on an album like this is difficult as I feel it's best to listen from start to finish. At the start of this post I embedded the title track &quot;Landmarks&quot; which features a bass led folk-like motif as its main theme. There is a spiritual quality to the piece with it almost feeling like a hymn. The interplay between Blade and Walden is also a particular highlight. &quot;He Died Fighting&quot;  (embedded above) in contrast features a rootsy bluesy theme driven by Cowherd's piano followed by some gutsy blues influenced soloing. While the soloists clearly exhibit virtuosic ability that is not what is important here, the focus is always on the tune - the band is almost completely devoid of ego which is part of the magic.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UuKjBpYzsQk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The album closes with the shorter piece &quot;Embers&quot; (above) based around a country-like theme but featuring gospel-like sensibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall Landmarks represents a truly original and fresh take on modern jazz. It takes influence from the past but is not beholden to it while not trying to be modern for the sake of it. The Fellowship Band have created a sonic universe that is all their own hopefully we will see many more releases from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/044-Landmarks/Landmarks.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/044-Landmarks/Landmarks.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Chick Corea and Arnoldo Perez Yeast Natural</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/chick-corea-arnoldo-perez-champagne" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chick Corea and Arnoldo Perez Yeast Natural" /><published>2021-02-13T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Chick-Corea-Arnoldo-Perez-Champagne</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/chick-corea-arnoldo-perez-champagne">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-02-13-Chick-Corea-Arnoldo-Perez-Champagne.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sEhQTjgoTdU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are heading back to the fine folks at Plot Coffee Roasting ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://plotroasting.com/&quot;&gt;https://plotroasting.com/&lt;/a&gt; ) - now a near permanent fixture on the blog. Plot are consistently crushing it lately with great coffee after great coffee, definitely check them out if you have not already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we have a super interesting one, and possibly a first for me. The coffee is from a farm &quot;Finca la Senda&quot; located within the Acatenango region of Guatemala. In the past few years I've noticed the quality of Guatemalan coffee has increased exponentially, I've had some really special coffees from there. What makes this coffee particularly interesting is the &quot;yeast maceration&quot; processing method. Here Pache varietals are picked and the whole cherries are placed under carbonic maceration for 30 hours. Following this a specific strain of Champagne yeast is added to the mix and maceration continues for a further 36 hours, before being sun-dried for 30 days. This is a fairly long processing time which gives plenty of opportunity for complex flavours to develop. The introduction of a Champagne yeast is new to me - at least I can't remember trying a yeasted coffee before (but I try many so I may have simply forgtten).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's just get down to business. On the dry aroma I don't get a huge bouquet, it is fairly quiet and refined in its presentation. There are fruity notes most notably orange and some delicate floral type notes but they're subtle. As I've stated many times in the past a lack of &quot;punch&quot; here does not always translate into the cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using my tried and tested filter recipe the first word that comes to mind for me is: Exceptional. This is an incredibly refined cup, I feel as though I should be sat in a tuxedo to do the coffee justice. The main flavour notes are oranges and citrus fruits. The mouthfeel is a little sticky and the slight floral hint gives the impression of elderflower or honeysuckle. What is really mindblowing however is the finish which is exactly like Champagne. You don't notice it initially but after the initial hit of flavour and particularly in the aftertaste you get that unmistakable Champagne drying quality and a really strong white grape punch. It is also super sensitive to temperature and it really evolves as the cup cools. I find it best on the cooler side of things as it allows the more delicate notes to pop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving onto the espresso: this coffee is definitely on the lighter side roast-wise so I was expecting a bit of a battle to get the best out of it (especially with the delicate flavour profile) - but it was a joy to dial in. I found it next to impossible to get a bad shot out of it - the only caveat being the machine needs to be blinding hot, too cold and some sourness creeps in. In the end I decided on a 1:2.25 ratio, this seemed to better preseve a silky mouthfeel that is otherwise lost. Going longer didn't increase the sweetness for me. The flavour profile is similar to the filter and that Champagne finish becomes even more intense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As both filter and espresso this coffee was fantastic and one I'm going to sorely miss. It may only be February but I feel this is a contender for &quot;coffee of the year&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I had intended to talk about a specific album, but on Thursday the jazz-world was shocked at news of the passing of Armando &quot;Chick&quot; Corea. So instead I thought I'd share my Chick stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/043-Chick-Corea/Chick-Corea.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word &quot;legend&quot; gets thrown around quite a lot these days, but Chick is one of the few truly deserving of that title. His career started in the mid 1960s working with the likes of Stan Getz, Blue Mitchell and Herbie Mann. His &quot;big break&quot; however came when he joined the Miles Davis band and was instrumental in driving the &quot;fusion&quot; sound that Davis was chasing at the time. After the stint with Davis he started another fusion group: &quot;Return to Forever&quot; - one of the most successful fusion groups of all time. In addition to rock he brought inspiration from Latin-American music (something he also visited in solo album &quot;My Spanish Heart&quot;). He also formed the &quot;Chick Corea Elektric Band&quot; - a fusion supergroup with legions of fans and the offshoot &quot;Akoustic Band&quot; where they dropped the electric instruments in favour of acoustic instruments. Subsequent to this Chick spent a lot of his career doing more traditional projects until the formation of another fusion group &quot;Five Peace Band&quot; with John McLaughlin, Kenny Garrett, Christian McBride and Vinnie Colaiuta. Chick Corea is one of the few artists who can span any decade and any style - you can essentially pick up any one of his records and have a good time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was never fortunate enough to meet Chick personally, but over the past 10 years or so I have seen him live countless times in many different contexts. One of the things you notice walking out of a Chick Corea gig is his warmth towards everybody. I remember one instance where he was playing a solo gig and the venue staff were keeping the doors closed while he was playing, only letting people get to their seats between tunes. Chick addressed this and said: &quot;what's going on? This is not a classical recital, let people come in and out as they want&quot; - there are not many artists around who would express such a sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then of course there is his use of the audience as a &quot;piano&quot; - whereby he'd get different sections of the audience each to sing a different note to create a chord to accompany his playing. This is something that others have tried but it usually feels uncomfortable and gimmicky, with Chick's enthusiasm and humour it totally works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another time I saw him in a trio context with Christian McBride on bass and Brian Blade on drums. To date one of the best gigs I have ever seen. It came across that they didn't even have a set list they just decided what they were going to play on the spot and the mood take them wherever they wanted to go. I'm sure there was a setlist or at least a shortlist to choose from, but the carefree energy added to an already amazing show. During this one I remember distinctly them playing &quot;Work&quot; by Thelonious Monk. People often talk about Chick in terms of raw technique and crazy knowledge of harmony - but he more than anybody understands what Monk is all about. He managed to capture all of the nuance from Monk - the feel, time and even captured the mannerisms often getting up from the piano and walking around during others solos. It was truly a joy to behold.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EpVef_no_cw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

I also remember attending the Elektric band reunion concert where they played the entire first album. All the guys recognised that the 80s synth sounds are a bit dated now so they had some fun with it. Chick even broke out the keytar a few times in true 80s style. Even though the synth sounds are not particularly popular today looking past that some of the music on that album still stands the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also the duet concert I saw between Chick and Herbie Hancock a couple of years ago. Even in his 70s Chick was still sprightly and energetic. He played some really daring music that night and one of the things I remember clearly is just seeing Herbie with a grin from ear to ear the entire time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In losing Chick we lost one of the few remaining artists from a golden era. A master, a genius, whatever superlative you wish to throw around Chick was all of those things. Right til the end he was still touring and playing some of the best jazz gigs you could ever see. He will be truly missed.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lagNpi1v5FY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

RIP Chick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/043-Chick-Corea/Chick-Corea.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/043-Chick-Corea/Chick-Corea.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>