<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-24T05:36:25-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JazzCoffeeStuff</title><subtitle>A blog about jazz, coffee, and stuff!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Weather Report and Fuglen</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/weather-report-fuglen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weather Report and Fuglen" /><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Weather-Report-Fuglen</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/weather-report-fuglen">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-07-24-Weather-Report-Fuglen.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9tw9uYQ5k50&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we have another instalment of my KaffeBox subscription - this time featuring coffee from: Fuglen Coffee Roasters, located in Oslo, Norway. This is the first time I've even heard of these guys and girls, part of the joy of a subscription such as this, and so one I was looking forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I want to note is the aesthetic of the coffee bags: they are very much my style. Each bag features a rather funky artwork, an example is below (taken from their webstore: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fuglencoffee.no/&quot;&gt;https://www.fuglencoffee.no/&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/065-Weather-Report/Fuglen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each artwork features a depiction of a bird - and after some google translating I now know that &quot;fuglen&quot; is &quot;the bird&quot; in Norwegian. Apart from the artwork the bags are pretty sparse with just the basic information you need: origin, produers, region, varietals, processing and roast date. I appreciate this approach, simple and to the point. Also plus points for using coffee bags that are easily recyclable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may recall as part of my subscription I receive 2 small bags (125g) of coffee - to allow me to dial in effectively I dedicate one to filter and one to espresso. This week I received a Kenyan and a Colombian coffee and I typically do not favour Kenyan coffee as espresso so that one was dedicated to filter duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start on the filter side: the Kenyan coffee is from the Kiambu County and produced by the Ndumberi Farmer coop. The stated cultivars are: SL-34, Ruiru-11, Batian and SL-28 (Peaberry). For those unaware: a peaberry is a mutation where each coffee cherry contains only 1 seed (&quot;bean&quot;) rather than 2 seperated by mucilage. Peaberries are very easy to identify visually as the beans will be &quot;rounded&quot; instead of having 1 flat side. It was/is believed that peaberry coffees taste better and so command a higher price, this is not something I've particularly noticed in the past so I tend not to search out peaberries specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto the coffee itself: the coffee is roasted a touch darker (visually) than one might expect from a &quot;nordic&quot; (but it is by no means &quot;dark&quot;). On the dry aroma you get the normal washed Kenyan profile: a very strong hit of blackcurrants. On aroma alone it is hard to get much more from it. Once it has been brewed again the predominant note is blackcurrant - as you would expect. Alongside are a supporting cast of rhubarb, orange, pink grapefruit and melon. Overall a very solid example of a washed Kenyan coffee. The acidity level is noticable but not overbearing, the sweetness is medium-low - just enough to take the edge off the acidity. If you like Kenyan coffees you'll like this one a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have a Colombian coffee from Tarqui, Huila. The farm in question is called Finca El Prado and the producer is Ferney Cruz Trujillo. The coffee has been washed and the cultivar is Caturra. In terms of dialing in the settings from the previous espresso I was running were nearly perfect so there was little for me to tweak and so I can't comment on how hard this one is to dial in. I found a ratio of 1:2.25 to work well in around 25s all in. This gave just enough mouthfeel but allowed the flavour notes to be adequately separated. The main notes for me were stone fruits along with a grapefruit acidity. It was not the most complex shot of espresso I ever had but it was very drinkable and highly enjoyable. I would describe it as a medium for acidity, sweetness and body - it's just the sort of coffee you can really enjoy. If I had to pick between the two coffees I'd say this one is my favourite of the pair, it just hit the spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I dug out a bit of an overlooked record from a band that is not at all overlooked: the 1982 self-titled &quot;Weather Report&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/065-Weather-Report/Weather-Report.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a move that confused record collectors and record shops alike, in 1982 Weather Report released their 10th studio album &quot;Weather Report&quot; - which shared a title with their 1971 debut album. I think this confusion led to this album being slightly overlooked in the Weather Report back catalogue, which is unfortunate as it is a great album. This is the second Weather Report album I ever owned - I remember purchasing the classic &quot;Heavy Weather&quot; on CD and loving it. Shortly after I found a vinyl copy of &quot;Weather Report&quot; (1982) in a second hand record store for very little money so I snapped it up without really knowing much about it.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gDCHFgeoiY4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

It is probably worth going into a little band history to put this album into context: the fusion super-group was formed/co-led by keyboard/pianist Joe Zawinul and saxophonist Wayne Shorter, who had previously worked together on Miles Davis' &quot;In a Silent Way&quot;. The band has had many other musicians pass through the ranks but by far the most successful/popular line-ups feature the great Jaco Pastorius on the bass and Peter Erskine on the drums. &quot;Weather Report&quot; (1982) is the last album to feature this classic line-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music itself has a kind of &quot;end of an era&quot; feel to it also - the collaborative efforts on previous albums make way for some of Joe Zawinul's more ambitious arrangements. The album feels a bit like a cross-over between Weather Report and The Zawinul Syndicate (Joe's next project). Jaco in particular seems to take a back seat on &quot;Weather Report&quot; - his only writing credit is in the concluding extended jam and he doesn't really take the limelight with any memorable basslines on this one. Many of his basslines are doubled by Zawinul's synths - something which angered Jaco and led him to a more &quot;acoustic&quot; direction in his following solo career. The album is therefore one for the Zawinul fans (of which I am certainly one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off in style with the grooving &quot;Volcano For Hire&quot; (embedded at the start of this blog post). This could have featured on just about any of the &quot;classic&quot; Weather Report recordings and not felt out of place. It highlights Erskine's unique drum grooves (supported by percussionist Robert Thomas Jr.), Zawinul's compositional voice and moments of magic from Jaco and Wayne. The tune has a nod to the &quot;world music&quot; style that Weather Report and Zawinul in particular were known for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most ambitious tune on the album is likely the 3 movement &quot;NYC&quot; suite (above). The piece is probably the most &quot;swinging&quot; on the album with Zawinul experimenting with the tonal and harmonic possibilities of his synths. There are many twists and turns throughout the piece and it keeps you on your toes and continually surprises. It is probably the most &quot;Syndicate&quot;-ish tune on the album and an interesting piece of history to see where Zawinul was heading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album concludes with the jam &quot;Dara Factor Two&quot; (below) - this is the only piece on the album that has writing credits from all band members (elsewhere on the album Shorter has one writing credit for &quot;When It Was Now&quot; with Zawinul picking up all other credits). The collaborative nature of this piece gives it a very different feeling to the rest of the album and it shows what great improvisers were in this band - it acts as a fitting send off for this incarnation of Weather Report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to it's lack of commercial success I wouldn't place this in the &quot;essential listening&quot; category (like say &quot;Heavy Weather&quot; or &quot;Black Market&quot;) but for Weather Report fans (or fans of fusion in general) it is worth checking out if it is a record you have overlooked.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/htwccmgWJRA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/065-Weather-Report/Weather-Report.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/065-Weather-Report/Weather-Report.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Africa Brass and Icon 7</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/africa-brass-icon-7" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Africa Brass and Icon 7" /><published>2021-07-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Africa-Brass-Icon-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/africa-brass-icon-7">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-07-17-Africa-Brass-Icon-7.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LoK8PeQFvcg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we have another coffee in the Icon series from the folks at Plot Coffee Roasting. This time we have an origin I rarely go for: Brazil. The stereotypes for Brazilian coffees are &quot;chocolatey&quot;, &quot;heavy&quot;, &quot;nutty&quot; and so on. These are not flavour notes I tend to favour. As you'd expect from an &quot;unobtainium&quot; coffee in the Icon series, this is not a typical coffee from Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee is from Daterra Coffee, located in Cerrado - the first &quot;A&quot; grade rainforest certified farm. Within Daterra coffee there is the &quot;Masterpiece Farm&quot; from which this particular lot was grown. Masterpiece is a dedicated research facility looking into the latest and greatest cultivars, processing methods and so on. Each lot is very small and they often achieve cup scores in excess of 90 (i.e. very good!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular coffee is a Aramosa cultivar - this is a &quot;pre-cultivar&quot; as its genetics are still being studied. Needless to say you don't see these very often and it is a first for me. The Aramosa is a cross between Arabica coffee and Racemosa coffee species. Nearly all the coffees on this blog are Arabica, Racemosa is harder to find - it brings with it naturally low caffeine and is drought and disease resistant. This is important for the future of coffee and so it is very interesting to see what happens with these latest &quot;cross&quot; cultivars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the cultivar this coffee is also an anaerobic processed lot. We have spoken about anaerobic processing in the past - the removal of oxygen in the fermentation process allows for different flavour compounds to develop. This coffee is therefore a full-house in the game of &quot;high end coffee bingo&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this fanciness means a thing unless the coffee tastes good however, so lets move onto the important stuff. As always with these Icon coffees the amounts are too low to reliably dial in espresso and taste as filter so this blog post is a filter coffee only post (normal espresso service to resume next week).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the dry aroma I get a very interesting profile, it is immediately recognisable as something different. I would describe it as sweet like, but old-fashioned sweets like parma violets, love hearts, etc. Quite a &quot;soft&quot; profile and almost a powder-y floralness to them. But there is also a bit of tropical funk there too but it is very restrained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the cup the first thing to notice is a complete lack of bitterness. The coffees we feature on this blog are typically not bitter to begin with, but this is a noticable step down. I can only presume it is the reduced caffeine levels. I would describe this as a soft and delicate coffee, it is one that only gives up its flavours when you really look for them. The cup itself is very complex, there are a lot of florals packed in there. Alongside is the powder-y sherbet-type sweetness we got off the nose. I also notice a feint aniseed note when the cup reaches just the right temperature too. In terms of fruity notes it has some tropical notes there along with your stone fruits. The sweetness level is high and the mouthfeel gives the impression of stickyness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very interesting cup, it is hard to describe because it is different to most other coffees I drink. It is one you really have to try for yourself to appreciate it. Yet again Plot manage to surprise with their Icon series, as always I look forward to see what the next month brings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is customary on Icon coffee posts I pick a jazz icon to pair with it. Amazingly it has taken 64 blog posts for this musician to appear: welcome to the blog John Coltrane. We take a look at his 1961 studio release &quot;Africa/Brass&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/064-Africa-Brass/Africa-Brass.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of &quot;classic&quot; Coltrane recordings &quot;Africa/Brass&quot; might seem an &quot;odd&quot; first choice for the blog. While it is perhaps less well known than some of the other more successful recordings &quot;Africa/Brass&quot; is one of my favourite Coltrane recordings. I'm going to say something controversial here: but I don't particularly enjoy many of Coltranes albums under his own name. The ones that are good are fantastic, but I feel there is a lot of filler too and I'm not a fan of &quot;A Love Supreme&quot; or any of the &quot;spiritual&quot; albums that followed. I can only assume my membership to the jazz-bloggers union is going to be quickly revoked after posting such heresy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Africa/Brass&quot; was released on Impulse records - now a legendary record label, but &quot;Africa/Brass&quot; marks only the 6th release on Impulse. This was quite a bold move by the label all things considered. While Coltrane was a big name after hits such as the impressive &quot;Giant Steps&quot; and &quot;Blue Train&quot; which earned him the reputation of being an all time great - &quot;Africa/Brass&quot; strayed quite far from the Coltrane formula through the addition of a big-band orchestra. As if the 21 piece big-band wasn't strange enough even the instrumentation is quite weird through the use of french horns and euphoniums. This is quite a big risk for a fledgling label when they could have just churned out a &quot;cutting date&quot; with the Coltrane band and sold a lot of units. I'm glad they took the risk however, as &quot;Africa/Brass&quot; is really a special album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album consists of just 3 tracks (modern reissues feature many more) and spans just 33 minutes in length (perhaps the one downside of the album). There are two Coltrane originals &quot;Africa&quot; and &quot;Blues Minor&quot; along with a reworking of &quot;Greensleeves&quot;. The orchestration comes courtesy of pianist and long-time collaborator McCoy Tyner and (perhaps a bit left-field) Eric Dolphy. The Dolphy connection perhaps adds to some of the &quot;weirdness&quot; in the orchestration, but it certainly adds to the experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With such long track lengths there is of course ample opportunity for extended soloing as you'd expect from a Coltrane record. John is on top form throughout his earlier &quot;sheets of sound&quot; firebreathing is still there but this is paired with the modal playing that dominated his later recordings. For me he catches just the right balance between the two. The contrast with the big band is also fascinating. I am also a huge fan of Coltrane on Soprano, I think he is if anything underated on this instrument as all the focus tends to be on his tenor magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although this is a big band record, the core of the album is still the Coltrane Quartet. At this time consisting of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Coltrane – soprano and tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McCoy Tyner – piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reggie Workman – bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elvin Jones – drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the album McCoy does McCoy things and he is instantly recognisable. He is such a huge part of the Coltrane sound of this era. He provides the &quot;dream like&quot; feel that allows John to really express himself. And of course he is no slouch himself, providing some killer piano solos throughout. Then of course we have the core of any band, the drummer. In this case Elvin Jones keeps things grooving and drives the music forward. For me one of the greatest drummers of all time. His voice is totally unique and again adds to the Coltrane sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With so few tracks it is hard to talk about &quot;top tracks&quot; so I have just embedded side 2 of the album in this post. To really appreciate this album, however, you should really listen from start to finish. I would recommend sticking to the &quot;original&quot; track listing rather than the extended re-issues as I don't think they add anything to the experience and really are just for the completist. If you have not heard &quot;Africa/Brass&quot; before you should definitely hunt down a copy, and if you have heard it before maybe it's time to give it another spin? As with many albums on this blog it is in the &quot;must listen&quot; category and well worth investing the time in.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dSJwSuekQO8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/064-Africa-Brass/Africa-Brass.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/064-Africa-Brass/Africa-Brass.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Time on my Hands and La Luna</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/time-on-my-hands-la-luna" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time on my Hands and La Luna" /><published>2021-07-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Time-on-my-Hands-La-Luna</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/time-on-my-hands-la-luna">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-07-10-Time-on-my-Hands-La-Luna.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/znoHziyUDHY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

For a bit of a change of pace on the blog this week we have a brand new roaster (to this blog): Sey Coffee ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seycoffee.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.seycoffee.com/&lt;/a&gt; ) from Brooklyn, NY. This is a roaster I have never sampled from before, importing coffee from the US is always problematic for those of us this side of the Atlantic. The shipping is often highly unpredictable and expensive, that fancy lot you were desperate to try could turn up months late (or not at all). Fortunately, Prufrock Coffee in London ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://prufrockcoffee.com/&quot;&gt;https://prufrockcoffee.com/&lt;/a&gt; ) have started a webstore and so we have access to some interesting roasters from all over the world with very little inconvenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sey have been on my &quot;to try&quot; list for quite a while and so I was happy to see their coffees become available. I already had to many bags of coffee so unfortunately I could only warrant a single bag to try. This of course raised the difficult question: which to try? Of the four or so on offer I opted for the Colombian &quot;La Luna&quot;, the selection criteria was fairly simple: it all came down to cultivar. This coffee is a 100% Pacamara lot. Pacamara is a cultivar that has very low yields and is extremely susceptible to pests/disease but has exceptional cup quality. It is one of my favourite cultivars but you do not see it very often. The coffee itself has undergone a pulped natural processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving straight in to the coffee itself. On the dry aroma: I'm getting honey and floral notes mostly but there is a feint fruity note in the background. It is not a particualrly &quot;loud&quot; coffee on the nose but it is certainly very appealling. Upon opening the bag for the first time I actually said: &quot;oh wow&quot; out loud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter coffee things start to get interesting. The coffee has a sugar-y sort of sweetness to it, an almost candyfloss type of vibe. However there is a floral lavendar type of note (although I may be specifying lavendar because the packaging is purple). As the cup cools the florals become more present and they are particularly noticable in the finish. The fruit notes on the nose are also present, I would describe them as a raspberry sharpness. The bag mentions tropical notes, and while I can notice them I'm not sure I would have gone for that as a descriptor without being prompted. The cup itself is very clean and the sharp acidity helps with this. The body and mouthfeel are pretty low, for me this is not problem but for those enjoying the chewier bigger coffees this might be a little thin for your tastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onto the espresso now: this one was remarkably easy to work with, it just requires a fine grind. If you want to make something approaching a ristretto out of this coffee you'll need a truly top end grinder - I could just about get a 1:2 out of it with my grinder on the edge of chirp. Given the relatively low body of this coffee however there isn't any harm in going a bit longer and my preference was a 1:2.75 ratio - this allowed some of the floral notes in the aftertaste to still be present. Going shorter and the cup became a bit more 1 dimensional (although still delicious). The flavour profile in the espresso is similar to the filter but more concentrated: the candyfloss sweetness is perhaps more like a caramel or honey and the raspberry note is a bit more prominent at the expense of the lavendar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall a kick-ass coffee from Sey, I'm glad I got to finally try some of their coffee and I'll be on the lookout for them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week I found myself digging out an old Scofield record from 1990: &quot;Time on my Hands&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/063-Time-on-my-Hands/Time-on-my-Hands.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Time on my Hands&quot; is a one of the first vinyl records I ever bought. I remember purchasing it quite clearly, at the time I was fairly new to jazz and still exploring. I already owned two of Sco's albums (&quot;A Go Go&quot; and &quot;Uberjam&quot;) which I had on CD which I really enjoyed but I hadn't heard anything else from him. &quot;Time on my Hands&quot; was a really pleasant surprise, it was totally different to the other Sco albums I had heard at that point and probably more &quot;traditional&quot;, it kicked off a bit of a Sco obsession for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Time on my Hands&quot; is interesting for a number of reasons: firstly it is John's first record on Blue Note which has some cachet in of itself. But it is also a &quot;super-group&quot; type recording with an all-star cast of musicians:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Scofield - guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Lovano - saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charlie Haden - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jack DeJohnette - drums

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/R8rpOUXpKYY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

With a lineup like this there is very little to go wrong! &quot;Time on my Hands&quot; is also the first recording with Sco and Lovano appearing together (to my knowledge) - and so the start of a successful partnership that produced many great records during the 90s. I believe this is what lifts &quot;Time on my Hands&quot; above other Sco records of the same era, while Sco's playing is always top-notch, the addition of Lovano seems to push Sco compositionally. The tunes on the album are much more recognisable and interesting than any on the previous Gramavision records. The interplay between John and Joe is also a joy to listen to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listening back to the album in 2021, things do sound a little dated however. The production itself has a very &quot;80s&quot; feel to it. In addition this was when all jazz guitarists for some inexplicable reason decided that they should leave their chorus pedals on 24/7 (to be fair it was not just jazz guitarists, but they are some of the worst offenders). The result is a very dated sound which may be difficult for some to deal with. The sound does fit the music however, the chorus adds an almost faux-leslie vibe to the guitar sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have listened to this album so many times over the years it is hard to pick out just a few tracks to talk about. One of the main strengths of the album is there is absolutely no filler, each tune is worthy of being there. This is in contrast to some of the prior Scofield records which have the odd fantastic tune but then some that don't quite live up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite tunes off the album is &quot;Flower Power&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). For me it really sums up John's compositional voice at the time, the theme is relatively simple but the way he plays with the timing is what really brings the piece alive. His lead playing shows off his &quot;laid-back&quot; approach that he further developed in later recordings. This is one of the few tracks where Joe Lovano does not appear however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A track where John and Joe certainly work together, however, is &quot;Wabash III&quot; (embedded above). This is a reimagining of &quot;Wabash&quot; that appeared a couple of years earlier on his &quot;Loud Jazz&quot; album (if anybody knows what happened to &quot;Wabash II&quot; I'd be very interested to hear!) Whereas the previous version had a rock snarl, &quot;Wabash III&quot; is much more sophisticated and very indicative of the 90s jazz movement towards more &quot;traditional&quot; sounds. The John/Joe interplay on this track is certainly one of the highlights of the album and you can see why they continued to collaborate. I also love Joe's solo on this track and I have stolen a number of licks from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My last pick is the closing track &quot;Fat Lip&quot; (embedded below). It's a tune with groove, swagger and rock attitude but also some sophistication. The sophistication of the compositions is a common theme throughout the album in general, the ideas are quite clever but they are done in a natural way and they are not thrown in your face in a &quot;look how clever I am&quot; way - I think this is why you can keep coming back to this album many years later. For the Scofield nerds out there: you can also hear the theme from &quot;I Don't Need No Doctor&quot; off his Ray Charles tribute album (and a riff John Mayer pinched for his own cover also).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a fan of John Scofield, or jazz guitar in general, and you haven't picked up a copy of &quot;Time on my Hands&quot; you really should. The tone and production may be a bit dated now, but it is worth sticking with it - you will be handsomely rewarded for it.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uBgenf00TsM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/063-Time-on-my-Hands/Time-on-my-Hands.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/063-Time-on-my-Hands/Time-on-my-Hands.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">From the Soul and Finca Momoto</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/from-the-soul-momoto" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From the Soul and Finca Momoto" /><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/From-the-Soul-Momoto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/from-the-soul-momoto">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-07-03-From-the-Soul-Momoto.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EOlDoVeru5c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week on the blog we are looking at another coffee from the folks at Crankhouse Coffee Roastery in Devon. You know you are in safe hands when purchasing from Crankhouse, they have a stellar reputation and for good reason. This time we have a rather special coffee called: &quot;Finca Momoto 'Beautiful Lot'&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee is from Panama and is a naturally processed Gesha cultivar. In of itself this is a reason to get excited, but in addition Finca Momoto is owned by Luis Miranda and Aliss Hartmann - the Hartmann name brings with a certain cachet in the coffee world. As you would expect this coffee is not exactly cheap, but all things considered I do not believe it is exorbitantly priced. In the recent past I bought 4 bags of coffee so terrible most of it had to be binned (to be clear not from Crankhouse, and the roasters in mention shall not be named) - so at the moment I do not mind paying a premium to get something I'm confident I'll enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also worth noting Crankhouse have recently changed their packaging and this is the first coffee I received in these clothes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/062-From-the-Soul/CH.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the design is a marked improvement from the previous design. I like the &quot;Um Bongo&quot; vibes the artwork has - and I should have really bought some Congolese coffee for the full effect!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But onto the coffee itself: the first thing to note is that this roast is light, I'd go as far as to say very light. I have no problem with this but it's something to keep in mind. On the dry aroma I get a perfumed floral bouquet (as one would expect from a Gesha) it is fairly delicate and it doesn't blow you away with intensity. In addition there is a slight hint of tropical fruit notes but they're not immediately apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a filter, prepared in my usual way, the first thing I noted down was: &quot;Oh Jeez... Beautiful lot indeed&quot;. Which just about sums it up, this coffee has an extremely elegant beauty to it. If you're after absolutely huge flavour surprising flavour notes this is probably not for you. Instead if you want a really clean and elegant cup with high complexity this is one worth buying. The flavour notes are typically &quot;Gesha&quot; in nature: apricots, honeysuckle and jasmine are the main ones. There are some faint more tropical notes of mango and passionfruit along with wild strawberries that come out to play at certain cup temperatures. As with many complex coffees this one enjoys being slightly cooler than you'd typically go. The acidity level is fairly low and the sweetness probably around a medium. The natural processing also seems to add some body and mouthfeel to the cup which is certainly enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso you would expect this to be a pain to dial in given the roast level, and in a way it is and in a way it's not. It's &quot;easy&quot; to dial in, in the sense that it's hard to make a bad tasting shot owing to the lower acidity levels. However it is &quot;hard&quot; to dial in to perfection, I found even a 0.1g change in dose can have quite a marked effect. In the end I settled for a 1:2.55 ratio pulled in about 22s. Reasonably long but reasonably quick. Going longer added more complexity but this coffee has some mouthfeel so I didn't want to lose that entirely. Going shorter made it difficult to distinguish individual flavour notes. In terms of flavours I would describe it as a perfumed apricot syrup. A really beautiful shot of espresso, but some of the complexity gets lost at this concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I expected this coffee was a knockoout and one I'll miss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I dug out a record from 1992: Joe Lovano's epic &quot;From the Soul&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/062-From-the-Soul/From-the-Soul.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me the early 90s represents a bit of a &quot;dead period&quot; for jazz. The synth-laden fusion sound of the 80s suddenly became seriously un-hip almost overnight (similar relationships with the synth exist in other musical genres too). The Jazz-Funk sound of MMW and the like had not taken off yet and so the period became a bit of a &quot;transition period&quot;. There were, however, a small group of musicians trying to push jazz back to a more &quot;traditional&quot; soundscape, and I consider Lovano to be one those at the forefront of that movement. Unfortunately many critics did not enjoy this, and in my opinion were unnecesarily harsh, claiming they were doing &quot;nothing new&quot;. &quot;From the Soul&quot; was one of the few albums that won over critics and fans alike during this period.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cbLfHSmkYO4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Looking at the lineup on the album it's not hard to see why it was so highly regarded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Lovano — tenor, alto, &amp;amp; soprano saxophones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michel Petrucciani — piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dave Holland — bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ed Blackwell — drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe is, of course, a master of the saxophone. Now regarded as one of the &quot;elder statesmen&quot; of jazz and for me personifies the &quot;jazz musician&quot; stereotype more than anybody else (and I mean that as a complement). His gravelly voice and &quot;hip&quot; vocabulary just become an extension of his music. He still tours quite widely to this day (current global situation excluded) and is one of the best live acts around, someone I always try and see if he is in town. While many sax players look for a very fluid legato style, Joe often favours a more &quot;herky-jerky&quot; staccato style which provides a lot of interesting rhythmic development in his solos. On &quot;From the Soul&quot; you hear glimpses of that style but there's not quite as much of it as on his more recent recordings. On the album you can hear inspiration from the prior masters of the instrument: Coltrane, Rollins and Coleman but there is a freshness and energy to his playing. It is easy to see why this was a landmark recording for Lovano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of Michel Petrucciani is interesting, one of the greatest pianists of his generation without a doubt. On this record (his only recording with Joe I believe) he plays in a very different style to what you would expect. Here he plays sparse lines and gives the music space to breath, for the Pertucciani historians certianly an interesting record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bass you have Dave Holland, one of my all-time favourite bass players. Another who is still touring heavily and well worth seeing live. I have a few stories about Dave's gigs but I'll save those until we feature one of Dave's albums. Here he just provides some great aggressive and hard hitting basslines and some unbelievable solos. Really all the musicians are on top form on this record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you'd expect from the name &quot;From the Soul&quot; this record features a number of ballads, but this is combined with more uptempo and energetic numbers. One such example is the track &quot;Evolution&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). This is perhaps the most &quot;Lovano&quot; of all the tracks and nobody would have batted an eyelid if this appeared on one of his latest releases. Blackwell's drumming provides the power to drive the track forward and Holland's basslines provide enough elasticity for Lovano to push and pull the meter at his leisure. For me one of the album highlights on an album which is all &quot;highlight&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the standards on the record is the ballad &quot;Portrait of Jennie&quot; (above) and with the slow tempo Joe shows why the album is called &quot;From the Soul&quot;. His tone is exquisite and he plays with just the right level of energy to keep things interesting while paying respect to the tune. When I think of the album this is instantly the track I think of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to pick a &quot;hit&quot; from the album I would likely pick &quot;Fort Worth&quot; (below). This is a track I have heard him play live multiple times and it always goes down well. It has the combination of having a good groove and an easily singable melody which is a surefire way to crafting a &quot;crowd favourite&quot;. Of course the playing is fantastic too which doesn't hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost every week I describe an album as a &quot;must listen&quot; for those interested in jazz, but that is the nature of featuring only one record a week - I get to focus on the true gems. This album is certainly worthy of the &quot;must listen&quot; status - especially since both Joe and Dave are still touring heavily and so these are musicians you can still get a chance to see live (the best way to consume jazz).

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NlRw0nPD3pk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/062-From-the-Soul/From-the-Soul.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/062-From-the-Soul/From-the-Soul.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s Mostly Residual and Diego Bermudez</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/mostly-residual-diego" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It's Mostly Residual and Diego Bermudez" /><published>2021-06-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-06-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Mostly-Residual-Diego</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/mostly-residual-diego">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-06-26-Mostly-Residual-Diego.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MaHeL5jyLDw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week we are sticking with the folks at Plot Roasting (far from their first appearance on this blog). In particular we are looking at their &quot;special edition&quot; coffee from Diego Bermudez. Diego, at this point, is a familiar name on this blog - his coffees have appeared multiple times in multiple different guises. He is widely regarded as one of the thought leaders of &quot;experimental processing&quot; and the quality in the cup speaks for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee this time is a Pink Bourbon cultivar. As you may recall from previous posts Pink Bourbon is a natural hybrid of Red and Yellow Bourbon cultivars. It has a very high cup quality but unfortunately it is quite hard to isolate and grow so it is much rarer than its red/yellow parents (and as such demands a premium). This particular coffee undergoes a stringent multistage process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At picking 90% ripe and 10% semi-ripe cherries are selected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherries are washed with sterilised water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First aerobic fermentation for 42 hours, 17 celcius. Cherries are whole and without water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second anaerobic fermentation 72 hours at 19 celcius. Cherries are whole and without water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherries de-pulped&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;26 hours drying in 37 celcius air with 3% humidity until reaching grain humidity of 10-11%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coffee stabilises in grainpro bags for 15 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you would expect from Diego; this is intricate and very controlled processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma I am hit with feint tropical fruit notes, caramels and sweetness. For such a &quot;crazy&quot; processing the dry aroma is quite restrained, but still inviting. As a filter brew the coffee is anything but restrained however. The cup is extremely complex and bursting with fruitiness. Some of the flavour notes include: strawberry, watermelon, lychee, grape, rhubarb, redcurrant and more. One of the notes listed on the label is: &quot;watermelon jolly ranchers&quot; and I struggle to come up with a better descriptor than that. The sweetness level of this coffee is very high and the acidity is medium-high which helps offset. I would describe the sweetness as a &quot;boiled sweet&quot; type sweetness alongside the fruity notes. The mouthfeel and body are fairly low but there's enough there to keep it interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso I find this coffee really shines, however. There is one small issue; the coffee requires an extremely fine grind. On my grinder I was just off chirp and could only get a 1:2.5 ratio consistently out of it - this is likely to be an espresso that would not perform too well without a quality grinder. Given the fine grind a lot of attention needs to be paid to puck prep, but as long as there's no obvious defect the shots are delicious and reasonably forgiving. The &quot;jolly ranchers&quot; tastenote from the filter gets amplified in its concetrated form and you have a sticky delicious boiled-sweet type shot. Personally a couldn't get enough of it (at time of writing I have enough for about 2 more shots left, I'll be sad to see it go). Some of the complexity of the filter cup is lost in the espresso but the punchiness and increased mouthfeel more than make up for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly both Plot and Diego Bermudez come up with another great coffee. I'm sure this will not be the last time they're featured here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the jazz side this week I dug out a record from 2006 - &quot;It's Mostly Residual&quot; by Cuong Vu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/061-Mostly-Residual/Mostly-Residual.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuong Vu is a Vietnamese-American trumpeter, he is best known for being part of the Pat Metheny Group during the early 00s - and this is certainly where I came across him, and why I picked up &quot;It's Mostly Residual&quot; back in 2006. While Pat Metheny Group records are, well, Pat Metheny-ish: Cuong's recordings take on a different vibe all together. He is more interested in textural soundscapes and he veers much further into the &quot;free&quot; side than you typically find on Metheny records. While I enjoy these sorts of explorations, many Metheny fans picking up a Vu record may be a little shocked and put off. It is perhaps for this reason that his albums maybe slightly overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &quot;It's Mostly Residual&quot; we have a quartet of musicians:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cuong Vu - trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stomu Takeishi - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ted Poor - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Frisell - guitar

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0_fUiPmKiq8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The first 3 members making up the &quot;Cuong Vu Trio&quot; who appear on many albums together, while guitarist Bill Frisell appears as a &quot;guest&quot; (for those interested in jazz guitar in 2016 there is also the &quot;Cuong Vu Trio Meets Pat Metheny&quot; which is interesting to compare the guitarists in identical setups). I make no apologies about being a huge Bill Frisell fan and Bill has appeared on the blog multiple times. On this album we have what I like to call &quot;Weird Bill&quot; - Bill has perhaps 3 main &quot;modes&quot; to work in: &quot;Country-influenced Bill&quot; is where most of his recent work lives, it is jazz fused with country/Americana. You then have &quot;Comping Bill&quot; where he accompanies other musicians and creates a soundscape to highlight their best qualities. Then you have &quot;Weird Bill&quot; where he plays really outside, uses lots of fuzz, feedback and noise. It is in complete contrast to his other modes which makes him so interesting as a musician. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw Bill in London promoting one of his &quot;Country Bill&quot; albums once, I was sat in the front row and beside me was a group of Americans. They were extremely obnoxious and talked through a lot of the set and were generally quite disrespectful. Just before the interval Bill was playing a standard/pop-tune off the album he was promoting - but at the end you could see the Bill smirk come out so you knew something was happening. He then played a couple of minutes of the craziest feedback &quot;noise-rock&quot; avant-garde music I've ever heard to finish off the first set. After Bill walked off stage I heard the Americans say: &quot;the first set was good, it's a shame about the technical issues at the end&quot; - I had to be very careful to make sure they couldn't hear me chuckling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the craziest tunes on the album is &quot;Expressions of a Neurotic Impulse&quot; (embedded at the start of this post), the main theme of which is a jarring, nervous, almost-punk-rock motif. It doesn't take long until it descends into full chaos with some manic drumming from Ted Poor and Bill Frisell making full use of his pedal board. At first listen it may appear quite &quot;random&quot; without much forethought - however the more you listen the more you get out of it and you can notice the many layers to the soundscape they create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another highlight is the track &quot;Brittle Like Twigs&quot; (above). While slightly less crazy that &quot;Expressions of a Neurotic Impulse&quot; still has its fair share of free moments. It is often difficult to blend the outside free ideas with swing or groove but I feel &quot;Brittle Like Twigs&quot; is a great example of this done well. It also features a killer &quot;Weird Bill&quot; solo at the end

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XaTZHhbzhIE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

With &quot;outside&quot; music it can often get overwhelming if the tempo and energy is high for the entire album. The real skill in constructing albums like this is to get the balance right betweenup tempo and lower tempo. One of the lower-tempo highlights on &quot;It's Mostly Residual&quot; is the track &quot;Patchwork&quot; (above). This appears beside &quot;Expressions of a Neurotic Impulse&quot; and the change in mood is striking. It starts off as something you could imagine hearing on a &quot;Country Bill&quot; album, but as it moves forward creates more of an &quot;uneasy&quot; feeling and it's a joy to hear the main theme slowly develop in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an album like &quot;It's Mostly Residual&quot; it's best to hear it in its entirety and picking out individual tracks like this does not really do it justice (I could have easily picked the other tracks to highlight - for example the New Orleans influenced crescendo to &quot;Chitter Chatter&quot;). So if you've liked what you've heard so far I'd strongly suggest finding a copy of &quot;It's Mostly Residual&quot; and giving it a few listens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/061-Mostly-Residual/Mostly-Residual.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/061-Mostly-Residual/Mostly-Residual.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Una Mas and Icon 6</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/una-mas-icon-6" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Una Mas and Icon 6" /><published>2021-06-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-06-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Una-Mas-Icon-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/una-mas-icon-6">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-06-19-Una-Mas-Icon-6.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TDETNk20Vkc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week marks the 6th installment of the Plot Roasting &quot;Icon&quot; series - as you may remember this is a &quot;premium&quot; coffee series showcasing some of the rarest and highest quality coffees available today. This time however things are a little different: in previous installments we have had Gesha cultivars and crazy processing methods, this time things are much more &quot;pedestrian&quot;. When not relying on the unobtainium cultivars or fermentation science experiment processes there is very little place to hide and so I'm hoping for a fantastic cup here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee is from San Ignacio, Peru - an origin I've found has improved quality-wise significantly over the last few years. The farm is called &quot;Fidel Huancas&quot; and the coffee itself won 4th place in the &quot;Cup of Excellence&quot;. For those that don't know the &quot;cup of excellence&quot; competitions are sort of like a &quot;michelin star&quot; review for coffee. A panel of &quot;expert&quot; tasters compare many coffees back to back and try and find the best coffee a country has produced in that given year. Those that win awards can typically command a much higher price for their coffee. It's worth remembering that although cup of excellence is quite broad (there are 13 countries with cup of excellence competitions) it does not cover every origin and so some really great coffees miss awards for geographical reasons alone. It's also worth keeping in mind that what professional tasters look for need not be what you actually enjoy drinking (along with many other caveats relating to shipping times, roaster skills, etc.) That being said I do tend to enjoy the cup of excellence coffees I have tried in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of cultivar we have a yellow Caturra and the processing is washed. As I said a fairly standard cultivar and processing, which means the coffee has to be exceptional to justify the price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with previous Icon coffees this is a relatively small bag (150g) so this will be an espresso free week on the blog. Normal service will resume next week (I have another coffee dedicated to espresso alongside the Icon and it's a peach).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the dry aroma I get soft and delicate floral notes of jasmine and honeysuckle.  Supporting this is a honey note that gives a &quot;sweet&quot; note to the aroma. It is fairly delicate on the nose and is not the punchiest coffee you'll ever sniff. Once brewed into a filter coffee you have an extremely complex cup. The peach and apricot notes are very prominent as is the jasmine like floral backdrop. The acidity level of this coffee is what I'd describe as &quot;just enough&quot; - it's not one I'd describe as particularly high acidity but it is crisp enough to keep you coming back for more. As the cup cools it transforms, this is one that is very sensitive to temperature. I strongly recommend drinking from a very thin walled cup so it has chance to cool down so you can experience all it has to offer. During the cool down phase I noted down the following descriptors: bramble, fig, redcurrant, lime, and I could probably think of a few more. In terms of body and mouthfeel it is relatively low and the sweetness level is quite high but not overpowering. Overall a very balanced cup, and despite the complexity it is a very easy drink. It is one you can also just sit and enjoy without the flavours becoming too distracting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As has been the case with all the Icons so far; this has been a knockout coffee and I look forward to next month's offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is customary on &quot;Icon&quot; weeks I've selected some iconic jazz to go alongside. This week it's another record from the Blue Note back catalogue from 1963: &quot;Una Mas&quot; by Kenny Dorham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/060-Una-Mas/Una-Mas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Most underrated&quot; is a contentious label in the jazz world, no matter who you pick out you can claim somebody else is even more underrated than them. But with Kenny Dorham you may have a decent case for making that argument. He has appeared on many of the greatest recordings in Blue Note history (both under his name and as a sideman) yet still lacks the acolades and &quot;prestige&quot; of some of his peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kenny started off as an active member on the be-bop scene, being part of the original Jazz Messengers as well as playing alongside Charlie Parker, Thelonious Monk, Sonny Rollins and Clifford Brown as well as the big bands of Dizzie Gillespie and Lionel Hamlityon (amongst others). He is perhaps best known for his post-bop work on Blue Note in the 1960s and in particular his partnership with Joe Henderson with whom he appeared a numerous records under either of their names or as sidemen under others names. The Dorham-Henderson partnership is perhaps once of the greatest in jazz history - in a very short period of time they managed to record large number of &quot;classic&quot; albums (with &quot;Una Mas&quot; being one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major part of Kenny's sound and songwriting style (at least during the 1960s) was the Latin and Cuban influences to his music. Latin and Cuban jazz have their own histories, but what Kenny managed to do so seemlessly was combine this with the language of be-bop. In this area he was somewhat of a pioneer with many taking influence from his compositions. The collaboration with Joe Henderson certainly helped in this regard given he was no slouch with regards to Latin influences either. In fact Kenny's most famous composition, &quot;Blue Bossa&quot;, appeared on the Joe Henderson album &quot;Page One&quot; from 1963. &quot;Blue Bossa&quot; has since become a standard in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to &quot;Una Mas&quot; itself, the lineup needs no introduction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kenny Dorham - trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joe Henderson - tenor saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herbie Hancock - piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Butch Warren - bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tony Williams - drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say this often in these &quot;icon&quot; series recordings: but any one of these musicians could be headline artists in their own right. Part of the joy of these recordings is hearing artists like Herbie Hancock be a &quot;mere&quot; sideman on a record. On &quot;Una Mas&quot; it never once feels like any one musician is trying to steal the limelight, they're all working to push the music to a better place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the only downside to &quot;Una Mas&quot; is its brevity: it clocks in at only 32 minutes in its original 3-track form (but feels even shorter), but thankfully an additional track was added in 1987 to bring it up to a 37 minute run time. But that should not be a reason to overlook the recording, every second is essentially a &quot;highlight&quot; and there is not a moment of filler on the album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album kicks off with the title track &quot;Una Mas&quot; (embedded at the start of this post), which is a built around a hard hitting Bossa-Nova groove. The main itself is punchy and catchy, one you might find yourself humming for days afterwards without realising. Then of course there are 3 killer solos from Dorham, Henderson and Hancock respectively. Given the tune's structure it is somewhat of a &quot;blank canvas&quot; and the improvisers can take it into whatever direction they choose. Dorham opts to stick to the Bossa-Nova vibe with the occassional use of a searing blues lick. Henderson does Henderson things and throws in some outside lines and more hard-bop vocabulary while Hancock sticks to his typical sophisticated harmonic style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second track on the album &quot;Straight Ahead&quot; (embedded below), as the name suggests, is a more straight ahead hard-bop romp. With a line-up like this at this time it would be a shame not hear them stretch their legs and that is certainly what they do here - it is essentially a canonical recording from the Blue Note hard-bop era. The rest of the album is comprised of &quot;Sao Paulo&quot; another Bossa influenced track but mellower than the chaotic &quot;Una Mas&quot; opener. The reissues of the album then feature the standard &quot;If Ever I Would Leave You&quot; by Loewe and Lerner, a great example of a hard-bop take on a ballad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all the &quot;icon series&quot; albums this one is &quot;essential listening&quot; for any jazz fan, especially those who enjoy Blue Note recordings. You can't go wrong with any of the Dorham/Henderson recordings from this period.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IcsgGTDNbUk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/060-Una-Mas/Una-Mas.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/060-Una-Mas/Una-Mas.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Squint and Austratt</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/squint-austratt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Squint and Austratt" /><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Squint-Austratt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/squint-austratt">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-06-12-Squint-Austratt.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bFRVK_1o2cU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

The blog is back after a short 1 week hiatus: over the past couple of weeks I had being trying some &quot;new&quot; (to me) roasters and the quality level was frankly quite low. I'm not in the business of writing negative reviews of coffee roasters, especially given the current economic climate for coffee companies generally, so took the week off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully this week we're back with some high quality coffee goodness - we have another installment of my Kaffebox subscription. This time featuring a pair of filter roast coffees from Norwegian roasters: Austrått Kaffebrenneri. I have to admit I had never heard of these guys before (part of the joy of the Kaffebox subscription) so was very much looking forward to giving them a go. Their website (in Norwegian) does not give much away but shows they took 3rd place in the Norwegian coffee roasting championship in 2018 and 2nd placce in 2020 - so a sign they know what they're doing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may recall with my Kaffebox subscription I dedicate one of the coffees to filter and one to espresso duties - this week the decision was made completely at random (so try not to read into any choices here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the filter side I opted for the Tanzanian &quot;JKT Itende&quot; - the cultivars appear to be N39, Bourbon and Kent (the latter being a variation on Typica that is more resistant to leaf-rust) and I believe the coffee is washed. Off the dry aroma I get berry notes mostly, it is fairly punchy but not an aroma bomb. As a filter the first thing I noticed was how clean the cup is (partly due to some particularly &quot;dirty&quot; cups in the preceeding weeks). The flavour profile consists of: blackcurrants/blackberries, apricots and good hit of honey sweetness. The cup is very sweet and juicy with just enough acidity to not be cloying. The mouthfeel is fairly thin and the aftertaste is quite intense but not particularly long-lived. It is not a super-complex cup of coffee compared to some, but it is certainly very enjoyable and it is easy to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have a Guatemalan &quot;Finca el Regalito&quot; - the cultivars are Caturra and Bourbon and again it is a washed coffee (I'm assuming &quot;vasket&quot; is &quot;washed&quot; in Norwegian). The dry aroma gives off a honey type quality, again it is punchy but there is not huge sillage. The roast level on this coffee is visibly very light which often equates to an espresso that is tough to dial in. That is not the case here however, it is suprisingly forgiving. For the past week I have been experimenting with the B-Plus screen (full review coming later) so was adjusting my grind and recipe quite often and I didn't end up with a single shot less than good. I found a 1:2.5 sort of range to be the best for this coffee with the temp at full whack. The flavour notes I pick up are dried fruits, baking spices, brown sugar and cocoa. It makes for a syrupy and sticky shot with very high levels of sweetness. The acidity is somewhat muted which makes it very easy to drink. Again not the most complex shot I've ever had but very enjoyable and easy to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall another good installment from Kaffebox - Austrått will definitely be one I'll keep an eye out for in future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week we are taking a first look at the &quot;hot off the press&quot; album from Julian Lage: &quot;Squint&quot; - since this was released yesterday (11th June 2021) this will be a &quot;first listen&quot; review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/059-Squint/Squint.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Julian's second appearance on the blog, in a prior post we looked at &quot;Love Hurts&quot; which was quite a restrianed look at ballads and standards (mostly). &quot;Squint&quot;, Julian's first release on Blue Note Records, takes a different approach: it is wilder, more ambitious, more virtuosic, freer and features (mostly) original compositions.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Jx_CuxesjmU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

I have been a fan of Julian's playing for a long time, what really impresses me is his fluidity and ease over the instrument. Listening/watching Julian it never seems like he is trying particularly hard, the guitar just seems an extension to his body and there's no blocker in the &quot;brain-guitar&quot; pathway. Sure, you might be able to find those with more technical &quot;chops&quot; but few seem as comfortable playing the instrument. This means that even when playing technically or harmonically complicated pieces he is still able to have &quot;feel&quot; and tell a story through his playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Squint&quot; is also the first recording to feature Julian's new signature Collings 470JL (I believe - at least the first since the guitar has been available) - based around a Gretsch duojet style guitar it marks a depature from the telecaster (or technically nachocaster) he has been known for. The change in tonality is quite evident - there is certainly more of a nasal quality to the break-up sounds and the cleans are a bit cleaner. He has also (in places) opted for more reverb and tremolo than in the past. Personally I'm more a fan of the telecaster sound, but even so then tones on &quot;Squint&quot; are still better than 99% of jazz electric guitar sounds out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the choice cuts on the album include the opener: &quot;Etude&quot; (embedded at the start of this post). As the name would suggest this is a solo guitar piece, somewhat designed as a technical &quot;practice&quot; piece. At a relatively short 2m27 it still packs a lot in - it could take a blog post in itself to analyse everything here. The main &quot;theme&quot; takes cues from Bach and classical music more generally, but this is blended with voice-leading jazz, blues and even the odd rock accents. The walk-down just after the main melody is a mind-bending lick, the use of open strings in such a line is just crazy. Watching him play you would be forgiven for thinking he was playing something trivial, it's honestly quite disheatening for the guitar players out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a solo record however and Lage is joined by Dave King on drums and Jorge Roeder on the bass. The whole album has an intimate almost &quot;jazz club&quot; feel and comes across a bit like a live performance - owing to the interaction between the musicians. This is particularly apparent on the track &quot;Familiar Flower&quot; (above) which is one of the freer pieces on the album and takes clear nods from Ornette Coleman. A part of Julian's playing that really comes out here is how easily he can switch from the most outside free ideas to more inside groove-based playing. It never feels like he's playing outside &quot;for the sake of it&quot;.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y10ZbXSW1Go&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Two other tracks I want to make a note of: firstly the revisiting of &quot;Day and Age&quot;, a track that appeared on his 2015 album &quot;World's Fair&quot;. On the previous album it appeared as a solo acoustic piece and became a bit of a &quot;signature tune&quot; for Lage. On &quot;Squint&quot; we are treated to an electric trio version - it takes on a whole new personality, slightly more downbeat and contemplative (perhaps reflecting a change in Julian's personality in the 6 years between recordings). Undoubtedly there will be comparisons to Bill Frisell given the &quot;Americana&quot; vibe to the piece but Julian certainly has his own voice here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other track I want to highlight is the beautiful rendition of Johnny Mandel's &quot;Emily&quot;. Julian released a video playing a solo version of this tune during the start of lockdown last year (video above). This is one of my favourite ballads and Julian's version is up there with my favourite renditions. I think as a guitarist one of the hardest tasks to do is to play a &quot;simple&quot; ballad like this and keep it entertaining yet respectful to the source, many others would have layered reharmonization over reharmonization to the point of being unrecognizable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tunes selected here are some of my initial highlights but &quot;Squint&quot; is full of gems. &quot;Boo's Blues&quot; for example being a swinging blues with a hint of Monk to it. Although there isn't really a &quot;lead single&quot; to this album, perhaps the most accessible is &quot;Saint Rose&quot; (below) - if this doesn't become a staple of Julian's live shows from now on I'll be very surprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &quot;review&quot; just reflects my intial impressions after a few listens of &quot;Squint&quot; - I'm sure there's much more to uncover hidden away in these tracks. I'd strongly suggest tracking down a copy and giving it a go.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v21st5PcUOU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/059-Squint/Squint.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/059-Squint/Squint.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sound of Summer Running and Koppi</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/summer-running-koppi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sound of Summer Running and Koppi" /><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Summer-Running-Koppi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/summer-running-koppi">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-05-29-Summer-Running-Koppi.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/l8iNkhmoALs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This blog post marks the next installment of my KaffeBox subscription. This time it features another of my favourite roasters: Koppi - located in Helsingborg, Sweden. They are perhaps one of the best known of the Scandinavian roasters and are highly acclaimed (and for good reason). I beleive they are also the originators of &quot;coffee tonic&quot; - a shot of espresso poured into a chilled tonic water with ice. With summer &lt;em&gt;potentially&lt;/em&gt; around the corner it is a great choice for a drink on a hot day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may remember my KaffeBox subscription consists of 2 bags each of 125g of coffee. I split these one on espresso duty and one on filter duty, so that I get enough to dial in the espresso properly. This week I selected based on origin, I went for the origin I typically find easiest to dial in for the espresso and the other for the filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with the filter we have a Colombian coffee &quot;Finca El Prado&quot;. The cultivar is Caturra and the coffee has been wet fermented followed by a full wash and raised bed drying. Diving right into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma there is an unmistakable strawberry note to this coffee, but this plays supporting cast to a sugar-syrup or light caramel note. As you would expect the roast level is fairly light here. In the cup the strawberry meets many other red berries: redcurrants, raspberries, cherry, you name it. It's a very fruity cup. There is a sharpness there too, the bag lists passionfruit but I would describe it more as a tart raspberry quality personally. The cup has a medium body and is quite juicy in its quality. It is definitely more on the complex end of things and the various red fruits come to the forefront as it cools. As I would expect from Koppi: a really well executed and tasty cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the espresso side we have a Costa Rican &quot;La Lia&quot; - a Catuai cultivar that has been fully washed. I am a big fan of Costa Rican coffee in espresso, I find it to typically be extremely forgiving and it's very difficult to mess up too much. This is true of this coffee also, the grind setting needed major adjustment from my previous espresso so my first shot had a 60s pull time - it was still delicious, albeit very intense. After dialing in I settled for a normale shot: 1:2 in 28s. This seemed to be the best compromise between mouthfeel and clarity for me. In terms of flavour note the predominant note is nuts, in particular hazelnuts and almonds. Alongside there is a crisp apple type acidity that cuts through and a stone fruit note. Overall it is not the most complex espresso in the world but it is very easy to drink, it's a coffee for when you just want a coffee. Again the execution is top level and it is truly a top class espresso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside Koppi this week, since London has had its first glimpses of summer, I have been listening to the 1997 release from Marc Johnson: &quot;The Sound of Summer Running&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/058-Sound-of-Summer/Sound-of-Summer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marc Johnson is a name that might not be instantly recognisable to many, he is not a household name and hasn't really had many &quot;hit&quot; records under his own name. However his back catalogue speaks for itself, having featured on albums from: Bill Evans, John Scofield, Lyle Mays, John Abercrombie and Stan Getz (plus many more). Having such an illustrious side-man career has clearly influenced his playing where you can hear the aforementioned (along with others) heavily in his playing.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/skdwbRI2eXk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&quot;The Sound of Summer Running&quot; (named after a Ray Bradbury story) is perhaps one of Johnson's best known recordings as a band-leader. Most likely due to the truly stellar cast of musicians on show:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marc Johnson – double bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Frisell – electric and acoustic guitars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pat Metheny – electric and acoustic guitars, 42-string Pikasso guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joey Baron – drums, tambourine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;dual guitar&quot; setup is likely to be influenced by prior work with John Abercrombie who often makes use of such line-ups. It is not often you get to hear 2 of the jazz guitar titans playing together. It is also rare to hear Pat Metheny play a supporting role, aside from a few obvious exceptions in his early career, he is typically in the &quot;limelight&quot;. On &quot;The Sound of Summer Running&quot; we see a different side to Metheny's playing that we don't often see. Then of course you have Bill Frisell, for my money one of the best guitar compers in the business. Hearing his interplay with Metheny is a joy on this album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the album is quite a restrained affair, it is not so much about huge chops or crazy harmonizations but more about creating a &quot;mood&quot;. While the Metheny and Frisell influences are on show it is really all about Johnson's voice as a composer: 7 out of 10 tunes being penned by him (with Frisell taking 2 of the remaining credits and Metheny 1). The &quot;Summer&quot; feel is quite clear throughout and it's an album that is very hard to dislike, it's a bit of a mystery why it is not more popular than it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some choice tracks include the opener &quot;Faith in You&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) which features a Metheny-ish main melody. The contrast in Metheny's and Frisell's solos is particularly interesting, Metheny being more at home but Frisell doing Frisell things. &quot;Union Pacific&quot; is another highlight (above) and perhaps the most &quot;straight-ahead&quot; with a strong swing and swagger. The main melody being played by Metheny and Frisell in unison is one of most memorable moments on the album for me and not something you get to hear very often.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/T8BESnWlzoo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

My last pick is the Frisell tune &quot;Ghost Town&quot; - one of his signature tunes. Getting to hear Metheny solo on this piece is a joy, the structure and changes are very far away from a typical Metheny tune so it is very interesting to see how he approaches it. Of course Frisell is right at home and works his magic on the tune. This version is as good as any of the versions on Frisell's own albums in my view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &quot;The Sound of Summer Running&quot; might not be considered &quot;essential&quot; listening by traditional standards, it is well worth hunting down a copy if you're after a no nonsense album that can fit into your day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/058-Sound-of-Summer/Sound-of-Summer.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/058-Sound-of-Summer/Sound-of-Summer.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Friday Afternoon in the Universe and Jairo Arcila</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/friday-afternoon-jairo-arcila" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Friday Afternoon in the Universe and Jairo Arcila" /><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Friday-Afternoon-Jairo-Arcila</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/friday-afternoon-jairo-arcila">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-05-22-Friday-Afternoon-Jairo-Arcila.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9zz-WKAlTvQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

On the blog this week we're heading back to Exeter and the folks at Crankhouse Coffee. A couple of weeks ago we looked at a rather elegant Ecuadorian cup from them, this week we are going much wilder with a coffee from Colombia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee is called Jairo Arcila Villarazo Natural (EF2) - the farm is located in Quindio and the cultivar is Castillo. The suffix EF2 refers to &quot;extended fermentation 2 extra days&quot;. As you may have guessed by now we're looking at a highly fermeneted natural coffee here. The process is described as: an initial 24 hours dry anaerobic fermentation. Following this the cherries are placed into bags and stored at 22 celcius (through use of a water tank) for an additional 60 hours. The cherries then dry on raised beds until an 18% moisture content before going back in the bags for 50 hours and dried on raised beds until the moisture is 10.5%. The sheer extent of the fermentation suggests this is going to be a very funky cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving right into the coffee itself: on the dry aroma you get that unmistakable &quot;natural funk&quot; - it always reminds me of black forest gateaux, bruised fruits and sherry. To me this is not a &quot;tropical fruit&quot; type natural/anaerobic - more of a deeper boozy sort of natural. I do not typically go for these sorts of coffees but it is always nice to mix things up every now and again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Served as a filter using my usual method: the first thing to note is that although this coffee is fairly high on the funk-o-meter it still has a good deal of clarity in the cup. The finish is long lasting but is fairly &quot;clean&quot; in nature. For me the major flavour notes are: bruised blueberries and cherry brandy. There is also an acidity that almost cuts through I would describe it as perhaps like a pink grapefruit, it is fairly subtle but it's just present enough to stop the cup being too cloying. As you'd expect the sweetness is very high and there is quite a lot of body - although it's not one you'll have to chew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an espresso this coffee really shines. The sheer amount of sweetness means you can really cut back on the ratio to make the most of the mouthfeel. I found good results down to around 1:1.5 - knocking on the door of being a ristretto. In such a concentrated shot you get huge intensity and a luscious body, it almost feels like a dessert. Most coffees I tend to go for don't perform well as ristretto (in my opinion at least) so it is nice to come across one every now and again. The flavour notes are much the same as in the filter although the acidity disappears and the boozy notes are amplified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although outside of my typical coffee preferences I highly enjoyed drinking this one. It also goes to show the variety on offer at Crankhouse that you can have a super polite and refined washed Ecuadorian and this all-aboard-the-funky-bus natural Colombian from one roaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the jazz this week it feels only right to go down the funky route. I have chosen an old favourite of mine: the 1995 release &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot; by Medeski, Martin and Wood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/057-Friday-Afternoon/Friday-Afternoon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've mentioned this a few times on the blog but Medeski, Martin and Wood (MMW) were one of the first jazz acts I got into heavily. Before them I had mostly been listening to the &quot;classics&quot; by (mostly) musicians who had passed long before I started listening to them. With MMW there was a band writing and performing new music who I could see live and I was all for it. They were also one of the first bands I can remember forming a new &quot;scene&quot;. They were pretty much the first of the 90s/00s wave of bands lugging wurlitzers and hammonds around gigs and managed to capture a &quot;cool&quot; younger crowd with live shows focussed on dancing and partying as opposed to the typical quieter and more respectful jazz audiences. This of course spun up many copy-cat acts trying to capture the same vibe but none felt as authentic as MMw.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b1-5jmuUkvM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

Many years ago MMW were in fact one of the first acts I ever saw at Ronnie Scott's - but unfortunately it was not the best gig I've ever been to. Their setlist was pitfully short (max 30 minutes) and they didn't seem to be enjoying their time playing. It was quite a devastating gig given how much I was looking forward to seeing them live. Thankfully this was a one off and I saw them many times since and have not been disappointed (a gig with John Scofield was a particular highlight).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's interesting to see where &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot; sits within the MMW discography. Their first album &quot;Notes from the Underground&quot; does not feature the trademark organ sounds, it is a good album but does not &quot;feel&quot; like the MMW we know now. The second album &quot;It's a Jungle in Here&quot; begins to feature more organ sounds but is still heavily rooted in funk (of the Sly and the Family Stone type). Then came &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot; - here the organ sounds are expanded and the band started to play with the avant-garde. The avant-garde became a key component of the MMW sound, they would often switch from hard hitting funk to some of the most out there music in the blink of an eye. It's for that reason I consider &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot; the album were MMW hit their stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest &quot;hit&quot; off the album is &quot;Chubb Sub&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) - it showcases the MMW funk grooves in full swing. John Medeski providing the hip organ sounds, Billy Martin playing with the laid-back rock grooves and Chris Wood holding the whole thing together with some really restrained upright bass lines. Some of the MMW avant-garde craziness is shown on the short track &quot;House Mop&quot; (above) - despite being fairly free form there is still a sense of groove. The avant-garde is something they lent into heavily with their later work with John Zorn. You also have pieces such as &quot;Last Chance to Dance Trance (Perhaps)&quot; (below) - here the focus is more on dancing/partying with a heavy latin influence to the meter. 

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qxSFlooNldQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

With such a variety of tracks on &quot;Friday Night in the Universe&quot;, the album becomes a microcosm of both &quot;old&quot; and &quot;new&quot; MMW. It in some sense bridges the gap between much of their other work. It is an album I often find myself coming back to and one well worth hunting down if you have not yet heard it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/057-Friday-Afternoon/Friday-Afternoon.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/057-Friday-Afternoon/Friday-Afternoon.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Blues and Abstract Truth and Icon 5</title><link href="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/blues-abstract-truth-icon-5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Blues and Abstract Truth and Icon 5" /><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/Blues-Abstract-Truth-Icon-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jazzcoffeestuff.com/blues-abstract-truth-icon-5">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2021-05-15-Blues-Abstract-Truth-Icon-5.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/44DfWE0gatQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

This week marks the return of the Plot Roasting Icon series. As you may recall this a coffee subscription consisting of &quot;unobtainium&quot; type coffees - some of the rarest and most sought after on the market. This installment is no different; it features another Gesha coffee this time from Diego Bermudez in Colombia. You may recall this name from the Assembly limited edition coffee from a few weeks back - this time we have a Gesha cultivar however. As with the forementioned coffee this weeks Icon coffee undergoes a complex multistage process. First the cherries are washed with sterilised water to reduce contamination. The whole cherries are then held in sealed tanks for 60 hours at 18 celcius, they are then depulped before entering a second anaerobic fermentation phase for 36 hours at 18 celcius. The coffee then undergoes a &quot;thermal shock&quot; wash procedure; first washing at 35 celcius then 12 celcius. This is followed by a controlled drying procedure for 29 hours at 35 celcius with relative humidity 25% until the grain humidity reaches 10-11%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving right in to the coffee itself: on the nose I am getting honey and caramel notes off the dry aroma. Like many of the Gesha cultivar coffees I've had it is a relatively restrained affair and there is not a huge sillage. Moving onto the filter: the first thing to strike me is just how complex this cup is. There is so much going on in the cup. It actually benefits from being consumed at a relatively cool temperature, at the higher temperatures the flavours can overwhelm. In terms of flavour notes there are big perfumed florals: lavendar, violet, jasmine - you name it. Alongside are the typical earl-grey tea type notes one would expect also. I've also picked out stone fruit notes along with citrus (most notably grapefruit). The finish is very very sweet, reminding me of sherbet. This is a coffee to savour and ponder over each individual note, there is a lot to discover in this cup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to a bit of a mix up I actually ended up with twice as much of this coffee as usual (300g) - which means for the first time I am able to try one of the Icons as an espresso. With a coffee this expensive it can be a little nerve-wracking to pull shots from, any sink-job dialing in shots are literally money down the drain! Fortunately however, this coffee required only minimal tweaks from the previous espresso I had been serving. I enjoyed this one at a 1:2.5 ratio in 28s with the machine temperature at full whack. As you'd expect this makes a great espresso too. There is one overriding flavour note I wrote down: Haribo Fangtastic sweets! There is a definite sourness to the espresso, but in a good way - not an indication of underextraction way. Especially paired with the syrupy sugar sweetness, it has a real &quot;sweet and sour&quot; thing going on which is really cool. I can't remember having an espresso with this sort of profile before so it was very enjoyable. That being said the complexity does get kind of lost so I do think filter is the best way to enjoy this coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet again Plot are killing it with the Icon series - very much looking forward to what the future brings with this subscription!

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SlkkQiZ-gV4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As is customary on Icon series posts: on the jazz side we are looking at an iconic album. This time around we are going back to 1961 on Impulse records: Oliver Nelson and &quot;The Blues and Abstract Truth&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/056-Blues-Abstract/Blues-Abstract.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oliver Nelson is one of the many jazz artists who died far too young at just 43 years old. It's perhaps for this reason his name is not as recognisable as others from his era. As a result &quot;The Blues and Abstract Truth&quot; is often an album overlooked by the jazz newbie who will not discover it until much later in their jazz journey (and kick themselves for not finding it earlier). To those in the know it is one of the most respected albums from the post-bop era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nelson is a saxophonist and clarinetist, on &quot;Blues&quot; he appears playing tenor and alto sax, however he is perhaps best known as a composer or arranger. &quot;The Blues and Abstract Truth&quot; offers a peek into his compositional sensibilities, with just a 7 piece band the tunes are not quite as expansive and experimental as some of his later works. He was also an acomplished composer outside of the jazz idiom having composed for classical and chamber groups along with TV and film scores. It would have been very interesting to see where he headed artistically had he had more time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lineup on &quot;The Blues and Abstract Truth&quot; is quite impressive in itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freddie Hubbard – trumpet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eric Dolphy – alto saxophone, flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oliver Nelson – tenor saxophone, alto saxophone &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Barrow – baritone saxophone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Evans – piano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul Chambers – bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roy Haynes – drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A true superstar lineup, each more than worthy of a blog post in their own right. For me part of the charm of this album is the contrast in the soloing: Hubbard offering up his usual powerful exuberance, Nelson being more introverted and contemplative and Dolphy being Dolphy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;standout&quot; track on the album is the opener &quot;Stolen Moments&quot; (embedded at the start of this post) which has subsequently become a standard in its own right. With so many horns they are able to produce some very rich and wide reaching chord voicings that add to the overall feel of the piece. Perhaps the standout however is the flute solo by Dolphy - an integral part of the recording and highly memorable. Another Dolphy highlight is in the 4th track &quot;Yearnin&quot; (below) where he presents the most &quot;outside&quot; playing on the album with his solo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another standout piece (and one of my favourites) is the second track: &quot;Hoe Down&quot; (above), based on the theme from Aaron Copland's &quot;Rodeo&quot;. The genius of this track is that it sets you up thinking you're in for a corny American folk piece before descending into some of the finest post-bop soloing you'll ever hear. Hubbard's solo is the one that really stands out for me on this one.

&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0tNZ6AG0xWc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

As with all the albums featured in the Icon series: this one is a &quot;must listen&quot; if you are a jazz fan. Be sure to pick up a copy through whatever medium you listen to your music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Lewis Cole (2021)</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/056-Blues-Abstract/Blues-Abstract.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://github.com/jazzcoffeestuff/blog/raw/master/images/056-Blues-Abstract/Blues-Abstract.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>